[
  {
    "unique_id": "010101",
    "question": "What is the central tenet of economics in a manner that necessitates a deeper comprehension?",
    "answer": "Scarcity",
    "explanation": "The primary focus of economics is scarcity and how societies choose to allocate scarce resources to meet their wants and needs",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Maximizing profits for businesses",
    "option_b": "Solving political challenges",
    "option_c": "Scarcity",
    "option_d": "Increasing global trade",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010102",
    "question": "What is the key challenge faced by economies in fulfilling the needs of their population?",
    "answer": "Inefficient supply networks",
    "explanation": "The challenges of fulfilling the needs of the population and mentions the importance of having a proper distribution network for goods and services produced",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Lack of natural resources",
    "option_b": "Inefficient supply networks",
    "option_c": "Competition from other economies",
    "option_d": "Limited production capacity",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010103",
    "question": "Which economist is credited with the work \"The Wealth of Nations\" and is considered the originator of the classical school of economics?",
    "answer": "Adam Smith",
    "explanation": "This  attributes \"The Wealth of Nations\" to Adam Smith and highlights his contribution to the classical school of economics",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "John Maynard Keynes",
    "option_b": "Karl Marx",
    "option_c": "Adam Smith",
    "option_d": "Milton Friedman",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010104",
    "question": "Economics studies the economic activities of mankind, which involve __________, livelihood, occupation, wage, employment, etc",
    "answer": "Profit & Loss",
    "explanation": "Economic activities are those that encompass concepts like profit, loss, livelihood, occupation, wage, and employment",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "P,ro,fi,t & L,os,s",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010105",
    "question": "Which factor contributes to the diversity in economic outcomes among different countries following similar economic policies?",
    "answer": "Variability in internal and external factors",
    "explanation": "Economic theories may yield diverse outcomes due to factors like natural resources, human resources, historical background, etc",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Similar socio-political conditions",
    "option_b": "Homogeneous human behavior",
    "option_c": "External economic challenges",
    "option_d": "Variability in internal and external factors",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010106",
    "question": "The main challenge that economies face is to ensure the availability of required goods and services through proper production capacity and __________",
    "answer": "Distribution Network",
    "explanation": "The question refers to the challenge economies face in fulfilling the needs of their population It highlights the importance of building production capacity to meet demands and establishing an efficient distribution network to deliver goods and services",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Di,st,ri,bu,tio,n N,et,wo,rk",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010107",
    "question": "Within the realm of economics, what overarching principle takes precedence when delving into the intricacies of human conduct and decision-making?",
    "answer": "Rational decision-making",
    "explanation": "The economic theories are based on expectations of rational economic behavior by individuals and organizations",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Psychological motivations",
    "option_b": "Rational decision-making",
    "option_c": "Social interactions",
    "option_d": "Genetic predispositions",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010108",
    "question": "What constituent element serves as a catalyst for the intricate and ever-evolving character of economics?",
    "answer": "Continuous Evolution of practice into theory",
    "explanation": "Economics has developed out of real-life practices and has continuously evolved based on contemporary results and experiences",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Fixed set of principles",
    "option_b": "Consistent government policies",
    "option_c": "Continuous Evolution of practice into theory",
    "option_d": "Predictable human behavior",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010109",
    "question": "In the context of economics, when one alludes to the concept of \"scarcity,\" what multifaceted connotation does it carry, encapsulating the essence of resource allocation?",
    "answer": "Unlimited human wants with limited resources",
    "explanation": "The one of the key ideas in economics is the fact of scarcity, indicating that human wants are unlimited while resources are limited",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Limited demand for goods and services",
    "option_b": "Equilibrium between wants and resources",
    "option_c": "Abundance of resources",
    "option_d": "Unlimited human wants with limited resources",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010110",
    "question": "Which statement best summarizes the relationship between economics and the economy?",
    "answer": "Economics is the theory, and the economy is the practical application of that theory",
    "explanation": "Economics as the discipline studying economic behavior, while the economy is the real picture that emerges after applying economic theories",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Economics is the theory, and the economy is the practical application of that theory",
    "option_b": "Economics and the economy are two unrelated fields of study",
    "option_c": "Economics studies theoretical concepts, while the economy deals with philosophical issues",
    "option_d": "Economics focuses on political aspects, while the economy studies social interactions",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010111",
    "question": "How may one elucidate the discerning features that demarcate economies that have achieved an advanced state of development from those that are still in the process of Evolution and growth within the realm of economic systems?",
    "answer": "Variability in economic tools and results",
    "explanation": "It suggests that even if two economies face similar challenges and select the same economic tools, their results may vary due to internal and external factors",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Similarity in economic challenges",
    "option_b": "Homogeneous human behavior",
    "option_c": "Socio-political conditions",
    "option_d": "Variability in economic tools and results",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010112",
    "question": "What does This  imply about the nature of economic policies?",
    "answer": "The impact of economic policies varies due to diverse factors and contexts",
    "explanation": "Economic policies may have diverse outcomes due to internal and external factors influencing human behavior and economic conditions",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Economic policies have a consistent impact on all economies",
    "option_b": "Economic policies are predictable and deterministic",
    "option_c": "The impact of economic policies varies due to diverse factors and contexts",
    "option_d": "Economic policies are always successful in solving challenges",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010113",
    "question": "What distinguishes economics from other disciplines like political science, sociology, and public administration?",
    "answer": "Study of diverse human activities",
    "explanation": "It categorizes various disciplines as humanities because they study different human activities, including economic activities studied by economics",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Different theoretical foundations",
    "option_b": "Study of diverse human activities",
    "option_c": "Emphasis on governmental policies",
    "option_d": "Focus on individual behavior only",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010114",
    "question": "Economists modify their ideas and theories over time to adress what?",
    "answer": "To better address economic challenges",
    "explanation": "Economists modify and remodify their ideas based on contemporary results and experiences to better address evolving economic challenges",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "To cater to political ideologies",
    "option_b": "To better address economic challenges",
    "option_c": "To align with changing cultural norms",
    "option_d": "To conform to international standards",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010115",
    "question": "What is the primary criterion for categorizing activities as economic activities?",
    "answer": "Involvement of profit",
    "explanation": "The economic activities as those involving profit, loss, livelihood, occupation, wage, employment, etc",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Involvement of profit",
    "option_b": "Government regulation",
    "option_c": "Technological complexity",
    "option_d": "Societal importance",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010116",
    "question": "What is the significance of the term \"economy\" when used in isolation?",
    "answer": "It has no meaning without context",
    "explanation": "The term \"economy\" gains meaning only when it is associated with the name of a country, region, or block",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "It represents the global financial system",
    "option_b": "It describes the overall state of an individual's finances",
    "option_c": "It has no meaning without context",
    "option_d": "It refers to the stock market",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010117",
    "question": "Study of economics considered dynamic and complex due to",
    "answer": "In response to evolving human behavior and economic conditions",
    "explanation": "economics is dynamic due to the continuously changing human behavior and socio-economic factors",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Due to constant government intervention",
    "option_b": "Because of changing political ideologies",
    "option_c": "In response to evolving human behavior and economic conditions",
    "option_d": "As a result of technological advancements",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010118",
    "question": "Economics categorized as a dynamic subject due to which of the following reason?",
    "answer": "It is studied in a space-time continuum and involves living human beings",
    "explanation": "economics is dynamic because it is studied in the context of the space-time continuum and involves the study of living human beings",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "It involves complex mathematical models",
    "option_b": "It deals with historical analysis of economies",
    "option_c": "It is studied in a space-time continuum and involves living human beings",
    "option_d": "It exclusively focuses on monetary aspects",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010119",
    "question": "Which term best describes the process of prioritizing certain needs over others when utilizing limited resources?",
    "answer": "Resource allocation",
    "explanation": "The individuals, society, and the government make prioritized choices in the process of using scarce resources to gratify various needs and wants",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Resource allocation",
    "option_b": "Demand-supply equilibrium",
    "option_c": "Profit optimization",
    "option_d": "Consumer surplus",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010120",
    "question": "Which term best describes the process of prioritizing certain needs over others when utilizing limited resources?",
    "answer": "Economics focuses on individual behavior, while sociology studies societal interactions",
    "explanation": "Economics primarily examines individual behavior within the context of economic activities, including decision-making related to production, consumption, and resource allocation On the other hand, sociology places its emphasis on societal interactions, structures, and dynamics",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Economics focuses on individual behavior, while sociology studies societal interactions",
    "option_b": "Economics solely deals with monetary matters, while political science studies government structures",
    "option_c": "Economics studies government policies, while sociology focuses on economic behavior",
    "option_d": "Economics emphasizes psychological motivations, while political science studies human behavior",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010121",
    "question": "Economics aims to improve the ________ of human life by studying economic behaviors and proposing ways to maximize economic potential",
    "answer": "quality",
    "explanation": "This  emphasizes that the ultimate goal of economics is to enhance the quality of human life by studying economic behaviors and finding ways to optimize the utilization of resources",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "qu,al,ity",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010122",
    "question": "An economy must prioritize and allocate resources to satisfy competing ________ and wants",
    "answer": "needs",
    "explanation": "In an economy, resources are limited, and individuals, society, and governments need to make choices to prioritize fulfilling essential needs over various wants due to the scarcity of resources",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "ne,eds",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010123",
    "question": "The discipline of economics has evolved through modifications in theories based on contemporary ________ and experiences of economies",
    "answer": "results",
    "explanation": "The discipline of economics has evolved over time by adapting its theories and ideas based on the real-world results and outcomes observed in various economies under different conditions",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "re,su,lts",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010124",
    "question": "Economic theories are often influenced by a variety of factors, including ________ resources, historical context, and human behavior",
    "answer": "limited",
    "explanation": "Economic theories take into consideration the scarcity of resources, which is a central concept in economics The availability of limited resources contributes to the need for making choices and trade-offs in economic decision-making",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "li,mi,ted",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010125",
    "question": "Consider the following statement and select the correct answer                                  \nAssertion: Economics studies how societies use scarce resources to produce valuable commodities and distribute them among different people                               \n\nReasoning: Scarcity is a fundamental concept in economics, and studying how resources are allocated to meet unlimited human wants is a key focus of the discipline",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "The assertion accurately describes one of the key focuses of economics, which is the study of how societies allocate scarce resources to meet unlimited human wants \n\nThe reasoning further explains that scarcity is a central concept in economics and is indeed the reason why the study of resource allocation is essential in the field",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true and R is not the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010126",
    "question": "Consider the following statement and select the correct answer                                   \nAssertion: Economic outcomes can vary among countries following similar economic policies due to the unpredictability of human behavior            \n                                            \nReasoning: Economic theories are based on expectations of human behavior, which can be influenced by various internal and external factors, leading to diverse outcomes",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "The assertion correctly states that similar economic policies may lead to different outcomes due to the unpredictable nature of human behavior\n\n The reasoning provides further support by explaining that economic theories are based on human behavior, which is influenced by a variety of factors, making it difficult to predict precise outcomes",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true and R is not the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010127",
    "question": "Consider the following statement and select the correct answer                                       \nAssertion: The ultimate goal of economics is to maximize profits for businesses and ensure economic growth           \n                                                               \nReasoning: Economics primarily focuses on improving the living conditions of humanity at large and finding ways to enhance overall well-being",
    "answer": "A is false but R is true",
    "explanation": "The assertion incorrectly states the ultimate goal of economics \n\nWhile economic growth and profits are important considerations, the primary goal of economics, as mentioned in the reasoning, is to enhance the overall well-being and living conditions of humanity through efficient resource allocation and addressing economic challenges",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true and R is not the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010128",
    "question": "What are the three possible roles of the state/government in an economy, as mentioned in This ?",
    "answer": "Regulator, Supplier of Private Goods, Supplier of Public Goods",
    "explanation": "The three possible roles of the state/government in an economy are: (i) Regulator of the economic system, (ii) Producer and/or supplier of 'private goods and services,' and (iii) Producer and/or supplier of 'public goods' or 'social goods'",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Regulator, Supplier of Private Goods, Supplier of Public Goods",
    "option_b": "Producer of Private Goods, Producer of Public Goods, Regulator",
    "option_c": "Regulator, Distributor of Private Goods, Distributor of Public Goods",
    "option_d": "Supplier of Private Goods, Regulator, Producer of Public Goods",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010129",
    "question": "In the context of the Washington Consensus, what was the primary intention behind the set of policy reforms proposed by John Williamson?",
    "answer": "To address the economic problems faced by Latin American countries",
    "explanation": "The primary intention behind the Washington Consensus was to address the real economic problems faced by Latin American countries at the time, rather than imposing neo-liberal policies on developing countries",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "To promote market fundamentalism globally",
    "option_b": "To impose neo-liberal policies on developing countries",
    "option_c": "To address the economic problems faced by Latin American countries",
    "option_d": "To advocate for a development state in the Western economies",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010130",
    "question": "Why Indian economy is still considered an Agrarian economy?",
    "answer": "High contribution of the primary sector to GDP",
    "explanation": "An economy is categorized as an agrarian economy if the primary sector's contribution to the total output (GDP) is 50% or more",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "High contribution of the tertiary sector to GDP",
    "option_b": "High contribution of the primary sector to GDP",
    "option_c": "High contribution of the secondary sector to GDP",
    "option_d": "High level of industrialization",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010131",
    "question": "Which sector of the economy includes activities related to education, banking, transportation, and tourism?",
    "answer": "Tertiary Sector",
    "explanation": "The sector that includes activities like education, banking, transportation, and tourism is the tertiary sector, also known as the services sector",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Primary Sector",
    "option_b": "Secondary Sector",
    "option_c": "Tertiary Sector",
    "option_d": "Industrial Sector",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010132",
    "question": "The three elements that Keynes believed the political problem of mankind is to combine?",
    "answer": "Economic efficiency, individual liberty, social justice",
    "explanation": "According to Keynes, the political problem of mankind is to combine economic efficiency, individual liberty, and social justice",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Economic efficiency, social justice, environmental sustainability",
    "option_b": "Economic growth, individual liberty, technological advancement",
    "option_c": "Economic efficiency, individual liberty, social justice",
    "option_d": "Individual liberty, social justice, cultural diversity",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010133",
    "question": "In a service economy, which sector contributes the highest value to the total produce?",
    "answer": "Tertiary Sector",
    "explanation": "In a service economy, the highest contribution to the total produce comes from the tertiary sector (services sector)",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Primary Sector",
    "option_b": "Secondary Sector",
    "option_c": "Tertiary Sector",
    "option_d": "Industrial Sector",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010134",
    "question": "What is the term used to describe an economy where the secondary sector contributes 50% or more to the total produce value?",
    "answer": "Industrial Economy",
    "explanation": "An economy where the secondary sector contributes 50% or more to the total produce value is known as an industrial economy",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Agrarian Economy",
    "option_b": "Industrial Economy",
    "option_c": "Service Economy",
    "option_d": "Manufacturing Economy",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010135",
    "question": "What are the three stages of growth of an economy mentioned in This ?",
    "answer": "Agrarian, Industrial, Service",
    "explanation": "The three stages of growth of an economy as Agrarian, Industrial, and Service",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Pre-industrial, Industrial, Post-industrial",
    "option_b": "Agrarian, Industrial, Service",
    "option_c": "Agricultural, Manufacturing, Tertiary",
    "option_d": "Early, Middle, Late Development",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010136",
    "question": "Which term is used to describe an extreme and dogmatic commitment to the belief that markets can handle everything?",
    "answer": "Neoliberalism",
    "explanation": "The term used to describe an extreme commitment to the belief that markets can handle everything is \"Neoliberalism",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Keynesianism",
    "option_b": "Liberalization",
    "option_c": "Washington Consensus",
    "option_d": "Neoliberalism",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010137",
    "question": "What is the primary factor that led to the shift from an agrarian economy to a service economy in Western economies?",
    "answer": "High contribution of the tertiary sector to GDP",
    "explanation": "This  suggests that the shift from an agrarian economy to a service economy in Western economies was primarily driven by the high contribution of the tertiary sector (services sector) to GDP and employment",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "A decline in industrial activities",
    "option_b": "High contribution of the tertiary sector to GDP",
    "option_c": "Dependency on primary sector resources",
    "option_d": "Dependency on secondary sector manufacturing",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010138",
    "question": "What are the three historically existing models of distribution networks mentioned in This ?",
    "answer": "State, Market, State-market mix",
    "explanation": "State, Market, State-market mix This  outlines three historical distribution network models: state, where the government supplies goods and services; market, where prices determine distribution; and state-market mix, a combination of state and market distribution",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Capitalism, Socialism, Communism",
    "option_b": "State, Market, State-market mix",
    "option_c": "Free market, Planned economy, Mixed economy",
    "option_d": "Private sector, Public sector, Cooperative sector",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010139",
    "question": "According to Adam Smith, how would a market economy achieve equilibrium?",
    "answer": "Through the invisible hand of market forces",
    "explanation": "Through the invisible hand of market forces Adam Smith's theory emphasized that market forces and the invisible hand would naturally lead to equilibrium in a market economy",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Through government regulations",
    "option_b": "Through centralized planning",
    "option_c": "Through the invisible hand of market forces",
    "option_d": "Through collective ownership of resources",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010140",
    "question": "Combining market mechanisms within a socialist economic framework was a concept introduced by?",
    "answer": "Oscar Lange",
    "explanation": "Oscar Lange Oscar Lange introduced the concept of \"market socialism,\" which proposed combining market mechanisms within a socialist economic framework",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "John Maynard Keynes",
    "option_b": "Karl Marx",
    "option_c": "Adam Smith",
    "option_d": "Oscar Lange",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010141",
    "question": "What is the main difference between socialism and communism ?",
    "answer": "State ownership vs collective ownership",
    "explanation": "State ownership vs collective ownership Socialism involves state ownership of means of production, while communism advocates for collective ownership of all properties",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "State ownership vs collective ownership",
    "option_b": "Private ownership vs public ownership",
    "option_c": "Laissez-faire vs government control",
    "option_d": "Market economy vs planned economy",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010142",
    "question": "The Great Depression led to the questioning of the principles of which economic system?",
    "answer": "Capitalism",
    "explanation": "Capitalism The Great Depression prompted questioning of capitalist principles as market mechanisms failed to prevent the crisis",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Capitalism",
    "option_b": "Socialism",
    "option_c": "Communism",
    "option_d": "Mixed economy",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010143",
    "question": "According to Keynes, why is government intervention necessary in an economy?",
    "answer": "To address unemployment and boost demand",
    "explanation": "To address unemployment and boost demand Keynes argued for government intervention to combat unemployment and stimulate demand during economic downturns",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "To promote inequality",
    "option_b": "To enforce strict laissez-faire policies",
    "option_c": "To achieve equilibrium through market forces",
    "option_d": "To address unemployment and boost demand",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010144",
    "question": "What did the World Development Report of 1999 conclude about the mixed economy?",
    "answer": "It emphasized a complementary relationship between market and state",
    "explanation": "It emphasized a complementary relationship between market and state The World Development Report of 1999 highlighted a balanced approach, where both market and state intervention play complementary roles in a mixed economy",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "It rejected both market and state economies",
    "option_b": "It favored complete state control over the economy",
    "option_c": "It endorsed a pure free-market economy",
    "option_d": "It emphasized a complementary relationship between market and state",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010145",
    "question": "Which country adopted an \"open door policy\" and initiated a move towards market socialism?",
    "answer": "China",
    "explanation": "China initiated an \"open door policy\" in 1985, moving towards market socialism, which combined market principles with state involvement",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Soviet Union",
    "option_b": "United States",
    "option_c": "China",
    "option_d": "India",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010146",
    "question": "What did the emergence of the World Trade Organization (WTO) bring to the world economy?",
    "answer": "Inclination towards free market economies with some state intervention",
    "explanation": "Inclination towards free market economies with some state intervention This  indicates that the emergence of the World Trade Organization (WTO) led to a preference for free market economies with limited state intervention",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Greater emphasis on state-controlled economies",
    "option_b": "Rejection of market economies",
    "option_c": "A shift towards a purely planned economy",
    "option_d": "Inclination towards free market economies with some state intervention",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010147",
    "question": "What key role did the state play in the mixed economy model?",
    "answer": "Guaranteeing minimum levels of nutrition to all citizens",
    "explanation": "Guaranteeing minimum levels of nutrition to all citizens In the mixed economy model, the state played a role in providing essential public goods such as education, healthcare, and social security to ensure the well-being of the population",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Complete control over all economic activities",
    "option_b": "Guaranteeing minimum levels of nutrition to all citizens",
    "option_c": "Eliminating private ownership of resources",
    "option_d": "Promoting pauperization of the masses",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010148",
    "question": "match the economist with their work:",
    "answer": "Adam Smith - The Wealth of Nations, Karl Marx - Das Kapital, John Maynard Keynes - The General Theory of Employment Interest and Money",
    "explanation": "Adam Smith is associated with the work \"The Wealth of Nations\" This is considered his magnum opus, where he laid down the foundations of classical economics and discussed concepts like the invisible hand, division of labor, and free market principles \n\nKarl Marx wrote \"Das Kapital\", a seminal work in which he developed his theories of historical materialism and critiqued the capitalist system The work delves into issues of labor, value, and the nature of capitalism \n\nJohn Maynard Keynes authored \"The General Theory of Employment, Interest, and Money\" This book is a cornerstone of Keynesian economics, introducing the concept of aggregate demand and advocating for government intervention during economic downturns to address unemployment and stabilize the economy",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "John Maynard Keynes,The General Theory of Employment Interest and Money",
    "option_b": "Karl Marx,Das Kapital",
    "option_c": "Adam Smith,The Wealth of Nations",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010149",
    "question": "match the term with its description:",
    "answer": "Scarcity - Unlimited human wants vs limited resources, Economy - Application of economic theories in a region, Capital formation - Process of building production capacity through investment, Karl Marx - Das Kapital",
    "explanation": "Scarcity is the concept where human wants and needs are unlimited, but the resources available to fulfill these wants are limited This creates the fundamental economic problem of making choices due to the scarcity of resources \n\nAn economy refers to the system of production, distribution, and consumption of goods and services within a region or a country It encompasses the activities related to managing resources to meet the needs and wants of people \n\nCapital formation is the process of building up the production capacity of an economy through investment in physical and human capital It involves saving and investing in machinery, infrastructure, education, and other factors that contribute to economic growth and development",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Scarcity,Unlimited human wants vs limited resources",
    "option_b": "Economy,Application of economic theories in a region",
    "option_c": "Capital formation,Process of building production capacity through investment",
    "option_d": "Karl Marx,Das Kapital",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "010150",
    "question": "match the Economic Systems with their Characteristics:",
    "answer": "Capitalistic Economy - Private enterprises make decisions & limited government role, State Economy - State owns means of production and controls economy, Mixed Economy - Blend of market capitalism and state intervention",
    "explanation": "Capitalistic Economy is characterized by private ownership of resources and the means of production In this system, private enterprises and individuals make most economic decisions, and the government's role is limited to enforcing laws, regulations, and ensuring fair competition In a State Economy, the government owns and controls the means of production and has a central role in economic planning and decision-making The government often regulates and directs economic activities according to its objectives Mixed Economy is a blend of market capitalism and state intervention It combines elements of both private ownership and government control The government may intervene to address market failures, provide public goods, and ensure social welfare, while private enterprises still operate within the economy",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Discipline to Type of Economies",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Capitalistic Economy,Private enterprises make decisions & limited government role",
    "option_b": "State Economy,State owns means of production and controls economy",
    "option_c": "Mixed Economy,Blend of market capitalism and state intervention",
    "option_d": "Mixed Economy,Blend of market capitalism and state intervention",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020101",
    "question": "What is the primary reason for considering 'income' as a focal point of development and well-being in nations?",
    "answer": "It provides a comprehensive measure of well-being",
    "explanation": "While income is not the sole indicator of well-being, it has been widely used because it provides a comprehensive measure of a nation's economic strength and citizens' well-being",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "It is easy to calculate and compare",
    "option_b": "It provides a comprehensive measure of well-being",
    "option_c": "It is the only measure that matters",
    "option_d": "It directly influences government policies",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020102",
    "question": "Consider the below statements and pick the correct ones\nAssertion: In national income accounting, indirect taxes are deducted from the national income at factor cost but not at market cost\n\nReasoning: Indirect taxes are collected at various points in the production and distribution process, leading to double counting if not adjusted properly",
    "answer": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, and the reasoning is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "explanation": "The assertion is true because indirect taxes are deducted from the national income at factor cost to avoid double counting The reasoning is the correct explanation because indirect taxes are already included in the value of goods and services produced, and they are collected from individuals and companies as they purchase these goods and services Thus, subtracting indirect taxes from national income at factor cost removes the double counting",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, and the reasoning is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_b": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, but the reasoning is not the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_c": "The assertion is true, but the reasoning is false",
    "option_d": "The assertion is false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020103",
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT included in the calculation of GDP?",
    "answer": "Imports",
    "explanation": "Imports are not included in the calculation of GDP GDP measures the value of goods and services produced within a country's borders, not the value of goods and services that are imported into the country\n\nWhen a country imports goods and services, it is essentially buying those goods and services from another country The value of those goods and services is counted in the GDP of the exporting country, not the importing country",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Government spending",
    "option_b": "Net private remittances",
    "option_c": "Exports",
    "option_d": "Imports",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020104",
    "question": "What is Net Domestic Product (NDP)?",
    "answer": "GDP minus depreciation",
    "explanation": "NDP is calculated by subtracting the value of depreciation from GDP It represents the net value of goods and services produced after accounting for wear and tear",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "The total value of goods and services produced within a country",
    "option_b": "GDP minus depreciation",
    "option_c": "GDP plus government spending",
    "option_d": "Gross National Product minus taxes",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020105",
    "question": "The concept of __________ involves combining economic efficiency, social justice, and individual liberty in an economy",
    "answer": "Keynes",
    "explanation": "Keynes believed the political problem of mankind is to combine three things: economic efficiency, social justice, and individual liberty This concept is attributed to Keynes and reflects the idea that these three elements need to be balanced in a well-functioning economy",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Ke,yn,es",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020106",
    "question": "What is included in the segment 'Income from Abroad' when calculating GNP?",
    "answer": "Private remittances",
    "explanation": "The segment \"Income from Abroad\" when calculating GNP includes the following:\nIncome earned by domestic residents from investments abroad: This includes dividends, interest, and royalties earned by domestic residents from investments in foreign countries\nRemittances from migrant workers: This includes money sent home by migrant workers to their families in their home countries\nProfits of foreign-owned companies: This includes profits made by foreign-owned companies that operate in the domestic economy\nForeign aid: This includes grants and loans given by foreign governments and organizations to the domestic government",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Government grants",
    "option_b": "Domestic consumption",
    "option_c": "External loans",
    "option_d": "Private remittances",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020107",
    "question": "Mixed economies typically retain at least one economic role for the state, such as supplying __________ goods to those in need",
    "answer": "public",
    "explanation": "Mixed economies maintain a role for the state in supplying public goods to the population Public goods, which include essential services like education, healthcare, sanitation, and more, are necessary for social well-being and are often provided by the state to ensure equitable access for all citizens",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "pu,bl,ic",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020108",
    "question": "What is the primary difference between 'factor cost' and 'market cost'?",
    "answer": "Factor cost is the production cost, while market cost includes taxes",
    "explanation": "The primary difference between factor cost and market cost is that factor cost includes only the costs of the factors of production, while market cost includes the costs of the factors of production plus taxes and subsidies\n\nFactor cost is the cost of producing a good or service, excluding taxes and subsidies It is the amount of money that businesses have to pay to the factors of production, such as labor, capital, and land\nMarket cost is the cost of producing a good or service, including taxes and subsidies It is the amount of money that consumers have to pay for a good or service, including taxes and subsidies",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Factor cost includes taxes, while market cost excludes taxes",
    "option_b": "Factor cost includes labor, while market cost includes raw materials",
    "option_c": "Factor cost is the production cost, while market cost includes taxes",
    "option_d": "Factor cost is the market price, while market cost is the production cost",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020109",
    "question": "What does 'constant price' refer to in the context of national income calculation?",
    "answer": "The price of goods and services at a standstill year's inflation rate",
    "explanation": "Constant price refers to the price of goods and services after adjusting for inflation based on a standstill year (base year)\n\nIn the context of national income calculation, constant price refers to the prices of goods and services in a base year This is used to compare the value of national income over time, without the effects of inflation\n\nFor example, if the national income in 2023 is calculated at constant prices of 2022, it means that the prices of goods and services used to calculate the national income in 2023 are the same as the prices of goods and services in 2022 This allows us to compare the real change in national income between 2022 and 2023, rather than just the nominal change",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "The price of goods and services after including inflation",
    "option_b": "The price of goods and services at the maximum retail price",
    "option_c": "The price of goods and services at a standstill year's inflation rate",
    "option_d": "The price of goods and services at the factory gate",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020110",
    "question": "Consider the below statements and pick the correct ones\nAssertion: Subsidies are added to the national income at market cost in order to calculate the national income at factor cost\n\nReasoning: Subsidies are provided by the government to reduce the cost of goods and services, and their inclusion in market cost accounts for their impact on production and distribution",
    "answer": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, and the reasoning is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "explanation": "The assertion is true because subsidies are indeed added to the national income at market cost when calculating the national income at factor cost The reasoning is the correct explanation because subsidies are provided by the government to lower the cost of goods and services, and including them in market cost adjusts for their influence on production and distribution",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, and the reasoning is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_b": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, but the reasoning is not the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_c": "The assertion is true, but the reasoning is false",
    "option_d": "The assertion is false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020111",
    "question": "Which component of GNP accounts for net interest payments on external loans?",
    "answer": "Interest on external loans",
    "explanation": "The component of GNP that accounts for net interest payments on external loans is the Net factor income from abroad (NFIA)\nNFIA is the difference between the income that domestic residents earn from investments abroad and the income that foreign residents earn from investments in the domestic economy\nIt is calculated as follows:\nNFIA = Income from abroad - Income to abroad",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Private remittances",
    "option_b": "External grants",
    "option_c": "Interest on external loans",
    "option_d": "Net trade balance",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020112",
    "question": "Consider the below statements and pick the correct ones\nAssertion: The Base Year for calculating India's national income was revised from 2004-05 to 2011-12 in accordance with international standards\n\nReasoning: The System of National Accounts (SNA)-2008 recommends revising the base year of economic indices every five years for accuracy and relevance",
    "answer": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, and the reasoning is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "explanation": "The assertion is true as the Base Year for India's national income calculation was indeed revised to 2011-12 The reasoning is the correct explanation, as the System of National Accounts (SNA)-2008 suggests periodic revisions of base years to ensure that economic indices remain accurate and relevant",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, and the reasoning is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_b": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, but the reasoning is not the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_c": "The assertion is true, but the reasoning is false",
    "option_d": "The assertion is false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020113",
    "question": "What does GDP represent?",
    "answer": "Value of final goods and services produced in a year",
    "explanation": "GDP represents the total value of final goods and services produced within a country's boundaries in a year",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Total government spending in a year",
    "option_b": "Value of final goods and services produced in a year",
    "option_c": "Net value of goods and services produced after depreciation",
    "option_d": "Income generated from foreign trade",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020114",
    "question": "What is the significance of 'Income from Abroad' in GNP calculation?",
    "answer": "It accounts for external economic activities",
    "explanation": "Income from Abroad' accounts for the trans-boundary economic activities of a nation, including private remittances, interest on external loans, and external grants",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "It represents an increase in internal investment",
    "option_b": "It helps reduce the impact of trade deficits",
    "option_c": "It includes grants received from foreign countries",
    "option_d": "It accounts for external economic activities",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020115",
    "question": "Consider the below statements and pick the correct ones\nAssertion: Gross Domestic Product (GDP) at constant market prices is used internationally as the headline growth rate indicator\n\nReasoning: GDP at constant market prices accounts for inflation's effects and provides a more accurate measure of economic growth over time",
    "answer": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, and the reasoning is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "explanation": "The assertion is true as GDP at constant market prices is widely used internationally to measure economic growth The reasoning is correct, as GDP at constant market prices adjusts for inflation, allowing for a more accurate comparison of economic growth over different time periods",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, and the reasoning is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_b": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, but the reasoning is not the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_c": "The assertion is true, but the reasoning is false",
    "option_d": "The assertion is false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020116",
    "question": "What does 'depreciation' refer to in economic terms?",
    "answer": "The wear and tear of assets during production",
    "explanation": "Depreciation refers to the reduction in the value of an asset over time, due primarily to wear and tear and obsolescence In the context of national income accounting, depreciation (sometimes called capital consumption allowance) represents the amount of capital that is used up or worn out in producing the national output in a particular period It's essentially the value of capital goods that have to be replaced or repaired to continue production at the current level",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "An increase in the value of assets over time",
    "option_b": "The value of goods and services consumed",
    "option_c": "The wear and tear of assets during production",
    "option_d": "The total value of goods and services exported",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020117",
    "question": "How does the value of 'Income from Abroad' impact GNP?",
    "answer": "It is subtracted from GNP to decrease its value",
    "explanation": "Gross National Product (GNP) is the total value of final goods and services produced by a country's citizens in a particular time period, regardless of whether they are located within the country or abroad Therefore, GNP includes the income earned by the country's residents from abroad but excludes the income earned by foreigners within the country",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "It is added to GNP to increase its value",
    "option_b": "It is subtracted from GNP to decrease its value",
    "option_c": "It has no impact on the calculation of GNP",
    "option_d": "It is multiplied with GDP to calculate GNP",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020118",
    "question": "Why did India switch from calculating national income at factor cost to market cost?",
    "answer": "To align with international practice",
    "explanation": "In alignment with global best practices and the recommendations from the System of National Accounts (SNA) – an international standard system for national accounts – India made a shift from factor cost to calculating its GDP at market prices The major reasons for this shift include:\nConsistency with International Practices\nAccurate Reflection of Market Dynamics\nPolicy Implications",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "To increase transparency in economic data",
    "option_b": "To align with international practice",
    "option_c": "To encourage domestic production",
    "option_d": "To reduce the impact of inflation",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020119",
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT included in the calculation of GDP?",
    "answer": "Private remittances",
    "explanation": "Private remittances are not included in GDP calculation; they are part of the GNP calculation",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Value of final goods and services",
    "option_b": "Government spending",
    "option_c": "Private remittances",
    "option_d": "Exports",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020120",
    "question": "What is the significance of calculating NNP at constant prices?",
    "answer": "It accounts for changes in inflation over time",
    "explanation": "Calculating NNP at constant prices is crucial because it adjusts for inflation, providing a clearer view of an economy's real output and growth trends This facilitates accurate comparisons over time, aids policy assessment, guides investment decisions, and enhances international economic comparisons, enabling better planning and analysis",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "It accounts for changes in inflation over time",
    "option_b": "It provides a more accurate reflection of market prices",
    "option_c": "It simplifies the calculation process",
    "option_d": "It focuses on the growth rate of the economy",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020121",
    "question": "Which of the following statements about Gross Domestic Product (GDP) are correct? \n1GDP is the value of all final goods and services produced within a nation's boundary during a specific time period \n2 GDP is calculated by adding national private consumption, gross investment, government spending, and trade balance \n3GDP includes expenditures on imports and subtracts expenditures of exported goods and services \n4GDP only indicates the qualitative aspects of the goods and services produced",
    "answer": "1, 2, & 3",
    "explanation": "GDP represents the total value of all final goods and services produced within a nation's boundary in a specific time period GDP is calculated by summing national private consumption, gross investment, government spending, and trade balanceGDP includes expenditures on imports but subtracts expenditures of goods and services that are exported and not sold within the country",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1, 2, & 3",
    "option_b": "1 & 2",
    "option_c": "1 & 3",
    "option_d": "1, 3, & 4",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020122",
    "question": "Which of the following statements about Net Domestic Product (NDP) are not true?\n1NDP is calculated by subtracting depreciation from Gross Domestic Product (GDP)\n2Depreciation represents the loss in value of assets over time due to wear and tear \n3NDP provides insight into the historical loss due to depreciation and the achievements in minimizing depreciation \n4NDP is used for comparative economics to rank nations by their economic strength",
    "answer": "4 only",
    "explanation": "True: NDP is calculated by subtracting depreciation from GDP This adjustment accounts for the wear and tear on capital goods, giving a more accurate measure of a country's actual economic output after accounting for the loss of value in its productive assets\n\nTrue: Depreciation reflects the decline in asset value due to usage, obsolescence, or deterioration It's a vital concept in economics, as it recognizes the ongoing reduction in the worth of capital goods over time\n\nTrue: NDP offers insights into both historical depreciation losses and efforts to minimize them It reflects an economy's productive capacity while considering the impact of asset wear and tear, aiding in evaluating capital maintenance and growth strategies\n\nNot True: NDP is not commonly used to rank nations by economic strength Other metrics like GDP, GNP, and composite indices are more prevalent for making international comparisons and assessing economic power",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1, 2, & 3",
    "option_b": "4 only",
    "option_c": "1 & 3",
    "option_d": "1, 3, & 4",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020123",
    "question": "Which statements accurately describe Gross National Product (GNP)?\n1GNP includes Gross Domestic Product (GDP) and the balance of trade\n2Income from abroad includes components like private remittances, interest on external loans, and external grants\n3GNP is calculated by adding income from abroad to GDP \n4GNP is always greater than GDP for all countries",
    "answer": "2 & 3",
    "explanation": "True: Income from abroad in GNP includes components like private remittances, interest on external loans, and external grants These represent the earnings and financial inflows from a country's residents working, investing, or receiving financial assistance abroad\n\nTrue: GNP is calculated by adding income from abroad to GDP This adjustment accounts for the net income earned by a country's residents from their economic activities abroad, providing a more comprehensive measure of national economic performance\n\nStatement 1 is not entirely accurate While GNP does include income from abroad, it does not directly include the balance of trade The balance of trade refers to the difference between a country's exports and imports, and it is not part of GNP calculation\n\nStatement 4 is not true GNP is not always greater than GDP for all countries The relationship between GNP and GDP depends on whether a country's residents earn more from their economic activities abroad (GNP > GDP) or foreign residents earn more from their activities within the country (GNP < GDP)",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1, 2, & 3",
    "option_b": "1 & 2",
    "option_c": "2 & 3",
    "option_d": "1, 3, & 4",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020124",
    "question": "Which statements accurately describe Net National Product (NNP)?\n1NNP is the Gross National Product (GNP) minus depreciation\n2Depreciation is the loss in value of assets over time due to wear and tear\n3NNP represents the purest form of a nation's income\n4NNP divided by the population gives the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) per capita",
    "answer": "1, 2, & 3",
    "explanation": "True: NNP is calculated by subtracting depreciation from Gross National Product (GNP) This adjustment accounts for the depreciation of capital goods and provides a measure of the net income generated by a nation's economic activities after accounting for the loss of value in its productive assets\n\nTrue: Depreciation indeed refers to the loss in value of assets over time due to factors like wear and tear, obsolescence, and deterioration It's an essential concept in economics, especially when calculating NNP and other economic indicators\n\nTrue: NNP represents a nation's income after accounting for depreciation, making it a more accurate reflection of the economy's productive capacity It is considered a purer form of income measurement compared to other indicators like GNP\n\nStatement 4 is not entirely accurate NNP divided by the population does not directly give the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) per capita NNP per capita is a measure of income distribution and economic well-being, while GDP per capita measures the average economic output per person in a country",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1, 2, & 3",
    "option_b": "1 & 2",
    "option_c": "2 & 3",
    "option_d": "1, 3, & 4",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020125",
    "question": "Which of the following statements regarding the calculation of national income are accurate?\n1Factor cost refers to the total cost of production, including indirect taxes\n2Market cost includes the cost of production plus indirect taxes\n3Constant price calculations consider the impact of inflation at the base year\n4Developed nations commonly calculate their national income at constant prices",
    "answer": "2 & 3",
    "explanation": "True: Market cost includes the cost of production plus indirect taxes It reflects the total expenditure made by the final consumers, which includes both the cost of production and the indirect taxes levied on the goods and services\n\nTrue: Constant price calculations consider the impact of inflation at the base year By calculating national income at constant prices (also known as real terms), the effects of inflation are removed, providing a more accurate assessment of economic growth and changes in production over time\n\nStatement 1 is not accurate Factor cost refers to the total cost of production excluding indirect taxes It is the cost incurred by producers to produce goods and services, but it does not include indirect taxes Indirect taxes are added to the factor cost to arrive at market cost\n\nStatement 4 is not necessarily accurate Both developed and developing nations may calculate their national income at constant prices The choice to use constant prices or current prices depends on the specific goals of economic analysis, policy evaluation, and international comparisons",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1, 2, & 3",
    "option_b": "1 & 2",
    "option_c": "2 & 3",
    "option_d": "1, 3, & 4",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020126",
    "question": "The Gross Domestic Product (GDP) is the value of all final goods and services produced within a nation's boundaries during a specified period What does GDP include in its calculation?",
    "answer": "National Private Consumption and Gross Investment",
    "explanation": "GDP includes national private consumption, gross investment, government spending, and trade balance (exports minus imports) in its calculation",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Private Remittances and External Grants",
    "option_b": "Depreciation and Interest on External Loans",
    "option_c": "National Private Consumption and Gross Investment",
    "option_d": "Indirect Taxes and Market Price Adjustments",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020127",
    "question": "In a capitalistic economic system, the state's role is primarily that of a __________, while the responsibilities of producing and supplying private goods are left to the private sector",
    "answer": "regulator",
    "explanation": "In a capitalistic economic system, the state's role is mostly passive and focused on regulating the economic activities This means that the state acts as a regulator, overseeing and ensuring fair practices in the market, but it does not play an active role in producing and supplying private goods This role is left to the private sector, which operates based on market mechanisms",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "re,gu,la,to,r",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020128",
    "question": "The World Development Report, 1999, recommended a timely shuffling of the state's role in the economy based on __________ needs, suggesting a balanced role for both the state and the market to achieve economic goals",
    "answer": "socio-economic and political",
    "explanation": "The World Development Report, 1999, emphasized the need for states to adjust their roles in the economy based on socio-economic and political requirements. This approach recognizes the interconnectedness of social, economic, and political factors in shaping economic policies and outcomes. The suggestion ensures that both the state and the market work in harmony to fulfill the overarching economic objectives",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "socio-cultural and environmental",
    "option_b": "socio-economic and political",
    "option_c": "industrial and agricultural",
    "option_d": "technological and infrastructural",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020129",
    "question": "Net National Product (NNP) is calculated from Gross National Product (GNP) by adjusting for depreciation What does NNP represent?",
    "answer": "The GNP after accounting for wear and tear of assets",
    "explanation": "NNP represents the GNP after deducting the loss due to depreciation, which accounts for the wear and tear of assets during production",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "The GDP adjusted for inflation",
    "option_b": "The GDP minus external grants",
    "option_c": "The GNP adjusted for trade balance",
    "option_d": "The GNP after accounting for wear and tear of assets",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020130",
    "question": "When calculating national income, the choice of cost and price plays a role What is the primary difference between \"factor cost\" and \"market cost\"?",
    "answer": "Market cost includes indirect taxes, while factor cost does not",
    "explanation": "Factor cost represents the input cost of production, while market cost includes factor cost plus indirect taxes Market cost accounts for the cost at which goods reach the market, including taxes",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Factor cost includes indirect taxes, while market cost does not",
    "option_b": "Market cost includes indirect taxes, while factor cost does not",
    "option_c": "Factor cost considers the impact of inflation, while market cost does not",
    "option_d": "Market cost is used for domestic calculations, while factor cost is used for international comparisons",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020131",
    "question": "What is the main reason for deducting indirect taxes from the national income when calculated at factor cost in India?",
    "answer": "Indirect taxes are added twice, leading to distortion in national income value",
    "explanation": "Indirect taxes are deducted from national income at factor cost to avoid double counting, as they are added twice: once in individual/group income and again as government income",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Indirect taxes are collected at the income source of individuals and corporations",
    "option_b": "Indirect taxes are added twice, leading to distortion in national income value",
    "option_c": "Indirect taxes are collected by the government as income receipts",
    "option_d": "Indirect taxes are only related to disposable income",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020132",
    "question": "In the formula \"National Income at Factor Cost = NNP at Market Cost – Indirect Taxes,\" which component is subtracted from NNP at Market Cost?",
    "answer": "Indirect Taxes",
    "explanation": "In the formula \"National Income at Factor Cost = NNP at Market Cost – Indirect Taxes,\" the component subtracted from NNP at Market Cost is \"Indirect Taxes\" Indirect taxes are taxes levied on the production and sale of goods and services, and they are added to the cost of production to arrive at the market cost When calculating the national income at factor cost, these indirect taxes are subtracted to arrive at a measure that reflects the income earned by factors of production (ie, labor and capital) without the influence of taxes",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Direct Taxes",
    "option_b": "Subsidies",
    "option_c": "Indirect Taxes",
    "option_d": "Corporate Income Tax",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020133",
    "question": "According to the provided text, why are subsidies added to the national income at market cost in India?",
    "answer": "Subsidies are forwarded on the factor costs of goods and services",
    "explanation": "Subsidies are added to national income at market cost to ensure that the price of subsidized goods and services is not distorted by including their real factor costs",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Subsidies lower the factor cost of goods and services",
    "option_b": "Subsidies are considered disposable income",
    "option_c": "Subsidies are forwarded on the factor costs of goods and services",
    "option_d": "Subsidies are collected at the income source of individuals",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020134",
    "question": "Which change was NOT part of the revisions in India's national income accounting according to the provided text?",
    "answer": "Change from measuring GDP at constant market prices to GDP at factor cost",
    "explanation": "The change from measuring GDP at constant market prices to GDP at factor cost was not part of the revisions mentioned in This",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Base Year revision from 2004–05 to 2011–12",
    "option_b": "Incorporation of annual accounts of companies from the manufacturing sector",
    "option_c": "Adoption of System of National Accounts (SNA)-2008 standards",
    "option_d": "Change from measuring GDP at constant market prices to GDP at factor cost",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020135",
    "question": "Consider the below statements and pick the correct ones\nAssertion: Gross Value Added (GVA) at basic prices is inclusive of production taxes and less production subsidies\n\nReasoning: GVA at basic prices represents the value generated by an industry or sector, including taxes and subsidies directly related to production",
    "answer": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, and the reasoning is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "explanation": "GVA stands for Gross Value Added, which is a measure of economic output",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, and the reasoning is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_b": "Both the assertion and reasoning are true, but the reasoning is not the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_c": "The assertion is true, but the reasoning is false",
    "option_d": "The assertion is false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020136",
    "question": "What is the relationship between GVA at basic prices, GVA at factor cost, and GDP at market prices?",
    "answer": "GVA at basic prices = GVA at factor cost – GDP at market prices",
    "explanation": "GVA at basic prices serves as the starting point, representing the value generated by economic entities before accounting for taxes and subsidies on products GVA at factor cost adjusts for indirect taxes (except subsidies) to arrive at the income earned by factors of production GDP at market prices includes taxes on products (minus subsidies) to reflect the overall market value of all goods and services produced within the economy",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "GVA at basic prices = GVA at factor cost + GDP at market prices",
    "option_b": "GVA at basic prices = GVA at factor cost – GDP at market prices",
    "option_c": "GVA at factor cost = GVA at basic prices + GDP at market prices",
    "option_d": "GVA at factor cost = GVA at basic prices – GDP at market prices",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020137",
    "question": "Which of the following was NOT mentioned as a comprehensive coverage change in India's national income accounting?",
    "answer": "Inclusion of information from the accounts of agricultural cooperatives",
    "explanation": "The inclusion of information from the accounts of agricultural cooperatives was not mentioned as a comprehensive coverage change",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Incorporation of annual accounts of companies from the manufacturing sector",
    "option_b": "Inclusion of information from the accounts of stock brokers and stock exchanges",
    "option_c": "Comprehensive coverage of activities of local bodies and autonomous institutions",
    "option_d": "Inclusion of information from the accounts of agricultural cooperatives",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020138",
    "question": "What was the growth rate of India's GDP at constant prices for the fiscal year 2016-17, as per the provided data?",
    "answer": "760.00%",
    "explanation": "The growth rate of GDP at constant prices is calculated by comparing the GDP of two consecutive years, adjusted for inflation This gives a more accurate picture of the real growth of the economy, as it removes the impact of inflation\n\nIn the case of India, the GDP growth rate at constant prices has been declining in recent years The growth rate in 2016-17 was lower than the growth rate of 76% in 2015-16 This decline is attributed to a number of factors, including the impact of demonetisation and the slowdown in the global economy",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "760.00%",
    "option_b": "710.00%",
    "option_c": "1190.00%",
    "option_d": "560.00%",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020139",
    "question": "Which component of the national income is estimated to be Rs 11153 lakh crore for the fiscal year 2016-17?",
    "answer": "GVA at basic constant prices",
    "explanation": "The GVA is the total value of goods and services produced in an economy, minus the value of intermediate inputs used in their production It is a measure of the productivity of an economy\n\nThe GVA at basic prices is calculated by adding up the value of output from all the different sectors of the economy, such as agriculture, manufacturing, services, etc It is a more comprehensive measure of economic activity than the GDP, as it does not take into account taxes and subsidies\n\nThe GVA at basic prices for the fiscal year 2016-17 is estimated to be Rs 11153 lakh crore, showing a growth rate of 66% over the GVA for the year 2015-16 of Rs 10491 lakh crore\n\nThe growth rate of the GVA at basic prices is lower than the growth rate of the GDP, as the GDP takes into account taxes and subsidies However, the GVA is a more accurate measure of economic activity, as it does not take into account these distortions\n\nThe growth of the GVA in 2016-17 was lower than the growth rate in 2015-16, but it was still positive This indicates that the Indian economy was still growing, albeit at a slower pace",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "GDP at constant prices",
    "option_b": "GVA at basic constant prices",
    "option_c": "PCI at constant prices",
    "option_d": "GVA at factor cost",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020140",
    "question": "What was the growth rate of India's per capita income (PCI) at constant prices for the fiscal year 2016-17?",
    "answer": "560.00%",
    "explanation": "The growth rate of India's per capita income (PCI) at constant prices for the fiscal year 2016-17 was 7%\n\nThis is according to the provisional estimates of annual national income, 2016-17 released by the Press Information Bureau The per capita income in real terms (at 2011-12 prices) for the year 2016-17 is estimated to attain a level of 82,269 as compared to77,803 for the year 2015-16\n\nThe growth rate of PCI at constant prices is calculated by comparing the PCI of two consecutive years, adjusted for inflation This gives a more accurate picture of the real growth in the standard of living of the people, as it removes the impact of inflation",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "620.00%",
    "option_b": "560.00%",
    "option_c": "1040.00%",
    "option_d": "740.00%",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020141",
    "question": "In the formula \"National Income at Factor Cost = NNP at Market Cost – Indirect Taxes + Subsidies,\" which components are added and subtracted from NNP at Market Cost?",
    "answer": "Indirect Taxes and Subsidies",
    "explanation": "Indirect taxes are subtracted from NNP at Market Cost because they are not paid by the factors of production They are paid by consumers or businesses to the government\nSubsidies are added to NNP at Market Cost because they are paid by the government to the factors of production They are intended to reduce the cost of production and encourage economic activity",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Indirect Taxes and Direct Taxes",
    "option_b": "Subsidies and Direct Taxes",
    "option_c": "Indirect Taxes and Subsidies",
    "option_d": "Corporate Income Tax and Subsidies",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020142",
    "question": "What is the purpose of revising the base year of economic indices, as recommended by the National Statistical Commission?",
    "answer": "To reflect changes in the structure of the economy",
    "explanation": "Capture structural changes in the economy As the economy changes, the composition of goods and services produced, the relative importance of different sectors, and the prices of goods and services change as well The base year should be revised to reflect these changes in order to ensure that the indices are a accurate measure of economic activity\n\nImprove the accuracy of the indices Over time, the weights used to calculate the indices may become outdated, leading to inaccuracies Revising the base year allows for the weights to be updated, which can improve the accuracy of the indices\n\nMake the indices more comparable over time When the base year is revised, the indices are re-calculated using the new weights This makes the indices more comparable over time, as they are not affected by changes in the weights",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "To update the tax rates for better accuracy",
    "option_b": "To reflect changes in the structure of the economy",
    "option_c": "To increase government revenue",
    "option_d": "To adjust for inflation rates",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020143",
    "question": "What is the main rationale for adding subsidies to the national income at market cost in India?",
    "answer": "To avoid distortion in the value of subsidized goods and services",
    "explanation": "The main rationale for adding subsidies to the national income at market cost in India is to reflect the true value of goods and services produced in the economy Subsidies are payments made by the government to producers to reduce the cost of production By adding subsidies to the national income, we are effectively taking into account the fact that the producers are receiving a lower price for their goods and services, which means that the value of the goods and services is lower",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "To avoid distortion in the value of subsidized goods and services",
    "option_b": "To increase government revenue",
    "option_c": "To encourage higher consumption",
    "option_d": "To align with international accounting standards",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020144",
    "question": "Which sector's estimates of Gross Value Added (GVA) are provided at basic prices according to the revised methodology?",
    "answer": "Manufacturing sector",
    "explanation": "The estimates of Gross Value Added (GVA) at basic prices are provided for all sectors of the economy according to the revised methodology This is a change from the previous methodology, which only provided GVA at basic prices for the agricultural sector The revised methodology is in line with international practice and provides a more accurate measure of the value of output produced in the economy",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Financial sector",
    "option_b": "Manufacturing sector",
    "option_c": "Agricultural sector",
    "option_d": "Services sector",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020145",
    "question": "What is the primary difference between GDP at constant market prices and GDP at factor cost?",
    "answer": "GDP at factor cost does not include indirect taxes and subsidies",
    "explanation": "The primary difference between GDP at constant market prices and GDP at factor cost is that GDP at constant market prices includes indirect taxes, while GDP at factor cost does not Indirect taxes are taxes that are levied on goods and services, such as sales tax and excise duty They are not paid by the factors of production, but by the consumers or businesses that purchase the goods and services GDP at factor cost is a more accurate measure of the income earned by the factors of production because it excludes indirect taxes",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "GDP at constant market prices includes indirect taxes and subsidies",
    "option_b": "GDP at factor cost includes direct taxes and subsidies",
    "option_c": "GDP at factor cost does not include indirect taxes and subsidies",
    "option_d": "GDP at constant market prices does not account for inflation",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020146",
    "question": "In the formula for calculating National Income at Factor Cost, the indirect taxes need to be ______________ from the NNP at Market Cost",
    "answer": "deducted",
    "explanation": "In the formula for calculating National Income at Factor Cost, the indirect taxes need to be subtracted from the NNP at Market Cost This is because indirect taxes are not paid by the factors of production, but by the consumers or businesses that purchase the goods and services By subtracting indirect taxes from the NNP at Market Cost, we are effectively taking into account the fact that the factors of production are not receiving the full amount of the price of the goods and services they produce",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "de,duc,ted",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020147",
    "question": "The revised methodology for calculating National Accounts in India, as per the System of National Accounts (SNA)-2008, includes improved coverage of activities of ______________ institutions",
    "answer": "local bodies",
    "explanation": "The revised methodology for calculating National Accounts in India, as per the System of National Accounts (SNA)-2008, includes improved coverage of activities of financial institutions This is a change from the previous methodology, which did not include financial institutions in the calculation of national accounts The revised methodology is in line with international practice and provides a more accurate measure of the economic activity in the country",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "lo,ca,l b,odi,es",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020148",
    "question": "The growth rate of India's Per Capita Income (PCI) at constant prices for the fiscal year 2016-17 was ______________ percent",
    "answer": "Seven",
    "explanation": "The growth rate of India's Per Capita Income (PCI) at constant prices for the fiscal year 2016-17 was 7% This is according to the provisional estimates of annual national income, 2016-17 released by the Press Information Bureau The per capita income in real terms (at 2011-12 prices) for the year 2016-17 is estimated to attain a level of 82,269 as compared to77,803 for the year 2015-16",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "sev,en,mo",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020149",
    "question": "match the Economic Components with Descriptions",
    "answer": "GVA at basic prices - Measured by GDP at constant market prices and excluding indirect taxes and subsidies, GDP at constant market prices - Derived from GVA at basic prices by subtracting production taxes and subsidies, GVA at factor cost - Estimated by adding subsidies to GVA at basic prices, National Income at Factor Cost - The final result of deducting indirect taxes and adding subsidies to NNP at Market Cost",
    "explanation": "GVA at basic prices represents the value of output generated within the economy, excluding production taxes and adding subsidies The description A fits this component \n\nGDP at constant market prices measures the total value of goods and services produced within the economy, adjusted for inflation, and excluding indirect taxes and subsidies The description B aligns with this component \n\nGVA at factor cost refers to the value of output produced minus production taxes and adding subsidies Description C matches this economic component\n\n National Income at Factor Cost is derived by subtracting indirect taxes and adding subsidies to Net National Product (NNP) at Market Cost Description D is associated with this component",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "GVA at basic prices - Measured by GDP at constant market prices and excluding indirect taxes and subsidies",
    "option_b": "National Income at Factor Cost,The final result of deducting indirect taxes and adding subsidies to NNP at Market Cost",
    "option_c": "GDP at constant market prices,Derived from GVA at basic prices by subtracting production taxes and subsidies",
    "option_d": "GVA at factor cost,Estimated by adding subsidies to GVA at basic prices",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020150",
    "question": "match the Changes in National Income Accounting with Implications",
    "answer": "Base Year Revision - Reflects changes in the economy's structure and inflation, Comprehensive Coverage of Financial Sector - Enhanced data from stock brokers, exchanges, and regulatory bodies, Incorporation of Annual Company Accounts - Improved accounting for non-manufacturing activities of companies",
    "explanation": "Base Year Revision affects how economic data is analyzed over time It allows for accurate comparison by adjusting for changes in inflation and the economy's structure, thus addressing the implications mentioned in B \n\nComprehensive Coverage of Financial Sector implies the incorporation of data from stock brokers, exchanges, and regulatory bodies, which leads to more accurate representation of economic activities, as stated in C \n\nIncorporation of Annual Company Accounts improves accounting for non-manufacturing activities of companies, capturing a more holistic view of their economic contributions, as indicated in A \n\nAdjustment for Subsidies ensures that the valuation of goods and services includes their actual value, accounting for subsidies This aligns with the implication mentioned in D",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Base Year Revision,Reflects changes in the economy's structure and inflation",
    "option_b": "Comprehensive Coverage of Financial Sector,Enhanced data from stock brokers, exchanges, and regulatory bodies",
    "option_c": "Incorporation of Annual Company Accounts,Improved accounting for non-manufacturing activities of companies",
    "option_d": "Adjustment for Subsidies,Ensures accurate valuation of subsidized goods and services in the national income",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020151",
    "question": "Net National Income is (1997)",
    "answer": "Net National Product at factor cost",
    "explanation": "National Income is the money value of all final goods and services produced in an economy during a financial year At the level of an economy, value of final goods and services is equal to the total income of all factors of production viz labour, capital, land and entrepreneurship",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Net National Product at market price",
    "option_b": "Net National Product at factor cost",
    "option_c": "Net Domestic Product at market price",
    "option_d": "Net Domestic Product at factor cost",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020152",
    "question": "The most appropriate measure of economic growth is its: (2007)",
    "answer": "Per Capita Real Income",
    "explanation": "Per capita real income is nothing but NNP at factor cost It means national income is sum total of all factor incomes adjusted for increase in prices",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Gross Domestic Product of a country’s",
    "option_b": "Net National Product",
    "option_c": "Net Domestic Product",
    "option_d": "Per Capita Real Income",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020153",
    "question": "The term National Income represents: (2001)",
    "answer": "gross national product at market prices minus depreciation and indirect taxes plus subsidies",
    "explanation": "gross national product at market prices minus depreciation and indirect taxes plus subsidies",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "gross national product at market prices minus depreciation",
    "option_b": "gross national product at market prices minus depreciation plus net factor income from abroad",
    "option_c": "gross national product at market prices minus depreciation and indirect taxes plus subsidies",
    "option_d": "gross national product at market prices minus net factor income from abroad",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020154",
    "question": "Which one of the following is the correct sequence in the decreasing order of contribution of different sectors to the Gross Domestic Product of India? (2007)",
    "answer": "Services - Industry - Agriculture",
    "explanation": "Contribution of different sectors to national income Services - 551%, Industry- 264%, Agriculture -185%",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Services - Industry - Agriculture",
    "option_b": "Services - Agriculture - Industry",
    "option_c": "Industry - Services - Agriculture",
    "option_d": "Industry - Agriculture - Services",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020155",
    "question": "With reference to’ Indian economy, consider the following statements:\n1 The Gross Domestic Product (GDP) has increased by four times in the last 10 years\n2 The percentage share of public sector in GDP has declined in the last 10 years\nWhich of the statement given above is/are correct? (2010)",
    "answer": "2 Only",
    "explanation": "The percentage share of public sector in GDP has declined in the last 10 years",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 Only",
    "option_b": "2 Only",
    "option_c": "Both 1 and 2",
    "option_d": "Neither 1 nor 2",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "020156",
    "question": "The national income of a country for a given period is equal to the: (2013-1)",
    "answer": "money value of final goods and services produced",
    "explanation": "Capital Account comprises of Foreign loans, Foreign Direct Investment and Portfolio Investment Capital Account is the net result of public and private international",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Introdution >> The Idea of National Income",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "total value of goods and services produced by the nationals",
    "option_b": "sum of total consumption and investment expenditure",
    "option_c": "sum of personal income of all individuals",
    "option_d": "money value of final goods and services produced",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030101",
    "question": "In which decade did social scientists begin challenging the concept of the 'economic man' and studying human actions more closely?",
    "answer": "1980s",
    "explanation": "In the 1980s, social scientists began challenging the concept of the 'economic man' which assumed humans act rationally They started studying actual human behavior and motivations more closely at the time Therefore, the 1980s is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "1960s",
    "option_b": "1970s",
    "option_c": "1990s",
    "option_d": "2000s",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030102",
    "question": "What is the term 'progress' commonly used by experts to denote?",
    "answer": "Betterment or improvement in anything",
    "explanation": "Progress refers to general betterment or improvement in any context It is not specific to only economic growth, technology, social issues etc Therefore, 'betterment or improvement in anything' is the most general and accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Economic growth",
    "option_b": "Technological advancement",
    "option_c": "Betterment or improvement in anything",
    "option_d": "Social development",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030103",
    "question": "What does the term \"economic growth\" in economics refer to?",
    "answer": "Increase in economic variables over a period of time",
    "explanation": "Economic growth specifically refers to the increase or growth in major economic metrics like GDP, national income, productivity, manufacturing etc over a defined period of time Therefore, 'increase in economic variables over a period of time' is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Increase in economic variables over a period of time",
    "option_b": "Expansion of physical infrastructure",
    "option_c": "Decrease in employment",
    "option_d": "Rise in inflation",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030104",
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): Economic growth is a quantifiable measure of the increase in economic variables over a specific period of time\n\nReason (R): Economic growth plays a crucial role in national and international economic analyses, informing policy decisions and financial planning",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true, and R is the correct explanation of A",
    "explanation": "Both statements are true - economic growth quantifies the increase in key economic variables over time and this growth data informs important policy decisions and financial planning Moreover, the reason correctly explains why economic growth is measured - it is to guide economic policies and planning Therefore, 'Both A and R are true, R explains A' is the most accurate option",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true, and R is the correct explanation of A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true, but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
    "option_c": "A is true, but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false, but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030105",
    "question": "Which of the following is an example of economic growth?",
    "answer": "An increase in the production of automobiles by 10% over the last year",
    "explanation": "An increase in automobile production directly signifies economic growth through expansion of the manufacturing sector More automobiles produced over time demonstrates rising productivity and output Therefore, 'An increase in the production of automobiles by 10% over the last year' is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "An increase in the production of automobiles by 10% over the last year",
    "option_b": "A decrease in exports",
    "option_c": "Stable unemployment rate",
    "option_d": "A decrease in the number of new startups",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030106",
    "question": "Which term is used to describe the difference between two periods converted into percentage form?",
    "answer": "Growth rate",
    "explanation": "Growth rate measures the change or difference between two time periods in percentage terms It provides insight into how much a variable has changed over a specific time frame Therefore, 'Growth rate' correctly fills the blank",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Growth rate",
    "option_b": "Inflation rate",
    "option_c": "Interest rate",
    "option_d": "Production rate",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030107",
    "question": "What type of progress is primarily associated with economic growth?",
    "answer": "Quantitative progress",
    "explanation": "Economic growth focuses on quantitative progress like higher GDP, industrial production, national income etc Qualitative aspects like social development, equality, quality of life are not its direct concern Therefore, 'Quantitative progress' is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Quantitative progress",
    "option_b": "Qualitative progress",
    "option_c": "Social development",
    "option_d": "Environmental sustainability",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030108",
    "question": "In the context of economics, what is economic development primarily concerned with?",
    "answer": "Quality of life",
    "explanation": "Economic development is primarily concerned with improving broader human welfare and people's overall quality of life in areas like healthcare, education, standard of living It is not just about higher incomes Therefore, 'Quality of life' is the most comprehensive answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Quality of life",
    "option_b": "Quantity of production",
    "option_c": "Expansion of infrastructure",
    "option_d": "Standard of living",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030109",
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): Economic development encompasses both quantitative and qualitative progress in an economy, whereas economic growth primarily represents quantitative progress\n\nReason (R): The distinction between economic growth and economic development emerged after the observation that some economies experienced high growth but low development, leading to the formation of the field of development economics",
    "answer": "Both assertion (A) and reason (R) are true, and reason (R) is the correct explanation of assertion (A)",
    "explanation": "The statements correctly distinguish economic development and economic growth Economic development includes both quantitative metrics and qualitative aspects of human welfare Economic growth focuses narrowly on quantitative factors like incomes, production etc The reason also correctly explains how this distinction arose - by observing instances of growth sans human development Therefore, 'Both A and R are true, R explains A' is the most accurate option",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both assertion (A) and reason (R) are true, and reason (R) is the correct explanation of assertion (A)",
    "option_b": "Both assertion (A) and reason (R) are true, but reason (R) is NOT the correct explanation of assertion (A)",
    "option_c": "Assertion (A) is true, but reason (R) is false",
    "option_d": "Assertion (A) is false, but reason (R) is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030110",
    "question": "Which of the following statements are aspects of economic development: \n1. Level of nutrition \n2. Availability of healthcare facilities \n3. Level of education",
    "answer": "All of the above",
    "explanation": "Nutrition, healthcare facilities, and education level are all key aspects that comprise economic development as they lead to an improved quality of life Therefore, 'All of the above' is the most comprehensive and accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Only 1 and 2",
    "option_b": "Only 2 and 3",
    "option_c": "Only 1 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030111",
    "question": "Economic development requires assuring a basic minimum level of what?",
    "answer": "Income",
    "explanation": "A basic minimum level of income needs to be guaranteed before initiating broader economic development, as income provides for essential human needs like food, healthcare etc Without this, quality of life cannot improve Therefore, 'Income' correctly fills the blank",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Income",
    "option_b": "Education",
    "option_c": "Employment",
    "option_d": "Infrastructure",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030112",
    "question": "Which statement correctly describes the relationship between economic growth and economic development?",
    "answer": "Economic development includes both quantitative and qualitative progress, while economic growth primarily emphasizes quantitative progress",
    "explanation": "Economic development encompasses both quantitative progress and qualitative improvements in areas like healthcare, education, society Economic growth focuses primarily on quantitative metrics like incomes, production Therefore, this statement best describes their relationship and is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Economic development includes both quantitative and qualitative progress, while economic growth primarily emphasizes quantitative progress",
    "option_b": "Economic growth and economic development are synonymous terms",
    "option_c": "Economic growth leads to economic development without exceptions",
    "option_d": "Economic development solely depends on technological advancements",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030113",
    "question": "Which combination represents an economy experiencing significant economic growth alongside substantial improvements in human well-being?\n1 Higher growth but lower development\n2 Lower growth but higher development\n3 Higher growth and higher development\n4 Lower growth and lower development",
    "answer": "Only 3",
    "explanation": "High economic growth along with high human development represents an economy with both quantitative expansion and improvements in quality of life Therefore, 'Only 3' which states 'Higher growth and higher development' is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Only 1",
    "option_b": "Only 2 and 3",
    "option_c": "Only 1 and 3",
    "option_d": "Only 3",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030114",
    "question": "What is the primary challenge in measuring development?",
    "answer": "Determining the factors that constitute development",
    "explanation": "The main difficulty in quantifying development is determining appropriate factors and indicators, as development comprises both quantitative and qualitative aspects There is lack of consensus on how to measure qualitative dimensions Therefore, 'Determining the factors that constitute development' is the most comprehensive and accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Defining economic growth accurately",
    "option_b": "Determining the factors that constitute development",
    "option_c": "Identifying the leading economists for guidance",
    "option_d": "Estimating the GDP of underdeveloped regions",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030115",
    "question": "Consider the follwing codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion(A): The main difficulty in quantifying development is that it involves both quantitative and qualitative aspects\n \nReason(R): Qualitative aspects such as beauty and taste cannot be measured using scales",
    "answer": "Both the Assertion (A) and the Reason (R) are true, and the reason is the correct explanation of the statement",
    "explanation": "The assertion that development has quantitative and qualitative aspects is true The reason that qualitative factors like beauty cannot be easily measured is also true and correctly explains the core difficulty in measuring development Therefore, option A is the most accurate choice",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both assertion (A) and reason (R) are true, and reason (R) is the correct explanation of assertion (A)",
    "option_b": "Both assertion (A) and reason (R) are true, but reason (R) is NOT the correct explanation of assertion (A)",
    "option_c": "Assertion (A) is true, but reason (R) is false",
    "option_d": "Assertion (A) is false, but reason (R) is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030116",
    "question": "What does HDI stand for in the context of measuring development?",
    "answer": "Human Development Index",
    "explanation": "HDI stands for Human Development Index It is a composite statistic of life expectancy, education, and per capita income indicators, which are used to rank countries into four tiers of human development A country scores higher HDI when the lifespan is higher, the education level is higher, and the GDP per capita is higher\n\nThe HDI was developed by the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) in 1990 It is used to measure the progress of countries towards achieving the Millennium Development Goals (MDGs) and the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs)",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Humanitarian Development Index",
    "option_b": "High Development Indicator",
    "option_c": "Human Development Index",
    "option_d": "Health and Education Index",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030117",
    "question": "The Human Development Report (HDR) measures development by combining three indicators: Health, Education, and _______",
    "answer": "Standard of Living",
    "explanation": "Health is measured by life expectancy at birth This is a measure of the average number of years a person can expect to live if current mortality patterns continue\n\nEducation is measured by mean years of schooling and expected years of schooling Mean years of schooling is the average number of years of formal education that a person has completed Expected years of schooling is the number of years of schooling that a child can expect to complete if current enrolment patterns continue\n\nStandard of living is measured by gross national income (GNI) per capita GNI per capita is a measure of the average income of a country's citizens",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Wealth",
    "option_b": "Happiness",
    "option_c": "Standard of Living",
    "option_d": "Economic Growth",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030118",
    "question": "match the following components of the HDI with their respective measurements:",
    "answer": "Education component - Mean years of schooling, Health component - Life expectancy at birth, Standard of Living component - Gross National Income per capita,  Living component - Nil",
    "explanation": "The HDI's education component measures mean years of schooling, health component measures life expectancy at birth, and standard of living measures GNI per capita Therefore, option C which matches these correctly is the right answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Education component,Mean years of schooling",
    "option_b": "Health component,Life expectancy at birth",
    "option_c": "Standard of Living component,Gross National Income per capita",
    "option_d": "Living component,Nil",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030119",
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\nAssertion(A): The HDI uses the logarithm of income to reflect the diminishing importance of income with increasing GNI \nReason(R): Logarithmic scales allow for easier comparison of income levels across countries with differing GNI values",
    "answer": "Both the assertion and the reason are true, but the reason is not the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "explanation": "The assertion that HDI uses logarithmic income is true However, the reason regarding easier comparison doesn't directly explain this use, hence doesn't explain the assertion Therefore, option B is the most accurate choice",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both the assertion and the reason are true, and the reason is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_b": "Both the assertion and the reason are true, but the reason is not the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_c": "The assertion is true, but the reason is false",
    "option_d": "The assertion is false, but the reason is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030120",
    "question": "Consider the following statement and conclusion:\nStatement: The UNDP classifies countries into three categories based on their achievements on the HDI \nConclusion: Low Human Development Countries have an HDI range of 0000–0499 points",
    "answer": "The statement is true, but the conclusion is false",
    "explanation": "The statement that UNDP categorizes countries by HDI achievements is true However, the conclusion about the HDI range for low human development countries is inaccurate Therefore, option B is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both the statement and the conclusion are true",
    "option_b": "The statement is true, but the conclusion is false",
    "option_c": "The statement is false, but the conclusion is true",
    "option_d": "Both the statement and the conclusion are false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030121",
    "question": "The HDI combines three indicators to measure development Which of the following is NOT one of those indicators?",
    "answer": "Happiness",
    "explanation": "HDI combines health, education, and standard of living to measure human development Happiness is not used as an indicator Therefore, 'Happiness' is the unambiguously correct answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Health",
    "option_b": "Education",
    "option_c": "Happiness",
    "option_d": "Standard of Living",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030122",
    "question": "What parameters were emphasized by member countries while using the Human Development Report (HDR) to quantify developmental efforts?",
    "answer": "Income, education, and life expectancy",
    "explanation": "Life expectancy at birth: This is a measure of the average number of years a person can expect to live if current mortality patterns continue It is a good indicator of the overall health of a population\nMean years of schooling: This is the average number of years of formal education that a person has completed It is a good indicator of the educational attainment of a population\nGNI per capita: This is a measure of the average income of a country's citizens It is a good indicator of the standard of living of a population\nGender inequality: This is a measure of the differences between men and women in terms of access to education, health care, and other resources It is a good indicator of the level of gender equality in a country\nPoverty: This is a measure of the number of people living below a certain income threshold It is a good indicator of the level of poverty in a country\nEnvironmental sustainability: This is a measure of the ability of a country to meet the needs of its people without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs It is a good indicator of the level of environmental sustainability in a country",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Cultural promotion",
    "option_b": "Income, education, and life expectancy",
    "option_c": "Material resources and technological advancements",
    "option_d": "Good governance and economic growth",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030123",
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): The UNDP-designed HDR's focus on income, education, and life expectancy reflects a consensus on the determinants of development \nReason (R): Material aspects are the only relevant factors for measuring development",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true, but R is not the correct explanation of A",
    "explanation": "The assertion that the HDR's parameters represent a consensus is true However, the reason that only material factors matter is false - the HDR doesn't encompass all dimensions of development Therefore, option B is the most accurate choice",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true, and R is the correct explanation of A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true, but R is not the correct explanation of A",
    "option_c": "A is true, but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false, but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030124",
    "question": "Consider the following statement and conclusion:\nStatement: The London School of Economics' critique of the HDI aimed to point out its incompleteness \nConclusion: The HDI lacks any significant impact on policymaking",
    "answer": "The statement is true, but the conclusion is false",
    "explanation": "The statement about the London School critique aiming to highlight HDI's limitations is true But the conclusion that HDI lacks policy impact is false and not implied Therefore, option B which states the statement is true but the conclusion is false is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both the statement and conclusion are true",
    "option_b": "Both the statement and conclusion are false",
    "option_c": "The statement is true, but the conclusion is false",
    "option_d": "The statement is false, but the conclusion is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030125",
    "question": "The London School of Economics' critique aimed to highlight the ________ of the HDI",
    "answer": "limitations",
    "explanation": "Some of the limitations of the HDI include:\n\nIt does not take into account inequality within countries\nIt does not take into account other important aspects of development, such as environmental sustainability and social justice\nThe weights given to the different indicators are arbitrary\nThe HDI is not a measure of happiness or well-being",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "li,mi,ta,ti,ons",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030126",
    "question": "Consider the following statement and conclusion:\nStatement: The UNDP-designed HDR's parameters of income, education, and life expectancy are important aspects of development \nConclusion: The HDR's parameters encompass all dimensions of development",
    "answer": "The statement is true, but the conclusion is false",
    "explanation": "The statement about HDR parameters being important development aspects is true However, the conclusion that HDR encompasses all dimensions of development is false Therefore, option B is the most accurate choice",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both the statement and conclusion are true",
    "option_b": "Both the statement and conclusion are false",
    "option_c": "The statement is true, but the conclusion is false",
    "option_d": "The statement is false, but the conclusion is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030127",
    "question": "What does GNH stand for?",
    "answer": "Gross National Happiness",
    "explanation": "GNH stands for Gross National Happiness It is a measure of the well-being of a country's citizens It was developed in Bhutan in the 1970s as an alternative to Gross Domestic Product (GDP), which is a measure of a country's economic output\n\nGNH is based on the belief that happiness is more important than material wealth It includes nine domains of well-being:\nPhysical health\nMental health\nTime use\nEducation\nEmployment\nCommunity vitality\nCultural diversity and resilience\nLiving standards\nGood governance\nEcological diversity and resilience",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Good National Hygiene",
    "option_b": "Gross National Health",
    "option_c": "Great National Happiness",
    "option_d": "Gross National Happiness",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030128",
    "question": "Which unique aspect did Bhutan include in their GNH index?",
    "answer": "Promoting cultural and ethical values",
    "explanation": "Bhutan's Gross National Happiness (GNH) index includes a unique aspect of community vitality This domain assesses the strength and resilience of communities, as well as the sense of belonging and social support that people feel\n\nCommunity vitality is important because it can help to promote happiness and well-being in a number of ways For example, strong communities can provide people with a sense of identity and belonging, which can help to buffer against stress and adversity They can also provide people with social support, which can help to improve their mental and physical health",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Higher income",
    "option_b": "Environmental sustainability",
    "option_c": "Good governance",
    "option_d": "Promoting cultural and ethical values",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030129",
    "question": "Material progress alone cannot guarantee what?",
    "answer": "True happiness",
    "explanation": "Material progress alone cannot guarantee happiness, fulfillment, or well-being\n\nMaterial progress refers to the increase in the availability of goods and services It is often measured by indicators such as GDP, income per capita, and consumption levels\n\nWhile material progress can improve people's lives in many ways, it cannot guarantee happiness, fulfillment, or well-being This is because happiness, fulfillment, and well-being are also influenced by other factors, such as relationships, health, and personal values",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Economic growth",
    "option_b": "High HDI rank",
    "option_c": "Poverty reduction",
    "option_d": "True happiness",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030130",
    "question": "The GNH advocates promoting _________ values unlike the HDI",
    "answer": "ethical and spiritual",
    "explanation": "GNH advocates promoting ethical and spiritual values unlike HDI's sole focus on material development Therefore, 'ethical and spiritual' correctly fills the blank",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "eth,ica,l a,nd s,pi,ri,tu,al",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030131",
    "question": "Which of the following is a valid criticism of Standard development model?",
    "answer": "Over-emphasizing material aspects",
    "explanation": "The SDM is based on a Western view of development\nThe SDM is focused on economic growth\nThe SDM is top-down\nThe SDM is not sustainable\nThe SDM is not equitable",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Ignoring sustainability",
    "option_b": "Increasing inequality",
    "option_c": "Limiting economic growth",
    "option_d": "Over-emphasizing material aspects",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030132",
    "question": "After 9/11, interest grew in assessing:",
    "answer": "Possibilities for multicultural coexistence",
    "explanation": "After 9/11, interest grew in assessing if different cultures could coexist globally - hence options about multiculturalism is most accurate",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Global terrorism levels",
    "option_b": "Redefining development",
    "option_c": "Humanitarian aid needs",
    "option_d": "Possibilities for multicultural coexistence",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030133",
    "question": "Experts suggest the idea of development should include which of the following values?",
    "answer": "Spiritual values",
    "explanation": "Experts suggest incorporating spiritual values while defining development beyond just material progress Therefore, this is the most accurate answer\n\nThe GNH advocates promoting non-material values unlike the HDI\nThe GNH is a more holistic measure of development than the HDI It takes into account a wider range of factors that contribute to well-being\nThe GNH is still a relatively new concept, and it is still being developed However, it has the potential to be a more meaningful measure of development than the HDI",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Political freedoms",
    "option_b": "Cultural promotion",
    "option_c": "Income equality",
    "option_d": "Spiritual values",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030134",
    "question": "Which organization released the World Happiness Report?",
    "answer": "Sustainable Development Solutions Network",
    "explanation": "The World Happiness Report is a publication of the Sustainable Development Solutions Network (SDSN), a global network of experts working to achieve the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) The SDSN is a collaboration between the United Nations and the Bertelsmann Foundation\n\nThe first World Happiness Report was released in 2012 The report is published annually and ranks countries according to their happiness levels The report is based on a survey of people in different countries about their levels of happiness\n\nThe 2023 World Happiness Report was released on March 18, 2023 Finland was ranked the happiest country in the world, followed by Denmark, Iceland, Switzerland, and the Netherlands The United States was ranked 16th, while India was ranked 136th",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "United Nations",
    "option_b": "World Health Organization",
    "option_c": "World Bank",
    "option_d": "Sustainable Development Solutions Network",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030135",
    "question": "Consider the World Happiness Report:\n\nStatement 1: The World Happiness Report ranks countries solely based on their GDP per capita\nStatement 2: The World Happiness Report assesses well-being by considering factors such as income, social support, and life expectancy\nStatement 3: The World Happiness Report is published annually by a collaboration of United Nations member states",
    "answer": "Only Statements 1 and 3 are correct",
    "explanation": "Statement 1 is False The World Happiness Report does not rank countries solely based on their GDP per capita It considers a variety of factors, including income, social support, life expectancy, freedom to make life choices, generosity, and absence of corruption\n\nStatement 2 is True The World Happiness Report assesses well-being by considering factors such as income, social support, and life expectancy It also considers other factors, such as freedom to make life choices, generosity, and absence of corruption\n\nStatement 3 is True The World Happiness Report is published annually by a collaboration of United Nations member states The SDSN, a global network of experts working to achieve the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs), is responsible for publishing the report",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Only Statement 1 is correct",
    "option_b": "Only Statements 1 and 3 are correct",
    "option_c": "Only Statements 2 and 3 are correct",
    "option_d": "Only Statement 2 is correct",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030136",
    "question": "Which parameter is NOT used to rank countries in World Happiness Report?",
    "answer": "Employment rate",
    "explanation": "Employment rate is not used to rank countries in WHR which focuses on aspects like GDP, social support, freedom instead Therefore, this is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "GDP per capita",
    "option_b": "Social support",
    "option_c": "Freedom",
    "option_d": "Employment rate",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030137",
    "question": "_____ and Autonomy are significant drivers of happiness at workplaces",
    "answer": "Worklife balance",
    "explanation": "Work-life balance and autonomy are key drivers of workplace happiness as per numerous studies Therefore, this correctly matches the provided parameters",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Wo,rk,li,fe b,al,an,ce",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030138",
    "question": "The World Hapiness Report advocates building _______ and Healthy Lives not guns or walls",
    "answer": "Social trust",
    "explanation": "The WHR advocates building social trust and healthy lives, not factors like guns or walls Therefore, the blanks are accurately filled",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "So,ci,al t,ru,st",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030139",
    "question": "When viewed as an emotion, happiness refers to feelings experienced:",
    "answer": "In the present moment",
    "explanation": "Viewing happiness as an emotion refers to present feelings, not future, overall, or long term Therefore, 'In the present moment' is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "For the future",
    "option_b": "Overall in life",
    "option_c": "Long term",
    "option_d": "In the present moment",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030140",
    "question": "Viewing happiness as life evaluation relates to which of the following?",
    "answer": "Overall satisfaction with one's life",
    "explanation": "Happiness as evaluation relates to overall life satisfaction rather than just daily joy or positive emotions Therefore, this is the most accurate choice",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Daily joy",
    "option_b": "Having purpose",
    "option_c": "Meeting goals",
    "option_d": "Overall satisfaction with one's life",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030141",
    "question": "When asked about happiness, What do people differentiate between?",
    "answer": "Short term emotions and long term satisfaction",
    "explanation": "Short-term happiness vs long-term happiness: Some people might focus on short-term happiness, such as feeling good in the moment Others might focus on long-term happiness, such as achieving their goals or making a difference in the world",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Personal and community happiness",
    "option_b": "Present and future",
    "option_c": "Daily joy and life fulfillment",
    "option_d": "Short term emotions and long term satisfaction",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030142",
    "question": "Which measures does the World Happiness Report incorporate?",
    "answer": "Subjective well-being and life evaluations",
    "explanation": "The World Happiness Report incorporates six measures to determine happiness:\n\nGDP per capita: This measures the average income of a country's citizens\nSocial support: This measures the strength of social networks and support systems in a country\nLife expectancy: This measures the average number of years a person can expect to live in a country\nFreedom to make life choices: This measures the degree to which people in a country have the freedom to make choices about their lives\nGenerosity: This measures the level of giving and volunteering in a country\nAbsence of corruption: This measures the level of corruption in a country",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Governance and income",
    "option_b": "Emotions and purpose",
    "option_c": "Relationships and leisure",
    "option_d": "Subjective well-being and life evaluations",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030143",
    "question": "match the types of happiness to their descriptions:",
    "answer": "Affective - Emotions, Evaluative - Life satisfaction, Hedonic happiness - smile, Eudaimonic happiness -Feel",
    "explanation": "The types - affective and evaluative, match correctly to the descriptions - emotions and life satisfaction respectively Therefore, this represents the right match",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Affective,Emotions",
    "option_b": "Evaluative,Life satisfaction",
    "option_c": "Hedonic happiness,smile",
    "option_d": "Eudaimonic happiness,Feel",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030144",
    "question": "Happiness has distinct emotional and evaluative aspects because people can differentiate between their?",
    "answer": "immediate emotions, overall life satisfaction",
    "explanation": "Happiness has distinct emotional and evaluative aspects because people can differentiate between their current feelings and their overall life satisfaction\n\nEmotional happiness refers to the immediate feeling of happiness or joy It is often associated with positive emotions, such as pleasure, contentment, and gratitude\nEvaluative happiness refers to the overall assessment of one's life It is often associated with life satisfaction, contentment, and well-being",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "present feelings, future aspirations",
    "option_b": "daily joy, life fulfillment",
    "option_c": "short-term happiness, long-term bliss",
    "option_d": "immediate emotions, overall life satisfaction",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030145",
    "question": "In 2011, what did a UN resolution encourage countries to measure?",
    "answer": "National happiness levels",
    "explanation": "In 2011, the United Nations General Assembly passed Resolution 65/309, which encouraged countries to measure the happiness and well-being of their citizens The resolution recognized that GDP is not a perfect measure of well-being and that other factors, such as social support, health, and freedom, are also important\n\nThe resolution called on countries to develop national indicators of happiness and well-being and to use these indicators to inform their policies It also called on the UN to promote the measurement of happiness and well-being and to share best practices\n\nThe resolution was a significant step forward in the effort to measure happiness and well-being It has been followed by a number of initiatives, including the World Happiness Report, which is published annually by the Sustainable Development Solutions Network",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Sustainable development goals",
    "option_b": "Poverty rates",
    "option_c": "Human rights protection",
    "option_d": "National happiness levels",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030146",
    "question": "When did the United Nations first publish the World Happiness Report?",
    "answer": "In 2012",
    "explanation": "The United Nations first published the World Happiness Report in 2012 It was published by the Sustainable Development Solutions Network (SDSN), a global network of experts working to achieve the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs)\n\nThe report is based on a survey of people in different countries about their levels of happiness The survey asks questions about people's life satisfaction, their sense of purpose in life, and their experiences of positive and negative emotions\n\nThe report also includes data on a variety of factors that are thought to contribute to happiness, such as GDP per capita, social support, life expectancy, and freedom to make life choices\n\nThe World Happiness Report is an important tool for understanding happiness and well-being It can be used to track progress towards the SDGs, which include a goal of ensuring that all people have a happy and fulfilling life",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "In 2015",
    "option_b": "In 2010",
    "option_c": "In 2000",
    "option_d": "In 2012",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030147",
    "question": "What did Buddha teach material possessions alone cannot provide?",
    "answer": "Inner contentment",
    "explanation": "Buddha taught that material possessions alone do not lead to inner contentment and fulfillment Therefore, this is the most accurate choice",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Wealth",
    "option_b": "Desire fulfillment",
    "option_c": "Social status",
    "option_d": "Inner contentment",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030148",
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n\nStatement I: Despite economic growth, happiness in the US has remained stagnant\nStatement II: Happiness in the US has increased despite economic growth\n\nWhich of the following is correct in respect of the above statements?",
    "answer": "Statement 1 is correct",
    "explanation": "Statement I is true According to the World Happiness Report, the happiness score of the United States has remained stagnant since 2008, despite significant economic growth In 2008, the United States was ranked 14th in the world in terms of happiness In 2023, the United States was ranked 16th\n\nStatement II is false There is no evidence to suggest that happiness in the United States has increased despite economic growth In fact, the evidence suggests the opposite",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Statement 1 is correct",
    "option_b": "Both Statement are Correct",
    "option_c": "Neither 1 or 2",
    "option_d": "Statement 2 is Correct",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030149",
    "question": "True sustainability is often necessary for?",
    "answer": "Protecting nature while raising human well-being",
    "explanation": "True sustainability requires protecting the natural environment while also raising human well-being - it cannot focus on just one goal Therefore, this is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Prioritizing either environment or human needs",
    "option_b": "Pursuing green economic growth to help the poor",
    "option_c": "Reducing consumption and resource use",
    "option_d": "Protecting nature while raising human well-being",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030150",
    "question": "What factor contributed to Finland's educational success?",
    "answer": "A strong sense of community in schools",
    "explanation": "* A strong focus on early childhood education\n* A highly effective teacher training system\n* A focus on equality and inclusion\n* A commitment to lifelong learning\n* A culture of trust and cooperation between teachers, parents, and students",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "High funding for education",
    "option_b": "Rigorous academic standards",
    "option_c": "Excellent teachers",
    "option_d": "A strong sense of community in schools",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030151",
    "question": "What middle path did Buddha and Aristotle recommend?",
    "answer": "Between austerity and material excess",
    "explanation": "Both Buddha and Aristotle recommended a middle path between extremes They believed that it was important to avoid the extremes of indulgence and asceticism Instead, they advocated for a balanced approach to life that would lead to happiness and well-being",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Between poverty and luxury",
    "option_b": "Between moderation and extremism",
    "option_c": "Between deprivation and indulgence",
    "option_d": "Between austerity and material excess",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030152",
    "question": "In the context of the economy, while models assume rationality, economic experts refer to which additional factors?",
    "answer": "emotional, social",
    "explanation": "While economic models assume human rationality, behavioral experts cite emotional and social factors that also influence behavior Therefore, the blanks are accurately filled",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "altruistic, ethical",
    "option_b": "impulsive, biased",
    "option_c": "cohesive, consistent",
    "option_d": "emotional, social",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030153",
    "question": "Rather than income, policies should promote:",
    "answer": "Human happiness and well-being",
    "explanation": "Well-being Policies should promote policies that improve people's well-being, such as access to education, healthcare, and housing\n\nEquality Policies should promote equality, so that everyone has an equal opportunity to succeed\n\nSustainability Policies should promote sustainability, so that future generations can enjoy the same level of well-being",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Equality",
    "option_b": "Meeting basic needs",
    "option_c": "Economic growth",
    "option_d": "Human happiness and well-being",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030154",
    "question": "What factors are linked to high life satisfaction?",
    "answer": "Social trust and community",
    "explanation": "* Strong social relationships\n* Good health\n* A sense of purpose in life\n* Financial security\n* Freedom to make choices\n* A supportive environment",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Low stress lifestyles",
    "option_b": "High social status",
    "option_c": "Career success",
    "option_d": "Social trust and community",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030155",
    "question": "What did Bhutan pioneer measuring?",
    "answer": "Gross National Happiness",
    "explanation": "Bhutan pioneered the novel concept of measuring holistic Gross National Happiness to guide policies Therefore, this is the unambiguously correct answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Human Development Index",
    "option_b": "GDP",
    "option_c": "Sustainable Development Goals",
    "option_d": "Gross National Happiness",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030156",
    "question": "What do high happiness countries like Denmark tend to have?",
    "answer": "Equality and good governance",
    "explanation": "High happiness countries like Denmark have tended to emphasize equality, social welfare, and good democratic governance over just incomes Therefore, this is the most accurate choice\n\n* Strong social safety nets\n* A high level of trust\n* A strong sense of community\n* A focus on work-life balance\n* A healthy work environment",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "High average incomes",
    "option_b": "Low unemployment",
    "option_c": "High-tech industries",
    "option_d": "Equality and good governance",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030157",
    "question": "Why do experts suggest measuring national happiness?",
    "answer": "To identify social issues needing change",
    "explanation": "Experts suggest measuring national happiness because it can help policymakers to make decisions that will improve the well-being of their citizens By measuring happiness, policymakers can see what is working and what is not, and they can make adjustments to their policies accordingly",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "To benchmark against GDP",
    "option_b": "To assess depression rates",
    "option_c": "To guide public policy",
    "option_d": "To identify social issues needing change",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030158",
    "question": "How does Gross National Happiness expand on GDP?",
    "answer": "By incorporating non-material well-being",
    "explanation": "GNH expands on GDP by incorporating non-material aspects of well-being like community, culture, environment GDP focuses just on material incomes and production Therefore, this is the most accurate choice",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "By including sustainability",
    "option_b": "By adding income equality",
    "option_c": "By factoring in leisure time",
    "option_d": "By incorporating non-material well-being",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030159",
    "question": "What do the authors conclude nations should aim to raise through policies?",
    "answer": "Public welfare and happiness",
    "explanation": "The authors conclude nations should craft public policies focused on sustainably raising human welfare and happiness, not just short-term economic growth Therefore, this is the most comprehensive answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "GDP growth",
    "option_b": "Income equality",
    "option_c": "Healthcare access",
    "option_d": "Public welfare and happiness",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030160",
    "question": "Adding insights from _____ can improve policy effectiveness",
    "answer": "behavioral economics",
    "explanation": "Insights from behavioral economics, by studying actual human behavior, can improve the effectiveness and impact of public policies Therefore, the blanks are accurately filled",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "be,hav,io,ra,l e,co,no,mi,cs",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030161",
    "question": "Which Indian sanitation program combined behavior insights with standard subsidies and information?",
    "answer": "Community-Led Total Sanitation",
    "explanation": "The Indian CLTS program combined insights from behavioral science with standard subsidies and info to help reduce open defecation Therefore, option A is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Total Sanitation Campaign",
    "option_b": "Clean India Mission",
    "option_c": "Central Rural Sanitation Program",
    "option_d": "Community-Led Total Sanitation",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030162",
    "question": "Consider the following Statement and Conclusion:\nStatement: More frequent microfinance meetings reduced defaults \nConclusion: Weekly meetings decreased defaults versus monthly",
    "answer": "Statement is true, Conclusion is true",
    "explanation": "The statement that more frequent microfinance group meetings helped reduce loan defaults is true And the conclusion that weekly meetings specifically decreased defaults compared to monthly meetings is also true Therefore, option D which states both parts are true is the most accurate choice",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Statement is false, Conclusion is false",
    "option_b": "Statement is true, Conclusion is false",
    "option_c": "Statement is false, Conclusion is true",
    "option_d": "Statement is true, Conclusion is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030163",
    "question": "Social identities can have a negative impact on ____ group performance",
    "answer": "marginalized",
    "explanation": "Extensive research has shown social identities, like race or caste, can negatively impact performance of marginalized groups by triggering limiting stereotypes in their minds Therefore, the blanks are accurately filled",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "mar,gi,na,li,zed",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030164",
    "question": "Which factor impacts development beyond fiscal policies? \nA Social norms and culture B Monetary policy",
    "answer": "A Social norms and culture",
    "explanation": "Beyond fiscal and monetary policies, social norms and culture have also been shown to influence a country's economic development and growth Therefore, option A is the most accurate assertion",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "B Monetary policy",
    "option_b": "Both A and B",
    "option_c": "Neither A nor B",
    "option_d": "A Social norms and culture",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030165",
    "question": "Societies with strong ____ and trust tend to perform better economically",
    "answer": "honesty",
    "explanation": "Countries and societies with strong honesty, trust, and social cohesion have historically tended to perform better economically as these traits enable cooperation and progress Therefore, the blanks are accurately filled",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "ho,ne,sty",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030166",
    "question": "match crime reduction theories to their descriptions:",
    "answer": "Broken Windows - Visible signs of disorder lead to increased crime, Strain Theory - Crime results from blocked opportunities for success, Social Disorganization Theory - Crime is more likely in socially unstable neighborhoods, Routine activity theory - motivated offenders & suitable targets and the absence of capable guardians",
    "explanation": "Broken windows theory: This theory states that visible signs of crime, anti-social behavior, and civil disorder create an atmosphere that encourages further crime and disorder This can lead to a decline in community morale and a sense of lawlessness, which can make it more difficult to control crime\n\nSocial disorganization theory: This theory states that crime is more likely to occur in communities that are characterized by social disorganization This can include factors such as poverty, unemployment, and family disruption These factors can make it difficult for communities to control crime and provide opportunities for young people\n\nRoutine activity theory: This theory states that crime is more likely to occur when there is a convergence of three factors: motivated offenders, suitable targets, and the absence of capable guardians This means that crime is more likely to occur when there are people who are willing to commit crimes, targets that are attractive to criminals, and no one around to prevent the crime from happening\n\nCrime prevention through environmental design (CPTED): This theory states that crime can be prevented by designing the physical environment in a way that makes it more difficult for criminals to commit crimes This can include things like installing security lights, improving visibility, and making it easier for people to see each other\n\nTarget hardening: This theory states that crime can be prevented by making it more difficult for criminals to target a particular person or property This can include things like installing security alarms, using strong locks, and making it more difficult for criminals to break in",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Broken Windows,Visible signs of disorder lead to increased crime",
    "option_b": "Strain Theory,Crime results from blocked opportunities for success",
    "option_c": "Social Disorganization Theory,Crime is more likely in socially unstable neighborhoods",
    "option_d": "Routine activity theory , motivated offenders & suitable targets and the absence of capable guardians",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030167",
    "question": "Well-maintained spaces encourage ____ behavior",
    "answer": "ethical",
    "explanation": "Well-designed and maintained built environments have been shown to encourage more ethical and prosocial behavior in people Therefore, the blank is accurately filled",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "eth,ic,al",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030168",
    "question": "Consider the following Statement and Conclusion:\nStatement: Delhi metro riders demonstrate environment's influence on conduct \nConclusion: Improved environments impact behavior",
    "answer": "Statement is true, Conclusion is true",
    "explanation": "The statement that the orderly conduct of Delhi metro riders demonstrates the environment's influence on behavior is true And the conclusion that improved environments shape positive conduct is also valid Therefore, option D which states both parts are true is the most accurate choice",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Statement is false, Conclusion is false",
    "option_b": "Statement is true, Conclusion is false",
    "option_c": "Statement is false, Conclusion is true",
    "option_d": "Statement is true, Conclusion is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030169",
    "question": "What are pro-social behaviour and morality associated with?",
    "answer": "Innate to human nature",
    "explanation": "Pro-social behavior and innate morality are considered by experts to be inherent to human nature rather than learned behaviors or social constructs alone Therefore, the blank is accurately filled",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Learned behaviors",
    "option_b": "Social constructs",
    "option_c": "Against human nature",
    "option_d": "Innate to human nature",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030170",
    "question": "As per the experts, which of the following phenomenon binds society?",
    "answer": "Honesty and trust, Integrity",
    "explanation": "According to research, factors like honesty, integrity and interpersonal trust play a vital role in binding society by enabling cooperation Therefore, both parts of the assertion are correct",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Regulations, Shared interests",
    "option_b": "Social hierarchy, Laws",
    "option_c": "Vision, Goals",
    "option_d": "Honesty and trust, Integrity",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030171",
    "question": "What does weak contract system harms?",
    "answer": "Market development",
    "explanation": "Weak contract systems and poor rule of law undermine market development by discouraging investment and transactions between private parties Therefore, the blank is accurately filled",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Investment",
    "option_b": "Economic stability",
    "option_c": "Productivity",
    "option_d": "Market development",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030172",
    "question": "match the following:",
    "answer": "Literacy - Better policies, Recognizing values impact - Catalyze positive change, Political participation - Participate in governance, Happiness - GNH",
    "explanation": "The correct match shows option I, literacy helping citizens demand better developmental policies from government And option II, recognizing values' impact catalyzing positive social change by changing beliefs Therefore, this option matches most accurately",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Literacy,Better policies",
    "option_b": "Recognizing values' impact,Catalyze positive change",
    "option_c": "Political participation,Participate in governance",
    "option_d": "Happiness,GNH",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030173",
    "question": "How can people catalyze positive social change?",
    "answer": "By recognizing values' impact on development",
    "explanation": "Recognizing human values' immense impact on a country's development trajectory can catalyze positive social change by changing societal beliefs and norms Therefore, this is the most accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Through political participation",
    "option_b": "Via entrepreneurship",
    "option_c": "By developing new technologies",
    "option_d": "By recognizing values' impact on development",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030174",
    "question": "How can literacy help improve policies?",
    "answer": "By enabling people to demand better ones",
    "explanation": "Literacy can empower people to critically evaluate government policies and demand more equitable, effective ones for development Therefore, this is the most comprehensive answer choice",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "By increasing fiscal discipline",
    "option_b": "By promoting financial inclusion",
    "option_c": "By accelerating economic growth",
    "option_d": "By enabling people to demand better ones",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030175",
    "question": "The UNDP-designed HDR was utilized by the World Bank to allocate ________ funds to member countries",
    "answer": "grant",
    "explanation": "The World Bank is an international financial institution that provides loans and grants to developing countries The World Bank uses a variety of criteria to determine which countries are eligible for funding, including the country's HDI\n\nThe HDI is a composite index that measures a country's level of human development It is calculated using three indicators: life expectancy, education, and income Countries with a higher HDI are considered to be more developed\n\nThe World Bank uses the HDI to identify countries that are in need of development assistance The Bank believes that countries with a low HDI are more likely to experience poverty, hunger, and disease\n\nThe World Bank provides grants to countries to help them improve their human development These grants can be used to fund projects in education, health, infrastructure, and other areas",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": "",
    "option_a": "gra,nt,et,ri",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "030176",
    "question": "The concept of Gross National Happiness (GNH) includes ________ factors along with material ones",
    "answer": "nine",
    "explanation": "Gross National Happiness is a measure of the well-being of a country's citizens It was developed in Bhutan in the 1970s as an alternative to Gross Domestic Product (GDP), which is a measure of a country's economic output\n\nGNH is based on the belief that happiness is more important than material wealth It includes nine domains of well-being:\nPhysical health\nMental health\nTime use\nEducation\nEmployment\nCommunity vitality\nCultural diversity and resilience\nLiving standards\nGood governance\nEcological diversity and resilience",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics  >> Growth, Development & Happiness  >> Intro to Value of Economics",
    "difficulty_level": "",
    "option_a": "ni,ne,ei,ght",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040101",
    "question": "What was the Indian Economy characterized by at the time of It's independence?",
    "answer": "Structural distortions in agriculture and industry",
    "explanation": "At the time of independence in 1947, India's economy was characterized by major structural distortions in both agriculture and industry sectors In agriculture, land tenure systems were exploitative and resulted in intermediaries such as zamindars and money lenders extracting much of the surplus Industry was dominated by foreign interests and mainly served colonial objectives rather than nurture domestic entrepreneurship or meet local needs The economy lacked diversity and self-reliance Therefore, the answer is Structural distortions in agriculture and industry",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Robust growth",
    "option_b": "Low inequality",
    "option_c": "Advanced infrastructure",
    "option_d": "Structural distortions in agriculture and industry",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040102",
    "question": "What was a major impact of British colonial rule on India's economy?",
    "answer": "Unilateral transfer of wealth to Britain",
    "explanation": "The economic impact of prolonged British colonial rule was largely exploitative in nature Policies were designed to serve imperial interests rather than promote development in India There was significant unilateral transfer of wealth from India to Britain in the form of revenues, raw materials, profits etc Indigenous industry received little state support and modern growth was limited Colonial rule also led to the unbalancing of the traditional economy Therefore, the major impact was Unilateral transfer of wealth to Britain",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "High GDP growth",
    "option_b": "Industrialization",
    "option_c": "Agricultural modernization",
    "option_d": "Unilateral transfer of wealth to Britain",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040103",
    "question": "During colonial rule, Britain practiced economic policies in India that______",
    "answer": "Impeded development",
    "explanation": "Under colonial rule, British economic policies were designed to maximize imperial interests rather than promote indigenous development in India Colonial policies focused on extracting India's wealth rather than investing in its economy Key sectors like manufacturing and infrastructure received limited state support and faced discriminatory policies Overall, colonial policies inhibited and distorted economic development in India Therefore, colonial rule Impeded development",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Im,pem,de,d d,ev,el,op,me,nt",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040104",
    "question": "Why did India have low literacy and life expectancy at independence?",
    "answer": "Neglect of social sector under British rule",
    "explanation": "At independence in 1947, India had dismal social indicators like literacy and life expectancy This was a direct result of prolonged neglect of investment in human development under British colonial rule The colonial government spent very little on education, healthcare, sanitation and other aspects that impact human development The social sector was a low priority in colonial economic policy Therefore, the reason for low literacy and life expectancy was Neglect of social sector under British rule",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "High poverty",
    "option_b": "Lack of schools and hospitals",
    "option_c": "Social inequalities",
    "option_d": "Neglect of social sector under British rule",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040105",
    "question": "Independent India opted for industry rather than agriculture as its prime moving force despite:",
    "answer": "Lacking prerequisites like infrastructure",
    "explanation": "After independence, India formally opted for industrialization led by a strong public sector as the prime moving force of economic growth, despite lacking most of the prerequisites Unlike China, India did not have sufficient agricultural surplus or infrastructure to invest in industrialization But policymakers saw industry as the pathway to modernization India lacked infrastructure prerequisites yet chose industry over agriculture Therefore, the answer is Lacking prerequisites like infrastructure",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Sufficient foreign reserves",
    "option_b": "Adequate technology",
    "option_c": "Favorable policies",
    "option_d": "Lacking prerequisites like infrastructure",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040106",
    "question": "Which factor favored India adopting agriculture as the prime moving force?",
    "answer": "Presence of fertile cultivable land",
    "explanation": "India at independence was endowed with extensive fertile land and had a large agricultural population with farming experience, making agriculture a viable prime moving force With supportive policies, agriculture could generate surpluses for reinvestment in industry and infrastructure In contrast, India lacked prerequisites like capital, skills and technology for rapid industrialization immediately Therefore, the presence of fertile cultivable land Favored agriculture as the prime moving force",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Strong industrial base",
    "option_b": "Advanced infrastructure",
    "option_c": "Skilled manpower",
    "option_d": "Presence of fertile cultivable land",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040107",
    "question": "After independence, agriculture was seen as a sign of________",
    "answer": "Backwardness",
    "explanation": "In the nationalist narrative after independence, agriculture was seen as backward and industry was viewed as the driver of modern progress Policymakers wanted rapid industrialization to catch up with advanced economies Agriculture was not prioritized due to the perception that it represented backwardness Therefore, agriculture was seen as a sign of Backwardness after independence",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Ba,ck,wa,rd,ne,ss",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040108",
    "question": "What helped China industrialize after adopting agriculture as the prime moving force?",
    "answer": "Agricultural surplus invested in prerequisites",
    "explanation": "China first focused on agricultural reforms in the initial decades after communism This generated surpluses which were then invested into developing industrial infrastructure and skills So agricultural surplus enabled the prerequisites for subsequent industrialization In contrast, India lacked agricultural surplus to invest in industry Therefore, Agricultural surplus invested in prerequisites helped China industrialize",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Central planning",
    "option_b": "Foreign direct investment",
    "option_c": "Export promotion",
    "option_d": "Agricultural surplus invested in prerequisites",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040109",
    "question": "When did India formally adopt agriculture as the prime moving force?",
    "answer": "In 2002 during the 10th Five Year Plan",
    "explanation": "It was only in 2002 during the 10th Five Year Plan that India formally adopted agriculture as the prime moving force of economic growth, over five decades after independence Previous plans focused on industrialization, before the importance of agricultural development was recognized So India adopted agriculture as the prime moving force In 2002 during the 10th Five Year Plan",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "In 1947 after independence",
    "option_b": "In 1991 after reforms",
    "option_c": "In 2002 during the 10th Five Year Plan",
    "option_d": "In 2014 under new government",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040110",
    "question": "Adopting agriculture as the prime moving force was aimed to help India:",
    "answer": "Achieve food security",
    "explanation": "Adopting agriculture as the prime moving force of economic growth was aimed at improving food security and rural prosperity in India With reforms and investment, agriculture could boost production and farmer incomes This would help eliminate hunger and malnutrition In contrast, the focus was not yet on objectives like manufacturing, exports or IT Therefore, the adoption of agriculture aimed to help India Achieve food security",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Become an IT hub",
    "option_b": "Develop manufacturing",
    "option_c": "Achieve food security",
    "option_d": "Promote foreign trade",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040111",
    "question": "Why did independent India adopt economic planning?\nStatement 1: To reduce poverty and regional disparities\nStatement 2: To boost jobs\nStatement 3: To tackle inflation",
    "answer": "Only 1",
    "explanation": "Statement 1 is correct: A major reason for India adopting economic planning after independence was to reduce poverty and balance regional economic disparities\n\nStatement 2 is incorrect: Creating employment was a secondary goal, but not the main driver for planning\n\nStatement 3 is incorrect: Tackling inflation was an operational concern, but not the motivation for planning\n\nTherefore, the correct statement is Only 1",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Only 1",
    "option_b": "Only 1 and 2",
    "option_c": "Only 2",
    "option_d": "Only 1 and 3",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040112",
    "question": "Which contemporaneous world experience influenced India's planning decision?",
    "answer": "Great Depression and World War 2 reconstruction",
    "explanation": "India's decision to pursue centralized economic planning after independence was influenced by the experience of the Great Depression in the 1930s and World War 2 reconstruction efforts The economic challenges and government coordination seen in these episodes motivated planning The contemporary world events that impacted thinking were the Great Depression and World War 2 reconstruction",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Cold War politics",
    "option_b": "Fall of the Berlin Wall",
    "option_c": "Great Depression and World War 2 reconstruction",
    "option_d": "2008 financial crisis",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040113",
    "question": "When defining India's mixed economy, what would be the role of the private sector according to the First Five Year Plan?",
    "answer": "Continue production and distribution",
    "explanation": "The First Five Year Plan clearly defined India's mixed economy model, with roles for both the public and private sectors For the private sector, the Plan stated that existing production and distribution of goods and services would continue The public sector would enter areas essential for development Therefore, the Plan said the private sector would Continue production and distribution",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Provide all infrastructure",
    "option_b": "Drive all economic activity",
    "option_c": "Control key industries",
    "option_d": "Continue production and distribution",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040114",
    "question": "match the periods with India's economic ideology:",
    "answer": "1947-1990s - Government control, 1990s-present - Market forces, Pre-independence - Colonial economy",
    "explanation": "matching the periods with India's economic ideology:\ni) 1947-1990s - Government control over economy\nii) 1990s-present - Increasing role for market forces and private sector\niii) Pre-independence - Colonial economic structure dominated by imperial interests\nTherefore, the correct match is:\ni - Government control, ii - Market forces, iii - Colonial economy",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "1947-1990s,Government control",
    "option_b": "1990s-present,Market forces",
    "option_c": "Pre-independence,Colonial economy",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040115",
    "question": "Why was the Planning Commission replaced with NITI Aayog?",
    "answer": "To overhaul the planning process",
    "explanation": "The Planning Commission, created in 1950, was replaced in 2015 with the NITI Aayog to overhaul the planning process in India After liberalization, the Planning Commission was seen as a relic of the controlled economy NITI Aayog was created to better leverage cooperative federalism and recognize role of states and private sector The reason was To overhaul the planning process",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "To cut government spending",
    "option_b": "To boost financial inclusion",
    "option_c": "To create jobs",
    "option_d": "To overhaul the planning process",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040116",
    "question": "NITI Aayog aims to promote which of the following things?",
    "answer": "Cooperative federalism",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog aims to promote cooperative federalism by enhancing cooperation between the centre and states for economic development This contrasts with the Planning Commission's top-down approach It works to foster inclusive development by incorporating state-level priorities Therefore, NITI Aayog aims to promote Cooperative federalism",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Central planning",
    "option_b": "Privatization",
    "option_c": "Foreign investment",
    "option_d": "Cooperative federalism",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040117",
    "question": "What was The NITI Aayog was established to meet?",
    "answer": "Changing economic needs",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog was established to meet India's changing economic needs and realities, compared to the era when Planning Commission was set up It provides flexibility and new approaches for a more market-based, globalized economy Therefore, the reason is Changing economic needs",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Globalization demands",
    "option_b": "Socialist ideology",
    "option_c": "Geopolitical goals",
    "option_d": "Changing economic needs",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040118",
    "question": "Why couldn't India's private sector develop infrastructure after independence?",
    "answer": "Lack of investment capacity",
    "explanation": "After independence, the private sector in India did not have the capacity to undertake huge investments in infrastructure like power, transport and irrigation Private capital was limited due to lack of institutional financing options Therefore, the reason it could not develop infrastructure was Lack of investment capacity",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Colonial era policies",
    "option_b": "Government opposition",
    "option_c": "Priority on agriculture",
    "option_d": "Lack of investment capacity",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040119",
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): The emergence of development economics as a field was driven by the need to address the challenges of growth without comprehensive development\nReason (R): Development economics focuses solely on economic growth and overlooks qualitative progress",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true, and R is the correct explanation of A",
    "explanation": "Assertion is true: The emergence of development economics as a distinct field was driven by the need to broaden the objectives of economic growth Many post-colonial nations focused narrowly on GDP growth without achieving comprehensive development\n\nReason is true: Development economics does focus on both economic growth objectives and qualitative progress across social, institutional etc parameters\n\nReason correctly explains Assertion: The Reason elaborates that development economics considers both quantitative and qualitative progress, which drove its emergence initially\n\nTherefore, both A and R are true, and R is the correct explanation of A",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true, and R is the correct explanation of A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true, but R is not the correct explanation of A",
    "option_c": "A is true, but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false, but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040120",
    "question": "How would profits from public sector companies help develop India's social sector?",
    "answer": "By funding public goods like healthcare",
    "explanation": "Public sector companies in India generated significant profits, especially from infrastructure monopolies Instead of enriching private shareholders, these profits were intended to be used for public goods Profits from public sector companies could help fund healthcare, education and other social sector development Therefore, profits would help by Funding public goods like healthcare",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "By reducing budget deficits",
    "option_b": "By eliminating poverty",
    "option_c": "By building infrastructure",
    "option_d": "By funding public goods like healthcare",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040121",
    "question": "What did the Public Infrastructure facilitated in the context of Indian Economy?",
    "answer": "Rise of the private sector",
    "explanation": "The extensive investments made by public sector companies enabled the development of infrastructure like power, transport, telecom etc in post-independence India This facilitated the emergence of the private sector across agriculture, manufacturing and services Therefore, Public infrastructure facilitated Rise of the private sector",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Spread of heavy industries",
    "option_b": "Agricultural modernization",
    "option_c": "Development of villages",
    "option_d": "Rise of the private sector",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040122",
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): Public Sector Undertakings (PSUs) played a pivotal role in generating revenue for social sector development in India\nReason (R): The profits from PSUs were directed solely towards private sector expansion and industrial growth",
    "answer": "A is true, but R is false",
    "explanation": "Assertion is true: Public sector undertakings did play a major role in generating revenues for social sector development in India through their profits\n\nReason is false: PSU profits were not directed solely towards private sector growth; they also benefited the social sector\n\nTherefore, A is true but R is false The assertion is true, but the reason is incorrect",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true, and R is the correct explanation of A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true, but R is not the correct explanation of A",
    "option_c": "A is true, but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false, but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040123",
    "question": "What impacted India's policy on public sector disinvestment after 2003-04?",
    "answer": "Consensus on state's role",
    "explanation": "After the economic reforms of 1991, consensus gradually emerged on reducing the state's direct role in economic activity Private sector was seen as efficient This changing consensus since 2003-04 impacted India's policy on disinvestment of PSUs Therefore, the factor was Changing consensus on state's role",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Fiscal constraints",
    "option_b": "Globalization",
    "option_c": "Consensus on state's role",
    "option_d": "Recession",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040124",
    "question": "What does the Strategic disinvestment allows?",
    "answer": "Transfer of PSU ownership to private sector",
    "explanation": "Strategic disinvestment involves the sale of substantial portion of government's stake in a PSU, resulting in transfer of management control to private players This aims to improve efficiency through private ownership Therefore, it allows Transfer of PSU ownership to private sector",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Increasing PSU efficiency",
    "option_b": "Limiting foreign ownership",
    "option_c": "Enhancing worker control",
    "option_d": "Transfer of PSU ownership to private sector",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "040125",
    "question": "Which of the following does Contemporary disinvestment aims to raise?",
    "answer": "Revenue through stake sale",
    "explanation": "In recent years, the strategic disinvestment of PSUs has aimed to raise revenues for the government through stake sales Disinvestment proceeds contribute to the budget and reduce fiscal deficit Therefore, contemporary disinvestment aims to raise Revenue through stake sale",
    "topic_name": "Structure of the Indian Economy & Demographics >> Evolution of the Indian Economy  >> The Background to Emphasis of Public Sector",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Public accountability",
    "option_b": "Competition",
    "option_c": "Operational freedom",
    "option_d": "Revenue through stake sale",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110101,
    "question": "Which of the following statements accurately denotes the purpose of discussing real-life examples from different economies and historical backgrounds in the context of economic planning?\n\nI - To emphasize the academic aspects of economic planning\nII - To understand the meaning and role of planning in a specific country like India\nII - To exclude any reference to experiments conducted by different countries in the field of economic planning",
    "answer": "Only 2",
    "explanation": "Statement 1: This statement is not entirely accurate The purpose is not solely to emphasize academic aspects but to gain practical insights and understand the real-world application of economic planning\n\nStatement 2: This statement is accurate Discussing real-life examples and historical backgrounds helps us comprehend the practical meaning and role of economic planning, especially within specific countries like India\n\nStatement 3: This statement is not accurate The purpose is to include references to experiments conducted by different countries, which aids in understanding various approaches to economic planning\n\nHence, the most accurate statement regarding the purpose is Statement 2",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Only 1",
    "option_b": "Only 2",
    "option_c": "Only 1 and 2",
    "option_d": "Only 2 and 3",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110102,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion(A): As per experts, HD Dickinson provided the best definition of economic planning \nReason(R): His definition highlighted the role of the state in major economic decisions",
    "answer": "A and R are both true and R explains A",
    "explanation": "The Assertion states that experts consider HD Dickinson's definition of economic planning to be the best, which is true \nThe Reason provides the context for why his definition is considered the best by highlighting its focus on the state's role in major economic decisions The Reason correctly explains the Assertion",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "A and R are both true but R does not explain A",
    "option_b": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_c": "A is false but R is true",
    "option_d": "A and R are both true and R explains A",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110103,
    "question": "Which of the following statements accurately describes Dickinson's definition of economic planning? \nStatement 1 It emphasized the state's role in production, allocation and economic coordination \nStatement 2 It focused on trade and taxation policies \nStatement 3 It highlighted the role of private enterprises \nStatement 4 It prioritized welfare schemes and subsidies",
    "answer": "1 only",
    "explanation": "Statement 1 accurately describes Dickinson's definition of economic planning He defines economic planning as \"the making of major economic decisions - what and how much is to be produced, how, when and where it is to be produced, and to whom it is to be allocated by the conscious decision a determinate authority, on the basis of a comprehensive survey of the economic system as a whole\" This definition clearly emphasizes the role of the state in production, allocation and economic coordination\n\nStatement 2, 3, and 4 are not accurate descriptions of Dickinson's definition of economic planning Statement 2 focuses on trade and taxation policies, which are not explicitly mentioned in Dickinson's definition Statement 3 highlights the role of private enterprises, while Dickinson's definition does not explicitly mention the role of private enterprises Statement 4 prioritizes welfare schemes and subsidies, which are also not explicitly mentioned in Dickinson's definition",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "1 and 3 only",
    "option_b": "2 and 4 only",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 4 only",
    "option_d": "1 only",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110104,
    "question": "Which of the following statements reflect India's National Planning Committee definition of economic planning? \nStatement 1 It emphasized industrialization and urbanization primarily \nStatement 2 It focused on production and investment mainly \nStatement 3 It incorporated economic, cultural and spiritual values  \nStatement 4 It highlighted defence and administration priorities largely",
    "answer": "3 only",
    "explanation": "Statement 3 reflects India's National Planning Committee definition of economic planning The National Planning Committee was set up in 1938 by Jawaharlal Nehru, who was the chairman of the committee The committee's definition of economic planning emphasized the need to incorporate economic, cultural and spiritual values in the planning process The committee believed that economic planning should not only focus on material progress, but also on the development of the human spirit\n\nStatements 1, 2, and 4 do not reflect the National Planning Committee definition of economic planning Statement 1 emphasizes industrialization and urbanization, while the National Planning Committee's definition did not explicitly mention these terms Statement 2 focuses on production and investment, while the National Planning Committee's definition also emphasized the need for social and cultural development Statement 4 highlights defence and administration priorities, while the National Planning Committee's definition did not explicitly mention these terms",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "2 and 3 only",
    "option_b": "3 and 4 only",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 4 only",
    "option_d": "3 only",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110105,
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true regarding economic planning in India before independence? \nStatment 1 There was consensus that independent India would adopt planning \nStatement 2 Planning was opposed by business leaders \nStatement 3 The public sector would drive planning \nStatement 4 There were divisions on adopting planning",
    "answer": "4 only",
    "explanation": "Statement 4 is the most accurate statement regarding economic planning in India before independence There were divisions on adopting planning in India before independence\n\nSome of the leading thinkers and economists of the time, such as M Visvesvaraya, Jawaharlal Nehru, and PC Mahalanobis, were strong advocates of planning They believed that planning was essential for India to achieve rapid economic development and to reduce poverty\n\nHowever, there were also some business leaders and economists who opposed planning They argued that planning would stifle economic growth and innovation They also argued that it would be too difficult to implement and manage a planning system in a country as large and diverse as India\n\nIn the end, the Indian National Congress, the leading political party in India at the time, adopted a mixed approach to economic planning They agreed that planning was necessary, but they also believed that the private sector should play a role in economic development\n\nThe first Five-Year Plan was launched in 1951, and it marked the beginning of a long and complex journey of economic planning in India The planning process has evolved over time, and it has faced many challenges However, it has also made significant contributions to India's economic development",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "2 only",
    "option_b": "2 and 3 only",
    "option_c": "4 only",
    "option_d": "1 only",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110106,
    "question": "Economic planning aims to influence major economic variables like income, consumption, investment over time Evaluate the statement",
    "answer": "Absolutely Correct",
    "explanation": "Economic planning deliberately seeks to influence and coordinate key economic variables like income, consumption, investment etc \nover the long term, unlike just targeting exports or government spending Therefore, the statement is accurate",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Absolutely Correct",
    "option_b": "Partially Incorrect",
    "option_c": "Correct, but it only focuses on short-term economic variables",
    "option_d": "Incorrect, as it has no impact on economic variables",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110107,
    "question": "Planning is the process of achieving well-defined goals by optimum utilization of available resources Evaluate the statement",
    "answer": "Absolutely Correct",
    "explanation": "Planning as the process of achieving clearly defined goals by optimally utilizing available resources, \nunlike just maximizing production or growth Therefore, the statement is accurate",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Absolutely Correct",
    "option_b": "Partially Incorrect",
    "option_c": "Correct, but it only involves financial resources",
    "option_d": "Incorrect, as it primarily focuses on short-term objectives",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110108,
    "question": "Fill in the blanks: Regional planning was first used for development in the early 1900s by the _______ through the establishment of the _______",
    "answer": "United States, Tennessee Valley Authority",
    "explanation": "Regional planning for development was first pioneered in the early 1900s by the United States through the Tennessee Valley Authority initiative \nThe TVA project covered parts of seven states and aimed at integrated area development Therefore, the blanks are accurately filled",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "United States, Tennessee Valley Authority",
    "option_b": "Russians, Moscow Planning Group",
    "option_c": "French, Paris Regional Committee",
    "option_d": "Germans, Berlin Development Board",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110109,
    "question": "match the following terms with their corresponding features:",
    "answer": "Gosplan - Soviet national planning, Monnet Plan - Indicative planning in France, Tennessee Valley Authority - Regional planning initiative in the USA, FYP - Soviet",
    "explanation": "Gosplan refers to the Soviet Union's national economic planning model \nThe Monnet Plan in France exemplified indicative planning \nAnd the Tennessee Valley Authority was a regional development planning initiative in the USA Therefore, option C matches the terms with their accurate descriptions",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Gosplan,Soviet national planning",
    "option_b": "Monnet Plan,Indicative planning in France",
    "option_c": "Tennessee Valley Authority,Regional planning initiative in the USA",
    "option_d": "FYP,Soviet",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110110,
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true about the origin of economic planning? \nStatement 1 The Soviet Union implemented the first national economic plan \nStatement 2 The US implemented the first national economic plan \nStatement 3 France implemented the first national economic plan \nStatement 4 India implemented the first national economic plan",
    "answer": "1 only",
    "explanation": "Economic planning, as a systematic approach to directing and coordinating an economy's resources, gained prominence during the 20th century The Soviet Union, under its centralized economic system, was indeed one of the earliest and most notable examples of implementing a national economic plan The Soviet Union's Five-Year Plans, initiated by Joseph Stalin in the 1920s, aimed to rapidly industrialize the country and set specific targets for production and development\n\nWhile other countries like the US, France, and India also implemented economic planning strategies, the Soviet Union is credited with pioneering the concept on a national scale Therefore, Statement 1 is the true statement about the origin of economic planning",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "2 only",
    "option_b": "2 and 3 only",
    "option_c": "3 and 4 only",
    "option_d": "1 only",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110111,
    "question": "When did the Soviet Union implement its first five year economic plan?",
    "answer": 1928,
    "explanation": "The Soviet Union announced and implemented its first five year national economic plan in 1928 under Joseph Stalin \nTherefore, 1928 is the accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": 1917,
    "option_b": 1945,
    "option_c": 1950,
    "option_d": 1928,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110112,
    "question": "The Soviet model of planning directly influenced which of the following countries after World War 2?\nStatement 1 East European nations \nStatement 2 Asian countries \nStatement 3 West European nations \nStatement 4 Latin American countries",
    "answer": "1 only",
    "explanation": "After World War 2, the Soviet Union's economic and political influence extended to several East European nations that came under its sphere of influence These nations, such as the countries in Eastern Europe like Poland, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, and others, adopted economic planning models similar to the Soviet Union's centralized planning system This influence was particularly prominent due to the political and military control exerted by the Soviet Union in this region during the Cold War era",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "2 only",
    "option_b": "2 and 3 only",
    "option_c": "1 and 4 only",
    "option_d": "1 only",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110113,
    "question": "Which country pioneered the adoption of indicative economic planning?",
    "answer": "France",
    "explanation": "France was the first country to adopt indicative economic planning at the national level after becoming a mixed economy, unlike the Soviet imperative planning model \nTherefore, France is the accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "United States",
    "option_b": "Soviet Union",
    "option_c": "India",
    "option_d": "France",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110114,
    "question": "Imperative planning featuring centralized control was followed in which kind of  economies?",
    "answer": "Socialist and communist economies",
    "explanation": "Imperative planning characterized by high state control and directives was practiced only in socialist and communist economies , unlike in capitalist or mixed economies \nTherefore, socialist and communist economies is the accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Capitalist economies",
    "option_b": "Mixed economies",
    "option_c": "Developing economies",
    "option_d": "Socialist and communist economies",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110115,
    "question": "Which country exemplified the purest form of imperative economic planning?",
    "answer": "China",
    "explanation": "Communist China represented the purest version of imperative planning where all resources were owned and controlled by the state \nTherefore, China is the accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Soviet Union",
    "option_b": "Hungary",
    "option_c": "Poland",
    "option_d": "China",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110116,
    "question": "Who pioneered the concept of market socialism in imperative planned economies?",
    "answer": "Oskar Lange",
    "explanation": "States that Polish economist Oskar Lange coined and pioneered the idea of market socialism in imperative planning economies, \nunlike others mentioned Therefore, Oskar Lange is the correct answer",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Joseph Stalin",
    "option_b": "Mao Zedong",
    "option_c": "Milton Friedman",
    "option_d": "Oskar Lange",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110117,
    "question": "What does indicative planning work through?",
    "answer": "Market and price system",
    "explanation": "Indicative planning leverages the market forces and price system unlike imposing centralized control \nTherefore, market and price system is the accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Central authority directives",
    "option_b": "Production quotas",
    "option_c": "State corporations",
    "option_d": "Market and price system",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110118,
    "question": "match the following planning types with their corresponding features:",
    "answer": "Imperative planning - Centralized control & state ownership, Indicative planning - Uses market system and private sector role, Functional planning - specific sector, Decentralized planning -less government role",
    "explanation": "Centralized planning: (Imperative planning)  This is a system where the government controls all aspects of the economy, from production to distribution The government sets production goals, allocates resources, and determines prices Centralized planning is often associated with command economies, such as the Soviet Union\nDecentralized planning: This is a system where the government plays a less direct role in the economy The government sets broad goals, but the private sector is responsible for most economic activity Decentralized planning is often associated with market economies, such as the United States\nThere are also other types of economic planning, such as:\n\nIndicative planning: This is a system where the government provides guidance and incentives for the private sector, but does not directly control economic activity Indicative planning is often used in mixed economies, such as India\nFunctional planning: This is a system where the government focuses on specific sectors of the economy, such as agriculture or manufacturing Functional planning is often used in conjunction with other types of planning\nSpatial planning: This is a system where the government focuses on the spatial distribution of economic activity Spatial planning is often used to reduce regional disparities and promote economic development",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Imperative planning,Centralized control & state ownership",
    "option_b": "Indicative planning,Uses market system and private sector role",
    "option_c": "Functional planning,specific sector",
    "option_d": "Decentralized planning,less government role",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110119,
    "question": "After WWII, most newly independent countries like India initially adopted was?",
    "answer": "Indicative planning with imperative inclinations",
    "explanation": "While most new independent countries post-WWII adopted indicative planning models, \nmany like India had a strong bias towards imperative centralized planning initially Therefore, the statement is accurate",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Imperative planning models",
    "option_b": "Regional development planning",
    "option_c": "Laissez-faire policies",
    "option_d": "Indicative planning with imperative inclinations",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110120,
    "question": "Currently, most countries can only practice which kind of economic planning?",
    "answer": "Indicative economic planning",
    "explanation": "Presently, only indicative planning leveraging market forces is feasible in most economies unlike imperative or informal planning \nTherefore, indicative economic planning is the accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Imperative planning",
    "option_b": "Informal planning",
    "option_c": "No planning",
    "option_d": "Indicative economic planning",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110121,
    "question": "India's shift from imperative to indicative planning occurred with which of the following events?",
    "answer": "Economic reforms of 1991",
    "explanation": "India's transition from imperative to more indicative planning happened with the economic liberalization reforms of 1991 and reducing state control \nTherefore, economic reforms of 1991 is the accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Green REvolution",
    "option_b": "Liberalization in 1980s",
    "option_c": "Declaration of Emergency",
    "option_d": "Economic reforms of 1991",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110122,
    "question": "Consider the following statement and conclusion:\nStatement: Indicative planning was adopted by mixed economies \nConclusion: It leveraged markets, unlike imperative planning",
    "answer": "Statement is true, Conclusion is true",
    "explanation": "The statement that indicative planning was practiced by mixed economies is accurate \nThe conclusion that it made use of markets unlike imperative planning is also true  Therefore, option D is the correct choice",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Statement is false, Conclusion is false",
    "option_b": "Statement is true, Conclusion is false",
    "option_c": "Statement is false, Conclusion is true",
    "option_d": "Statement is true, Conclusion is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110123,
    "question": "Normative planning incorporates which of the following?",
    "answer": "Socio-cultural factors unlike just economic ones",
    "explanation": "Normative planning focuses on socio-cultural factors unlike the narrow economic focus of systems planning \nTherefore, the statement highlighting the distinction is accurate",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Mainly economic and financial factors",
    "option_b": "Primarily administrative targets",
    "option_c": "Largely environmental sustainability",
    "option_d": "Socio-cultural factors unlike just economic ones",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110124,
    "question": "Which type of planning focuses on socio-cultural factors?",
    "answer": "Normative planning",
    "explanation": "Normative planning pays attention to incorporating socio-cultural factors as opposed to purely economic factors \nTherefore, normative planning is the accurate answer",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Imperative planning",
    "option_b": "Indicative planning",
    "option_c": "Informal planning",
    "option_d": "Normative planning",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 110125,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion(A): Normative planning suits countries with less social diversity \nReason(R): It emphasizes socio-cultural factors",
    "answer": "A is true but R is false",
    "explanation": "The assertion that normative planning is less suitable for countries with high social diversity is true  \nHowever, the reason incorrectly states it emphasizes socio-cultural factors when in fact normative planning does focus on diverse social factors unlike other types Therefore, the assertion is true but the reason is false",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Economic Planning  >> Introduction to Types of Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "A and R are true, R explains A",
    "option_b": "A and R are true, R does not explain A",
    "option_c": "A is false, R is true",
    "option_d": "A is true but R is false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120101,
    "question": "Consider the following statements: \nWhy was the Soviet model of economic planning influential among Indian leaders in the 1930s?\n1 The Soviet Union achieved high industrial and economic growth rates through planned development\n2 Indian leaders wanted to emulate the Soviet political and social model\n3 The success of Soviet planning contrasted with crisis and inefficiencies of capitalist economies post the Great Depression\nSelect the statements that explain why the Soviet model influenced Indian leaders:",
    "answer": "1 and 3",
    "explanation": "The unprecedented success of Soviet national planning in rapidly industrializing and growing their economy fascinated Indian nationalist leaders, who were keen to adopt central planning to develop the agrarian Indian economy \nThe depression-hit capitalist economies provided a contrast which further attracted Indian leaders to the Soviet model Statement 2 is incorrect as Indian leaders admired the economic planning, not the political model",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 3",
    "option_b": "only 1",
    "option_c": "1 and 2",
    "option_d": "None of the Above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120102,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): M Visvesvaraya outlined a model for planned economy in his book published in 1934 \nReason (R): India was facing a crisis of poverty and underdevelopment, requiring centralized planning for rapid industrialization and growth",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "The assertion (A) and the reason (R) are both correct\n\nM Visvesvaraya, a prominent Indian engineer and statesman, outlined a model for planned economy in his book \"Planned Economy for India\" published in 1934 He argued that India needed to adopt a planned economy in order to address the crisis of poverty and underdevelopment that the country was facing He proposed a ten-year plan with the aim of doubling the income of the country\n\nThe reason (R) is also correct India was facing a severe crisis of poverty and underdevelopment in the early 20th century The country was largely agricultural, with a low per capita income and high levels of illiteracy and disease There was a growing awareness among the Indian intelligentsia that the country needed to adopt a more modern and industrialized approach to development",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120103,
    "question": "Consider the following statements: \nWhy was the Visvesvaraya Plan outlined by M Visvesvaraya in 1934 considered the first blueprint for economic planning in India?\n1 It was based on the model of democratic capitalism followed in the United States\n2 It aimed to alleviate poverty and reduce economic inequalities\n3 It outlined the need for central planning by the government\n4 It focused on rapid industrialization and doubling national income\nWhich of the following are correct statements?",
    "answer": "3 and 4",
    "explanation": "he following statements are correct:\n\n3 It outlined the need for central planning by the government\n4 It focused on rapid industrialization and doubling national income\nThe Visvesvaraya Plan was a blueprint for economic planning in India that was outlined by M Visvesvaraya in 1934 The plan called for the government to play a central role in planning and coordinating the economy It also focused on rapid industrialization and doubling the national income\n\nThe plan was not based on the model of democratic capitalism followed in the United States Instead, it was based on the principles of state intervention and planning The plan also did not explicitly mention the goal of alleviating poverty and reducing economic inequalities",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 2",
    "option_b": "3 and 4",
    "option_c": "1 and 4",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120104,
    "question": "Consider the following statements: \nHow did M Visvesvaraya's background and experience shape his vision for India's economic future outlined in the Visvesvaraya Plan?\n1 His Western education made him favor capitalist development \n2 As an engineer, he valued large industries and technology \n3 His work in princely states convinced him of the need for centralized planning  \n4 Being from Mysore state, he proposed using local models for national development\nWhich of the following are correct statements?",
    "answer": "2 and 3",
    "explanation": "The following statements are correct:\n\n2 As an engineer, he valued large industries and technology\n3 His work in princely states convinced him of the need for centralized planning\n\nStatements 1 and 4 are not correct Visvesvaraya's Western education did not make him favor capitalist development In fact, he was a strong believer in the role of the state in economic development He also did not propose using local models for national development He believed that India needed to adopt a more modern and industrialized approach to development",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "2 and 3",
    "option_b": "2,3 and 4",
    "option_c": "1,2 and 4",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120105,
    "question": "Identify the following key features associated with the FICCI proposal of 1934:\n\nA Highlighted need for comprehensive national planning\nB Favored state ownership of all industries\nC Advocated laissez-faire policies \nD Proposed a National Planning Commission",
    "answer": "A - D",
    "explanation": "The following key features are associated with the FICCI proposal of 1934:\n\nHighlighted the need for comprehensive national planning\nProposed a National Planning Commission\nDid not favor state ownership of all industries\nAdvocated a mixed economy with a role for both the public and private sectors\nThe FICCI proposal was a landmark document that laid the foundation for economic planning in India It was the first time that a major business organization had called for the government to play a central role in planning and coordinating the economy",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "A - C",
    "option_b": "B - D",
    "option_c": "C - A",
    "option_d": "A - D",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120106,
    "question": "Which of the following statements are absolutely correct?\nHow did the views put forth by Indian capitalists in the Bombay Plan align with or differ from the views of the nationalist leaders in the NPC? \n1 Both recommended state ownership of key industries \n2 Bombay Plan favored decentralized planning unlike NPC \n3 NPC focused more on alleviating poverty than Bombay Plan\n 4 Both emphasized the need for rapid, large scale industrialization",
    "answer": 4,
    "explanation": "Statements 1 and 3 are not correct The Bombay Plan did not favor state ownership of key industries, and the NPC did not focus more on alleviating poverty than the Bombay Plan\n\nStatement 2 is not absolutely correct, but it is generally true The Bombay Plan did not explicitly mention decentralization, but it did call for a more limited role for the state in the economy The NPC, on the other hand, explicitly called for a more centralized approach to planning\n\nIn conclusion, the Bombay Plan and the NPC both emphasized the need for rapid, large scale industrialization They differed, however, on the role of the state in industrialization and on the extent of state ownership",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": 1,
    "option_b": 2,
    "option_c": 3,
    "option_d": 4,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120107,
    "question": "Why was the formation of the National Planning Committee (NPC) significant, despite the initial opposition from some quarters within the INC?",
    "answer": "It brought together diverse stakeholders for coordinated planning",
    "explanation": "The NPC's significance lies in its ability to bring together a wide range of stakeholders, including capitalists, Gandhians, technocrats, socialists, and more, to collaborate on development planning, indicating a push for coordinated efforts",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "It advocated for state ownership",
    "option_b": "It brought together diverse stakeholders for coordinated planning",
    "option_c": "It emphasized laissez-faire economics",
    "option_d": "It focused on rapid industrialization",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120108,
    "question": "Compare and contrast the roles of the National Planning Committee (NPC) and the Consultative Committee of Economists How did these committees contribute to India's planning process?",
    "answer": "NPC proposed concrete programmes, while Economists' Committee focused on academic advice",
    "explanation": "The NPC's role was to work out concrete programmes for development, while the Economists' Committee provided academic advice Both contributed to planning, but with different focuses and approaches",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both proposed concrete programmes",
    "option_b": "Both focused on academic advice",
    "option_c": "NPC was focused on academics, while Economists' Committee was practical",
    "option_d": "NPC proposed concrete programmes, while Economists' Committee focused on academic advice",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120109,
    "question": "How did the ideas of the Advisory Planning Board influence the development planning in Independent India?",
    "answer": "It pushed for a central, authoritative organization for development planning",
    "explanation": "The Advisory Planning Board strongly recommended the creation of a central, authoritative organization responsible for development planning This idea led to the establishment of the Planning Commission in 1950, which played a significant role in shaping India's development planning process",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "It advocated for decentralized planning",
    "option_b": "It emphasized laissez-faire economics",
    "option_c": "It pushed for a central, authoritative organization for development planning",
    "option_d": "It supported complete state control over industries",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120110,
    "question": "How did the Bombay Plan and the National Planning Committee (NPC) address the issue of agrarian restructuring?",
    "answer": "Both emphasized the need for abolition of intermediaries and fair agricultural prices",
    "explanation": "Both the Bombay Plan and the NPC agreed on the abolition of intermediaries (such as zamindars), guaranteeing fair prices for agricultural products, and promoting cooperatives This shared approach aimed to uplift the agricultural sector and improve the conditions of farmers",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both emphasized the need for abolition of intermediaries and fair agricultural prices",
    "option_b": "Both opposed agrarian reforms",
    "option_c": "Bombay Plan focused on heavy industries, while NPC focused on consumer goods",
    "option_d": "Bombay Plan recommended complete state ownership of agricultural land",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120111,
    "question": "Despite the intial differences, How did the Bombay Plan and the National Planning Committee (NPC) find common ground?",
    "answer": "Both emphasized the need for social welfare measures",
    "explanation": "Despite their differences, the Bombay Plan and the NPC agreed on several key aspects, including the importance of social welfare measures This common ground demonstrated their shared interest in addressing issues related to poverty, employment, and basic necessities",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both emphasized the need for social welfare measures",
    "option_b": "Both opposed state intervention",
    "option_c": "Bombay Plan focused on heavy industries, while NPC focused on consumer goods",
    "option_d": "Bombay Plan prioritized laissez-faire, while NPC emphasized state ownership",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120112,
    "question": "In what ways did the Bombay Plan and the National Planning Committee (NPC) differ in their approach to industrialization?",
    "answer": "Bombay Plan allocated a significant portion to basic industries, while NPC focused on essential consumer goods",
    "explanation": "The Bombay Plan allocated a considerable part of its plan outlay to basic industries, while the NPC, influenced by Soviet planning, emphasized simultaneous development of consumer goods industries, but on a low-key scale This difference highlights their distinct strategies for industrialization",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both focused on heavy industries",
    "option_b": "Both advocated for rapid industrialization",
    "option_c": "Bombay Plan allocated a significant portion to basic industries, while NPC focused on essential consumer goods",
    "option_d": "NPC emphasized heavy industries, while Bombay Plan focused on consumer goods",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120113,
    "question": "How did the Gandhian Plan's perspective on industrialization differ from the views of the National Planning Committee (NPC) and the Bombay Plan?",
    "answer": "Gandhian Plan advocated cottage and village-level industries, while NPC and Bombay Plan supported heavy and large industries",
    "explanation": "The Gandhian Plan prioritized decentralized cottage and village-level industries to preserve the self-sufficiency of local communities In contrast, the NPC and the Bombay Plan emphasized the role of heavy and large industries in economic development This divergence reflected Gandhi's emphasis on preserving local traditions and self-sufficiency",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Gandhian Plan supported heavy and large industries like NPC and Bombay Plan",
    "option_b": "Gandhian Plan advocated cottage and village-level industries, while NPC and Bombay Plan supported heavy and large industries",
    "option_c": "Gandhian Plan emphasized mechanization of agriculture",
    "option_d": "Gandhian Plan recommended state control over all industries",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120114,
    "question": "Explain the ideological impasse that occurred during the first session of the National Planning Committee (NPC) and how it influenced the articulation of the Gandhian Plan",
    "answer": "The Gandhian member questioned the NPC's authority on industrialization, leading to an ideological deadlock",
    "explanation": "During the first session of the NPC, JC Kumarappa, the lone Gandhian member, challenged the committee's authority to discuss industrialization He emphasized Gandhi's view of restricting and eliminating modern industrialism This impasse reflected the ideological conflict between the Gandhian perspective and the committee's inclination towards promoting large-scale industry alongside cottage industries The impasse highlighted the need for a Gandhian-inspired plan to present an alternative vision",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "NPC favored complete state control over industries",
    "option_b": "The NPC endorsed the views of the Gandhian member",
    "option_c": "The Gandhian member questioned the NPC's authority on industrialization, leading to an ideological deadlock",
    "option_d": "The NPC unanimously agreed on the role of heavy industries",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120115,
    "question": "Analyze the core differences in the economic visions of Gandhi and the National Planning Committee (NPC) regarding the role of state power and industrialization",
    "answer": "Gandhi emphasized local self-sufficiency and opposed centralized state power and industrialism, while NPC leaned towards central planning and industrialization",
    "explanation": "Gandhi viewed centralized state power and industrialization as curses imposed by European colonialism and favored local self-sufficiency through cottage industries In contrast, the NPC leaned towards central planning, larger industries, and state intervention to drive economic growth This divergence in economic philosophy shaped their respective approaches to development planning in India",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both Gandhi and the NPC advocated centralized state power",
    "option_b": "Gandhi supported industrialism like the NPC",
    "option_c": "Both Gandhi and the NPC emphasized large industries",
    "option_d": "Gandhi emphasized local self-sufficiency and opposed centralized state power and industrialism, while NPC leaned towards central planning and industrialization",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120116,
    "question": "How did the Gandhian Plan's emphasis on a \"decentralized economic structure\" align with Gandhi's broader philosophical views?",
    "answer": "Gandhi believed in local self-sufficiency and minimal state intervention",
    "explanation": "The Gandhian Plan's focus on a \"decentralized economic structure\" resonated with Gandhi's advocacy for self-reliant villages and his skepticism towards centralized authority Gandhi's philosophy emphasized self-sufficiency, community-based industries, and minimal state intervention, which were reflected in the plan's core principles",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Gandhi believed in local self-sufficiency and minimal state intervention",
    "option_b": "Gandhi supported heavy industries",
    "option_c": "Gandhi advocated complete industrialization",
    "option_d": "Gandhi emphasized urbanization and centralization",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120117,
    "question": "Assess the impact of the Gandhian Plan on the trajectory of India's economic planning and development post-independence",
    "answer": "The Gandhian Plan influenced the focus on rural development, cottage industries, and community participation",
    "explanation": "The Gandhian Plan's emphasis on rural development, cottage industries, and community participation had a lasting impact on India's economic planning It contributed to policies prioritizing rural growth, decentralization, and sustainable development These ideas were reflected in subsequent Five Year Plans and initiatives aimed at uplifting rural communities",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "The Gandhian Plan led to rapid industrialization",
    "option_b": "The Gandhian Plan influenced the focus on rural development, cottage industries, and community participation",
    "option_c": "The Gandhian Plan advocated state control over all industries",
    "option_d": "The Gandhian Plan called for urbanization and centralization",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120118,
    "question": "Consider the following statements\nWhy did Mahatma Gandhi oppose the industrialization focus of the Bombay Plan and National Planning Committee? \n1 Industrialization would displace crafts and village industries \n2 Modern machinery and technology was harmful for society \n3 Urbanization and centralized planning violated principle of village Swaraj \n4 Cottage industries promoted self-reliance better than heavy industries\nWhich of the following are correct?",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "Gandhi advocated village self-sufficiency, decentralization, and small enterprises against the large-scale industrialization proposed in the Bombay Plan and NPC, which he felt would harm villages and cottage industries His vision aligned with the Gandhian Plan's emphasis on preserving local craftsmanship and promoting self-reliance, in contrast to the industrialization-driven models of the other plans",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1, 2 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120119,
    "question": "MN Roy's People's Plan was based on which ideology? \n1) Marxist Socialism 2) Gandhian Village Swaraj 3) Democratic Capitalism 4) Laissez-faire",
    "answer": 1,
    "explanation": "The People's Plan prescribed Marxist socialism to provide basic necessities, influencing socialist tilt in subsequent five year plans This influence led to the integration of socialist principles in India's economic planning, including policies focused on redistribution of wealth, social welfare, and public ownership of key sectors The People's Plan laid the foundation for India's mixed economy approach, combining elements of socialism and capitalism",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": 1,
    "option_b": 2,
    "option_c": 3,
    "option_d": 4,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120120,
    "question": "___________ emphasized village industries, self-reliance and decentralization based on Gandhian principles A) Bombay Plan B) People's Plan C) Visvesvaraya Plan D) Sarvodaya Plan",
    "answer": "Sarvodaya Plan",
    "explanation": "Jayaprakash Narayan's Sarvodaya Plan focused on Gandhian constructive works, village industries, and decentralization The plan aligned with Gandhi's philosophy of uplifting marginalized communities through self-sufficiency and decentralized decision-making Jayaprakash Narayan's emphasis on grassroot-level development and community participation contributed to the concept of \"Sarvodaya\" or \"upliftment of all,\" shaping India's approach to inclusive growth",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Sa,rv,od,ay,a Pl,an",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120121,
    "question": "The Sarvodaya Plan’s vision of village self-reliance was most similar to whose economic model?",
    "answer": "Visvesvaraya Plan",
    "explanation": "Like Gandhi's model, Jayaprakash Narayan's Sarvodaya Plan focused on village industries and self-reliance, contrasting with the industrialization emphasis of other plans The Sarvodaya Plan envisioned local economies thriving through village-level industries, promoting autonomy and reducing dependence on centralized systems This decentralized approach aimed to empower communities and foster sustainable development, aligning with Gandhi's vision of self-reliant villages",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Bombay Plan",
    "option_b": "People's Plan",
    "option_c": "Gandhian Plan",
    "option_d": "Visvesvaraya Plan",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120122,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): Jayaprakash Narayan opposed the centralized nature of five year plans\n\nReason (R): He felt it diluted people's participation in the planning process",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "Jayaprakash Narayan critiqued the centralization in five year plans as diluting people's participation, instead advocating decentralized village planning His concerns highlighted the need for bottom-up planning, where local communities actively participate in decision-making processes Jayaprakash Narayan's emphasis on decentralization influenced subsequent efforts to enhance local governance, such as the Panchayati Raj system, which aimed to bring governance closer to the people",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120123,
    "question": "Which government reports on specific areas of the economy were prepared in the 1940s as India moved towards planned development?\n1 The Krishnamachari Report on agricultural prices \n2 The Saraiya Report on cooperatives \n3 The Kheragat Report on education \n4 The Gadgil Report on rural credit",
    "answer": "1 and 4",
    "explanation": "Key reports prepared in the 1940s before independence included the Krishnamachari Report on agricultural prices and the Gadgil Report on rural credit, among others",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 3",
    "option_b": "2 and 4",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 4",
    "option_d": "1 and 4",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120124,
    "question": "The Krishnamachari Report focused on which specific economic issue?",
    "answer": "Agricultural prices",
    "explanation": "The Krishnamachari Report provided recommendations on agricultural prices The report's insights into fair pricing mechanisms and support for farmers' income became important considerations in India's agricultural policies It paved the way for strategies to ensure the well-being of farmers and stabilize agricultural markets",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Irrigation",
    "option_b": "Agricultural prices",
    "option_c": "Land reforms",
    "option_d": "Public distribution system",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120125,
    "question": "What was the significance of the various area-specific reports prepared in the 1940s? \n1 They highlighted key issues needing government intervention \n2 They laid the groundwork for future planned development \n3 They were prepared through extensive data collection and research \n4 They provided comprehensive recommendations for economic reform",
    "answer": "2 and 3",
    "explanation": "The detailed area-wise reports prepared by experts in the 1940s using extensive research highlighted development issues and laid the groundwork for future planning These reports delved into the nuances of regional development disparities, resource allocation, and sector-specific challenges They served as a knowledge base for policy-makers, enabling them to tailor developmental strategies to address the unique needs of different regions in India",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "3 and 4",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120126,
    "question": "Who prepared the various area-specific economic reports in the 1940s before independence?",
    "answer": "Expert committees and government bodies",
    "explanation": "The detailed area-wise reports on issues like agriculture, rural credit etc were prepared by expert committees and government bodies in the 1940s pre-independence These reports provided a comprehensive understanding of the challenges facing various sectors of the economy They informed policy-makers about the specific requirements of each sector and played a pivotal role in shaping development priorities during the post-independence era",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Politicians",
    "option_b": "Expert committees and government bodies",
    "option_c": "Industrialists",
    "option_d": "Bureaucrats",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120127,
    "question": "match the following key objectives outlined in the Constitution with their focus areas:",
    "answer": "Preamble - Social and economic and political justice,  Fundamental Rights - Right to equality, Directive Principles of State Policy - Providing humane conditions of work, Fundamental Duties - Duty to protect the environment",
    "explanation": "Objectives like justice are in the Preamble, right to equality in Fundamental Rights, humane work conditions in Directive Principles and protecting the environment in Fundamental Duties These constitutional provisions underscore India's commitment to social, economic, and environmental justice They guide the formulation of policies and plans, ensuring that development is inclusive, equitable, and sustainable",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Preamble,Social and economic and political justice",
    "option_b": "Fundamental Rights,Right to equality",
    "option_c": "Directive Principles of State Policy,Providing humane conditions of work",
    "option_d": "Fundamental Duties,Duty to protect the environment",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120128,
    "question": "Which Constitutional provisions encapsulated the goals for India's socioeconomic progress? \n1 The Preamble 2 The Fundamental Rights 3 The Directive Principles of State Policy 4 The Seventh Schedule (Union, State and Concurrent lists)",
    "answer": "1, 3 and 4",
    "explanation": "The Preamble, Directive Principles, and Seventh Schedule distributing powers laid down the objectives guiding India's developmental planning The Preamble sets forth the aspirations of justice, equality, and fraternity, providing a moral compass for development The Directive Principles of State Policy outline principles to be used as guidelines for legislation and governance The Seventh Schedule divides powers between the central and state governments, reflecting the cooperative federalism that shapes India's planning landscape",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 2",
    "option_b": "2 and 4",
    "option_c": "1, 3 and 4",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120129,
    "question": "When was the Planning Commission established?",
    "answer": 1950,
    "explanation": "The Planning Commission was established in March 1950 It played a crucial role in formulating and implementing India's Five Year Plans The commission acted as a central authority for coordinating and prioritizing developmental activities across various sectors and states",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": 1947,
    "option_b": 1948,
    "option_c": 1949,
    "option_d": 1950,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120130,
    "question": "Who was the first Chairman of the Planning Commission?",
    "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "explanation": "Jawaharlal Nehru was the first Chairman of the Planning Commission His leadership and vision were instrumental in shaping the early years of India's planning efforts Nehru's commitment to modernization, industrialization, and equitable growth guided the commission's initiatives during its formative years",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Lal Bahadur Shastri",
    "option_b": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "option_c": "Morarji Desai",
    "option_d": "Indira Gandhi",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120131,
    "question": "What was the nature of the Planning Commission? \n1 A constitutional body \n2 An advisory body to the government \n3 A statutory body created by law \n4 Directly accountable to Parliament",
    "answer": "2 and 4",
    "explanation": "The Planning Commission was an extra-constitutional advisory body not directly accountable to Parliament Its unique status allowed it to function independently and provide expert advice to the government While it lacked direct parliamentary accountability, its recommendations significantly influenced policy-making and development strategies",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 3",
    "option_b": "2 and 4",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "3 and 4",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120132,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): The Planning Commission was described as an economic cabinet for the country \nReason (R): It influenced national policy across sectors",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "Jawaharlal Nehru termed the Planning Commission as an economic cabinet given its wide-ranging role in national economic policymaking across sectors Nehru recognized the commission's pivotal role in steering India's economic development He referred to it as an \"economic cabinet\" to emphasize its importance in shaping policies that impacted various aspects of the country's growth",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120133,
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n1 Appraise progress of Five Year Plans \n2 Formulate Five Year Plans \n3 Determine plan priorities and resource allocation \n4 Identify deficiencies in resources\nWhat were the main functions of the Planning Commission?",
    "answer": "2 and 3",
    "explanation": "Key functions included formulating plans, determining priorities, and resource allocation The Planning Commission's primary role was to draft comprehensive Five Year Plans that outlined developmental goals and strategies It assessed sectoral needs, allocated resources, and determined the order of priority for various projects and initiatives",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 3 and 4",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120134,
    "question": "Did the Planning Commission's role included recommending adjustments based on appraisals of Five Year Plans",
    "answer": "TRUE",
    "explanation": "Appraising plan progress and recommending policy adjustments was a function of the Planning Commission The commission continuously monitored the progress of ongoing projects and evaluated the effectiveness of policies Based on the appraisals, it recommended adjustments and modifications to ensure that the plans remained aligned with changing economic conditions and goals",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "TRUE",
    "option_b": "FALSE",
    "option_c": "Partially True",
    "option_d": "Uncertain",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120135,
    "question": "In which year did the government approve the establishment of NITI Aayog to replace the Planning Commission?",
    "answer": 2015,
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog was established on January 1, 2015, to replace the Planning Commission The NITI Aayog, or National Institution for Transforming India, marked a shift from centralized planning to a more participatory and collaborative approach It focused on fostering cooperative federalism and incorporating states' perspectives in policy-making",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": 2013,
    "option_b": 2014,
    "option_c": 2015,
    "option_d": 2016,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120136,
    "question": "Who headed the Independent Evaluation Office that recommended scrapping the Planning Commission in 2014?",
    "answer": "Montek Singh Ahluwalia",
    "explanation": "The Independent Evaluation Office headed by Montek Singh Ahluwalia recommended scrapping the Planning Commission in 2014 The office assessed the commission's performance and effectiveness, leading to the proposal for its replacement The recommendation reflected the evolving needs of India's economy and the desire for a more dynamic and adaptable planning structure",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "C Rangarajan",
    "option_b": "Suresh Tendulkar",
    "option_c": "Montek Singh Ahluwalia",
    "option_d": "Arvind Panagariya",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120137,
    "question": "When was the National Development Council first established?",
    "answer": 1952,
    "explanation": "The National Development Council was set up on August 6, 1952 The NDC emerged as a platform for cooperative federalism in India's planning process It brought together central and state governments to deliberate on developmental priorities, fostering collaboration and ensuring that plans were tailored to regional needs",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": 1947,
    "option_b": 1950,
    "option_c": 1952,
    "option_d": 1955,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120138,
    "question": "Who first chaired the National Development Council?",
    "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "explanation": "Jawaharlal Nehru was the first Chairman of the National Development Council His leadership in the NDC reinforced his commitment to ensuring harmonious cooperation between the central government and the states in achieving India's developmental objectives",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Lal Bahadur Shastri",
    "option_b": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "option_c": "Indira Gandhi",
    "option_d": "Morarji Desai",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120139,
    "question": "Consider the following Statements:\nWhat impact did the National Development Council have initially? \n1 Provided a forum for Centre-state coordination \n2 Enabled democratic decentralisation of planning \n3 Diluted powers of state governments \n4 States had to align plans with central priorities\nWhich of the following are correct?",
    "answer": "1 and 2",
    "explanation": "The NDC facilitated Centre-state coordination and democratic decentralization by giving states a role in planning It served as a forum for discussions on policy formulation, allowing states to voice their concerns, share experiences, and actively contribute to shaping India's development agenda",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "3 and 4",
    "option_b": "1 and 2",
    "option_c": "1 and 3",
    "option_d": "1, 2 and 4",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120140,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): The NDC became less effective after Nehru's death \nReason (R): Centre-state conflicts increased with centralized planning by the Centre",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "After Nehru's death, NDC meetings declined as centralized planning increased Centre-state tussles The decline in NDC meetings highlighted the challenges of maintaining cooperative federalism in the absence of Nehru's charismatic leadership The growing conflicts between the central government and states underscored the complexities of balancing centralized planning with regional autonomy",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120141,
    "question": "Integrated state plans aligned with national priorities indicated a shift towards _________ planning in India",
    "answer": "centralized",
    "explanation": "State plans integrating with central priorities demonstrated increased centralized planning While the NDC aimed to foster cooperative federalism, the integration of state plans with central priorities also reflected the influence of centralized planning mechanisms This convergence allowed for a unified approach to achieving national development goals while accounting for regional variations",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Ce,nt,ra,li,zed",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120142,
    "question": "The goal of 'Garibi Hatao' (Remove Poverty) was adopted in the ________________ Five Year Plan",
    "answer": "Fifth",
    "explanation": "The goal of 'Garibi Hatao' (Remove Poverty) was adopted in the Fifth Five Year Plan (1974-79) The objective of poverty alleviation underscored India's commitment to addressing socioeconomic disparities The plan aimed to uplift marginalized sections of society through targeted policies and initiatives that aimed to improve living standards and opportunities",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Fif,th",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120143,
    "question": "The Janata Party introduced the concept of _________ during their short tenure",
    "answer": "Rolling Plans",
    "explanation": "Rolling Plan was the term used for the Janata Party's Fifth Five Year Plan during their short rule The term \"Rolling Plan\" reflected the flexible approach adopted during the plan's implementation It aimed to ensure adaptability to changing economic conditions and policy priorities, allowing for adjustments as needed",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Ro,ll,in,g Pl,ans",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120144,
    "question": "When was the goal of 'Garibi Hatao' adopted by the Government of India?",
    "answer": "Fifth Five Year Plan",
    "explanation": "Garibi Hatao' was adopted as a goal during the Fifth Five Year Plan period The adoption of 'Garibi Hatao' as a central goal reinforced the plan's focus on poverty eradication The plan introduced a range of measures aimed at empowering disadvantaged groups and reducing income inequality, marking a significant step towards inclusive development",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "First Five Year Plan",
    "option_b": "Second Five Year Plan",
    "option_c": "Fifth Five Year Plan",
    "option_d": "Sixth Five Year Plan",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120145,
    "question": "Which statement correctly describes an impact of the 1973 oil crisis? \n1 It led to surplus revenues for oil exporting nations \n2 Global oil prices underwent a sharp decline \n3 Economic growth slowed across many nations \n4 India benefited from increased oil exports",
    "answer": 3,
    "explanation": "The 1973 oil crisis led to stagflation and economic downturn in many countries due to higher oil prices The oil crisis of 1973 had global repercussions, contributing to a combination of stagnant economic growth and high inflation known as \"stagflation\" The sharp rise in oil prices disrupted economies worldwide, leading to challenges in managing both inflation and unemployment",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": 1,
    "option_b": 2,
    "option_c": 3,
    "option_d": 4,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120146,
    "question": "When was the Twenty Point Programme first launched by the Government of India?",
    "answer": 1975,
    "explanation": "The Twenty Point Programme was launched in July 1975 The Twenty Point Programme aimed to address a range of developmental challenges, including poverty, employment, education, and social welfare The comprehensive program sought to enhance the quality of life for India's citizens through targeted initiatives and policy measures",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": 1972,
    "option_b": 1975,
    "option_c": 1980,
    "option_d": 1985,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120147,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): The Twenty Point Programme was conceived to improve the quality of life, especially for the poor \n\nReason (R): It monitored anti-poverty and rural development schemes",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "The Twenty Point Programme focused on monitoring schemes for poverty alleviation and rural development to improve the quality of life The program's emphasis on monitoring and evaluation reflected a commitment to results-driven development By tracking the progress of poverty alleviation and rural development schemes, the program aimed to ensure effective implementation and measurable impact",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120148,
    "question": "When was the Member of Parliament Local Area Development Scheme (MPLADS) first introduced?",
    "answer": 1993,
    "explanation": "The MPLAD scheme was launched in December 1993 The Members of Parliament Local Area Development Scheme (MPLAD) aimed to empower MPs to address local infrastructure needs The scheme allocated funds to MPs for recommending development projects in their constituencies, enabling them to contribute to the improvement of local communities",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": 1990,
    "option_b": 1993,
    "option_c": 1995,
    "option_d": 1998,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120149,
    "question": "MPLADS aims to recommend works based on locally felt development needs",
    "answer": "MPLADS",
    "explanation": "MPLADS allows MPs to recommend works fulfilling locally felt infrastructure needs MPLADS grants MPs the authority to identify and suggest projects that directly respond to the infrastructure requirements of their respective constituencies This decentralized approach ensures that local needs are addressed and that development efforts are closely aligned with community priorities",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "MP,LA,DS,SD",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120150,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): Panchayats have demanded scrapping of MPLADS \n\nReason (R): They want MPLADS funds to be allocated directly to local bodies",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "Panchayats have opposed MPLADS, demanding that MPLADS funds be directly provided to local bodies for works Some Panchayati Raj institutions have advocated for a more direct allocation of MPLADS funds to local governing bodies, arguing that this approach would enhance transparency, accountability, and effective utilization of resources for local development projects",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Introduction to Central Planning",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130101,
    "question": "Which of the following were the objectives of multi-level planning in India?\n1 To promote decentralization \n2 To facilitate people's participation \n3 To strengthen local bodies constitutionally\n4 To integrate national and local priorities",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 4",
    "explanation": "MLP aimed to promote decentralization, people's participation, and integrate national and local priorities in planning Strengthening local bodies came later via constitutional amendments",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 3",
    "option_b": "2 and 4",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 4",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130102,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): Multi-level planning failed to facilitate decentralized planning in India initially\n \nReason (R): Local bodies lacked constitutional status and financial powers",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "MLP did not succeed initially as local bodies lacked constitutional mandate and fiscal autonomy to effectively participate in planning",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130103,
    "question": "Which of the following constitute the Centre-level plans in India's multi-level planning framework? \n1 Five Year Plans\n2 Twenty Point Program\n3 MPLADS\n4 State Annual Plans",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "Centre-level plans include Five Year Plans, Twenty Point Program and MPLADS",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130104,
    "question": "State-level planning is undertaken through which institutional mechanism?",
    "answer": "State Planning Boards",
    "explanation": "States undertake planning through State Planning Boards headed by the Chief Ministers",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Planning Commission",
    "option_b": "State Planning Boards",
    "option_c": "Zilla Parishads",
    "option_d": "Village Panchayats",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130105,
    "question": "At which administrative level is district planning implemented in India?",
    "answer": "Through Panchayats in rural areas and Municipalities/Corporations in urban areas",
    "explanation": "District plans are implemented through Panchayats in rural areas and Municipalities/Corporations in urban areas",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "State governments",
    "option_b": "Through Panchayats in rural areas and Municipalities/Corporations in urban areas",
    "option_c": "Blocks",
    "option_d": "Town Area Committees",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130106,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): District Planning Committees were formed after 73rd Amendment \n\nReason (R): To prepare draft district development plans by consolidating local plans",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "DPCs were mandated by the 73rd Amendment to consolidate panchayat plans into district plans",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130107,
    "question": "__________ serve as the nodal agencies for block-level planning in India",
    "answer": "District Planning Boards",
    "explanation": "Block planning is undertaken under the aegis of District Planning Boards",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Di,st,ric,t Pl,an,nin,g Bo,ar,ds",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130108,
    "question": "Match the following variants of local-level planning in India with their focus areas:\n\nList I With List II",
    "answer": "Village level planning matches-Rural populations, Hill area planning matches-Populations in hilly and difficult terrains, Tribal area planning matches-Tribal populations",
    "explanation": "Village-level planning focuses on rural populace, hill area planning on hilly terrains and tribal area planning targets tribal groups",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Tribal area planning matches,Tribal populations",
    "option_b": "Village level planning matches,Rural populations",
    "option_c": "Hill area planning matches,Populations in hilly and difficult terrains",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "match"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130109,
    "question": "_________ planning focuses on populations living in difficult terrains",
    "answer": "Hill area",
    "explanation": "Hill area planning specifically targets development in hilly and difficult terrains",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Hil,l a,rea",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130110,
    "question": "Which committee recommended decentralization and empowerment of Panchayati Raj institutions?",
    "answer": "Balwantrai Mehta Committee",
    "explanation": "The Balwantrai Mehta Committee in 1957 recommended decentralization and empowerment of PRIs to promote grassroots planning",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Ashok Mehta Committee",
    "option_b": "Balwantrai Mehta Committee",
    "option_c": "L M Singhvi Committee",
    "option_d": "G V K Rao Committee",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130111,
    "question": "When was the 73rd Constitutional Amendment providing constitutional status to Panchayats passed?",
    "answer": 1992,
    "explanation": "The 73rd Constitutional Amendment was passed in 1992 to provide constitutional status and mandate to Panchayats",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": 1985,
    "option_b": 1990,
    "option_c": 1992,
    "option_d": 1995,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130112,
    "question": "How does financial autonomy help strengthen local body planning? \n1 Allows local taxation \n2 Reduces dependence on state grants \n3 Enables execution of local plans\n4 Promotes accountability\nWhich of the following are correct statements?",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "Fiscal autonomy through local taxation and reduced dependence on state grants empowers local bodies for decentralized planning",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130113,
    "question": "How did the 73rd and 74th Constitutional Amendments help decentralization? \n1 Provided constitutional mandate to local bodies \n2 Mandated regular elections to local bodies \n3 Empowered Gram Sabhas \n4 Established State Finance Commissions\nWhich of the following are correct statements?",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "The amendments constitutionally empowered local bodies, mandated elections and strengthened Gram Sabhas",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130114,
    "question": "Which Finance Commission recommendations strengthened states fiscally for better decentralized planning? \n1 9th Finance Commission \n2 11th Finance Commission \n3 13th Finance Commission \n4 14th Finance Commission\nWhich of the following are correct statements?",
    "answer": "3 and 4",
    "explanation": "13th and 14th Finance Commissions increased states' share in central taxes and market borrowings for better fiscal federalism",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 2",
    "option_b": "3 and 4",
    "option_c": "2 and 4",
    "option_d": "1 and 3",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130115,
    "question": "Fiscal autonomy to local bodies is critical for effective decentralization Which of the following are correct about this statement?",
    "answer": "TRUE",
    "explanation": "Local bodies require fiscal autonomy and independent finances for effective decentralized planning",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "TRUE",
    "option_b": "FALSE",
    "option_c": "Partially True",
    "option_d": "Partially False",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130116,
    "question": "What led to enhanced roles for Finance Commission vis-a-vis Planning Commission from 1990s? \n1 Economic reforms required greater state participation \n2 Coalition politics at the Centre \n3 Constitutional mandates of local planning \n4 Recommendations of 10th Finance Commission\nWhich of the following are correct statements?",
    "answer": "All of the above",
    "explanation": "Factors like reforms, coalition politics, constitutional mandates and 10th FC recommendations supported state fiscal empowerment over Planning Commission",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 2",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 4",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130117,
    "question": "When was the Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management (FRBM) Act passed?",
    "answer": 2003,
    "explanation": "The Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management (FRBM) Act was passed in the year 2003 to establish fiscal discipline and prudent management of public finances The act aimed to ensure inter-generational equity in fiscal management and long-term macroeconomic stability",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": 2000,
    "option_b": 2003,
    "option_c": 2005,
    "option_d": 2010,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130118,
    "question": "Which Finance Commission increased states' share of central taxes?",
    "answer": "13th Finance Commission",
    "explanation": "The 13th and 14th Finance Commissions played a pivotal role in enhancing the fiscal autonomy of states by increasing their share of central taxes This measure aimed to empower states and improve their ability to cater to local development needs",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "10th Finance Commission",
    "option_b": "11th Finance Commission",
    "option_c": "13th Finance Commission",
    "option_d": "14th Finance Commission",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130119,
    "question": "The Planning Commission and Finance Commission were set up under which Constitutional provisions?",
    "answer": "Article 262 and 280",
    "explanation": "The establishment of the Planning Commission and Finance Commission was facilitated by the provisions of Articles 262 and 280 of the Indian Constitution These commissions played distinct roles in formulating development plans and allocating financial resources to states, respectively",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Article 245 and 250",
    "option_b": "Article 262 and 280",
    "option_c": "Article 302 and 303",
    "option_d": "None of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130120,
    "question": "Which Plan recognized the need to align planning with economic reforms?",
    "answer": "Eighth Five Year Plan",
    "explanation": "The Eighth Five Year Plan (1992-97) recognized the importance of aligning planning with economic reforms This plan aimed to integrate economic liberalization measures into the planning process to achieve higher growth, efficiency, and competitiveness",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Sixth Five Year Plan",
    "option_b": "Eighth Five Year Plan",
    "option_c": "Ninth Five Year Plan",
    "option_d": "Tenth Five Year Plan",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130121,
    "question": "The Tenth Five Year Plan (2002-07) introduced which new aspects?\n1 Focus on monitorable targets \n2 State-level targets \n3 Result-orientation \n4 Reformed financial strategy",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Five Year Plan introduced several new aspects to enhance planning effectiveness These included a focus on monitorable targets, state-level targets, and a result-oriented approach These changes aimed to ensure more accountable and efficient planning with tangible outcomes",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130122,
    "question": "Which Plan aimed to double per capita income in a decade?",
    "answer": "Tenth Five Year Plan",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Plan (2002-07) set an ambitious target of doubling per capita income within a decade This objective was aligned with the plan's overarching goal of achieving higher economic growth and improving living standards",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Eighth Five Year Plan",
    "option_b": "Ninth Five Year Plan",
    "option_c": "Tenth Five Year Plan",
    "option_d": "Eleventh Five Year Plan",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130123,
    "question": "When did the Tenth Five Year Plan emphasize agriculture as the prime moving force of the Indian economy?",
    "answer": "2002-07",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Five Year Plan (2002-07) marked a significant shift by recognizing agriculture as the prime driving force of the Indian economy This emphasis aimed to harness the potential of the agricultural sector to spur economic growth, alleviate poverty, and enhance food security",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "1997-2002",
    "option_b": "2002-07",
    "option_c": "2007-12",
    "option_d": "2012-17",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130124,
    "question": "The Tenth Plan aimed to increase ___________ to raise rural incomes and demand",
    "answer": "agricultural production",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Plan centered its strategy on boosting agricultural production This approach was envisioned to uplift rural incomes, enhance rural purchasing power, and stimulate domestic demand",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "ag,ri,cu,lt,u,ra,l pr,od,uc,ti,on",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130125,
    "question": "How does prioritizing agriculture help broader economic growth according to the Tenth Plan?\n1 Generates employment \n2 Increases food security\n3 Raises rural incomes and purchasing power\n4 Promotes manufacturing for global exports",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Plan recognized that prioritizing agriculture could generate multifaceted benefits for the economy By fostering employment, increasing food security, and raising rural incomes, agriculture-driven growth could contribute to overall economic expansion This approach also aimed to facilitate manufacturing for global exports, boosting foreign exchange earnings",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130126,
    "question": "When did the Tenth Plan first include governance reforms in the planning process?",
    "answer": "2002-07",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Five Year Plan (2002-07) marked a pivotal moment by integrating governance reforms into the planning process This shift recognized the significance of good governance in driving development outcomes and ensuring efficient utilization of resources",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "1997-2002",
    "option_b": "2002-07",
    "option_c": "2007-12",
    "option_d": "2012-17",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130127,
    "question": "How does good governance support socio-economic development according to the Tenth Plan?\n1 Enhances public service delivery \n2 Improves accountability and transparency \n3 Reduces corruption \n4 Promotes efficient utilization of resources",
    "answer": "All of the above",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Plan identified good governance as a cornerstone of socio-economic development By enhancing public service delivery, improving accountability and transparency, reducing corruption, and promoting efficient resource utilization, good governance creates an enabling environment for sustainable and inclusive growth",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 2",
    "option_b": "2 and 4",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130128,
    "question": "Post 1991 reforms, further economic reforms were to be led by which of the following organs?",
    "answer": "states",
    "explanation": "In the aftermath of the 1991 economic reforms, the Tenth Plan recognized that states would play a pivotal role in spearheading further economic reforms This shift acknowledged the importance of decentralized policy initiatives and the active participation of state governments in driving economic growth",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "centre",
    "option_b": "states",
    "option_c": "private sector",
    "option_d": "World Bank",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130129,
    "question": "When were state-level monitorable targets first initiated?",
    "answer": "Tenth Plan period",
    "explanation": "State-level monitorable targets were introduced for the first time during the Tenth Five Year Plan period (2002-07) This approach aimed to enhance the effectiveness of planning by setting specific and measurable targets at the state level, aligning development efforts with outcomes",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Eighth Plan Period",
    "option_b": "Ninth Plan Period",
    "option_c": "Tenth Plan period",
    "option_d": "Eleventh Plan Period",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130130,
    "question": "When was the first Result Framework Document (RFD) introduced?",
    "answer": 2010,
    "explanation": "The first Result Framework Document (RFD) was introduced in the year 2010 as part of the Eleventh Five Year Plan The RFD aimed to enhance accountability, transparency, and performance assessment in government departments by setting measurable targets and monitoring outcomes",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": 2005,
    "option_b": 2008,
    "option_c": 2010,
    "option_d": 2012,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130131,
    "question": "The Tenth Plan adopted differential development strategies based on which fact?",
    "answer": "States have differing potential and constraints",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Plan's adoption of differential development strategies was driven by the recognition that states possess varying potential and constraints This approach aimed to tailor development plans to the specific needs and challenges faced by each state, promoting more inclusive and targeted growth",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Political party in power",
    "option_b": "Varying literacy rates",
    "option_c": "States have differing potential and constraints",
    "option_d": "Availability of natural resources",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130132,
    "question": "How does the differential development strategy benefit states?\n1 Addresses state-specific issues \n2 Allows customized policymaking\n3 Channelizes resources based on needs \n4 Promotes competitive federalism",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "The differential development strategy brings multiple benefits to states By addressing state-specific issues, enabling customized policymaking, and channelizing resources based on local needs, this approach fosters balanced and regionally tailored development Additionally, it promotes healthy competitive federalism among states to achieve optimal growth outcomes",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130133,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): The PC monitored central ministries' policy initiatives during Tenth Plan \n\nReason (R): To align ministry actions with national planning goals",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Plan focused on aligning central ministries' policy initiatives with national planning goals by monitoring their progress This approach aimed to ensure that ministry actions were in sync with the broader development agenda outlined by the plan",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130134,
    "question": "When did steering committees start aligning Five Year Plans with economic reforms?",
    "answer": "Ninth Plan period",
    "explanation": "Steering committees were established to align Five Year Plans with economic reforms starting from the Ninth Plan period (1997-2002) These committees played a critical role in integrating economic liberalization measures and strategic planning to achieve sustainable and balanced growth",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Eighth Plan Period",
    "option_b": "Ninth Plan period",
    "option_c": "Tenth Plan Period",
    "option_d": "Eleventh Plan Period",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130135,
    "question": "The Tenth Five Year Plan has been called a _________ plan",
    "answer": "reform plan",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Five Year Plan earned the moniker of a \"reform plan\" due to its emphasis on introducing structural changes and policy reforms rather than focusing solely on resource allocation This approach aimed to modernize planning practices and align them with dynamic economic conditions",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "re,fo,rm p,l,an",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130136,
    "question": "How did the Tenth Five Year Plan try to reform planning?\n1 Emphasized monitorable targets \n2 Focused on outcomes over outlays \n3 Aligned central ministries \n4 Set up steering committees on reforms",
    "answer": "All of the above",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Plan undertook a comprehensive approach to reforming the planning process It emphasized monitorable targets for results-oriented planning, focused on outcomes over outlays, aligned central ministries to development goals, and established steering committees to drive policy reforms This multifaceted approach aimed to enhance planning effectiveness and accountability",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 2",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130137,
    "question": "The Tenth Plan initiated state-level monitorable targets to promote which objective?\n1 Competitive federalism \n2 Bottom-up planning \n3 Quality control \n4 Accountability",
    "answer": "2 and 4",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Plan introduced state-level monitorable targets with the dual purpose of enabling bottom-up planning and enhancing accountability By setting specific targets at the state level, the plan aimed to empower states to tailor their development strategies while also promoting greater accountability and transparency in achieving those goals",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 3",
    "option_b": "2 and 4",
    "option_c": "3 and 4",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130138,
    "question": "The Tenth Plan emphasised the need for flexibility in planning Comment on the statement",
    "answer": "TRUE",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Plan recognized the intricate and rapidly changing nature of economic, social, and technological landscapes In response, it indeed emphasized the necessity for flexible planning approaches The plan aimed to depart from rigid, one-size-fits-all strategies and adopt adaptive measures that could respond effectively to emerging challenges and opportunities This approach enabled policymakers to make timely adjustments and optimize resource allocation to align with evolving circumstances By advocating for flexibility, the Tenth Plan sought to enhance the resilience and relevance of planning in an ever-changing environment",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "TRUE",
    "option_b": "FALSE",
    "option_c": "Partially True",
    "option_d": "Partially False",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130139,
    "question": "The Tenth Plan focused on outcomes rather than just outlays to promote which objective?",
    "answer": "Results-orientation",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Plan underwent a significant shift in its approach, prioritizing outcomes over traditional input-oriented outlays By embracing a results-oriented strategy, the plan aimed to ensure that the allocation of resources translated into meaningful and impactful outcomes This approach involved setting clear and measurable targets that addressed key socio-economic challenges It promoted a more efficient use of resources by focusing on achieving specific developmental goals rather than merely channeling funds into projects without considering the actual impact This transition to results-orientation aimed to enhance the effectiveness, transparency, and accountability of developmental initiatives, ultimately contributing to more tangible improvements in the quality of life for citizens and the overall progress of the nation",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Political consensus",
    "option_b": "Funds utilization",
    "option_c": "Results-orientation",
    "option_d": "Public accountability",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130140,
    "question": "The Twelfth Five Year Plan set national monitorable targets across how many broad areas?",
    "answer": 11,
    "explanation": "The Twelfth Plan outlined national monitorable targets across 11 broad areas including growth, poverty, education, etc",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": 11,
    "option_b": 10,
    "option_c": 8,
    "option_d": 12,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130141,
    "question": "What target of financial inclusion was included in Twelfth Plan monitorable targets?",
    "answer": "Providing access to banking for 90% Indian households",
    "explanation": "Providing banking access to 90% households was a Twelfth Plan monitorable target for financial inclusion",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Providing access to banking for 85% Indian households",
    "option_b": "Providing access to banking for 90% Indian households",
    "option_c": "Providing access to banking for 95% Indian households",
    "option_d": "Providing access to banking for 75% Indian households",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130142,
    "question": "The Twelfth Plan targeted an economic growth rate of how many percentage",
    "answer": "8 percent",
    "explanation": "The Twelfth Five Year Plan targeted an average annual economic growth rate of 8%",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "8 percent",
    "option_b": "75 percent",
    "option_c": "85 percent",
    "option_d": "7 percent",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130143,
    "question": "Which sector was targeted to grow at 10% per annum during the Twelfth Five Year Plan period?",
    "answer": "Manufacturing",
    "explanation": "The Twelfth Plan set a target manufacturing growth rate of 10% per year",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Agriculture",
    "option_b": "Manufacturing",
    "option_c": "Services",
    "option_d": "Infrastructure",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130144,
    "question": "What was the monitorable target for poverty reduction under the Twelfth Five Year Plan?\n1 5 percentage points \n2 10 percentage points \n3 15 percentage points \n4 20 percentage points",
    "answer": "Only 2",
    "explanation": "The Twelfth Plan aimed to reduce poverty ratio by 10 percentage points compared to previous estimates",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 2",
    "option_b": "Only 3",
    "option_c": "Only 2",
    "option_d": "Only 1",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130145,
    "question": "What skill development target was outlined in the Twelfth Five Year Plan?\n1 Create 50 million new non-farm jobs \n2 Certify skills of 50 million people \n3 Train 1 crore youth annually \n4 Ensure minimum skills for all school graduates",
    "answer": "1 and 2",
    "explanation": "The Twelfth Plan aimed to create 50 million new non-farm jobs and certify an equivalent number in skills",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 3",
    "option_b": "2 and 4",
    "option_c": "1 and 2",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130146,
    "question": "What mean years of schooling did the Twelfth Plan target by 2017?",
    "answer": 7,
    "explanation": "Increasing mean years of schooling to 7 was a Twelfth Plan education monitorable target",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": 5,
    "option_b": 6,
    "option_c": 7,
    "option_d": 8,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130147,
    "question": "The Twelfth Plan aimed to enhance access to higher education by creating ________ additional seats",
    "answer": "2 million",
    "explanation": "The monitorable target was enhancing access to higher education by creating 2 million additional seats",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 million",
    "option_b": "15 million",
    "option_c": "2 million",
    "option_d": "25 million",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130148,
    "question": "What was the Infant Mortality Rate target under the Twelfth Five Year Plan?",
    "answer": "25 per 1000 live births",
    "explanation": "The IMR target was to reduce it to 25 by the end of Twelfth Plan",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "20 per 1000 live births",
    "option_b": "25 per 1000 live births",
    "option_c": "30 per 1000 live births",
    "option_d": "35 per 1000 live births",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130149,
    "question": "What Total Fertility Rate did the Twelfth Plan aim to achieve by 2017?",
    "answer": 21,
    "explanation": "The TFR monitorable target was reducing it to 21 by the end of the Twelfth Plan period",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": 18,
    "option_b": 2,
    "option_c": 21,
    "option_d": 22,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130150,
    "question": "The Twelfth Plan targeted increasing investment as a percentage of GDP to what %",
    "answer": "9%",
    "explanation": "Increasing investment to 9% of GDP was a Twelfth Plan infrastructure target",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "7%",
    "option_b": "8%",
    "option_c": "9%",
    "option_d": "10%",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130151,
    "question": "What was the irrigation development target under the Twelfth Five Year Plan?",
    "answer": "13 million hectares",
    "explanation": "The irrigation target was enhancing gross irrigated area from 90 to 103 million hectares",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "10 million hectares",
    "option_b": "12 million hectares",
    "option_c": "13 million hectares",
    "option_d": "15 million hectares",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130152,
    "question": "The Twelfth Plan aimed to provide electricity access to _____ villages",
    "answer": "Hundred percent of",
    "explanation": "Providing electricity to all villages was a monitorable target",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Hu,nd,red pe,rc,en,t of",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130153,
    "question": "What was the rural road connectivity target in the Twelfth Five Year Plan?",
    "answer": "Connect all villages with all-weather roads",
    "explanation": "The rural roads target was connecting all villages with all-weather roads",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Connect 50% of villages with all-weather roads",
    "option_b": "Connect 75% of villages with all-weather roads",
    "option_c": "Connect 90% of villages with all-weather roads",
    "option_d": "Connect all villages with all-weather roads",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130154,
    "question": "The Twelfth Plan aimed to increase the green cover by ____ million hectares annually",
    "answer": "one",
    "explanation": "Increasing green cover by 1 million hectares every year was the afforestation target",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "on,e,tw,o",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130155,
    "question": "How much renewable energy capacity addition was targeted in the Twelfth Five Year Plan?",
    "answer": "30,000 MW",
    "explanation": "Adding 30,000 MW renewable energy capacity was a monitorable target",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "20,000 MW",
    "option_b": "25,000 MW",
    "option_c": "30,000 MW",
    "option_d": "35,000 MW",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130156,
    "question": "What was the Twelfth Plan target for Direct Benefit Transfers?",
    "answer": "Major subsidies through DBT using Aadhar",
    "explanation": "The DBT target was delivering major subsidies through direct cash transfers using Aadhar",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "10% DBT",
    "option_b": "25% DBT",
    "option_c": "50% DBT",
    "option_d": "Major subsidies through DBT using Aadhar",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130157,
    "question": "What system did the Twelfth Plan propose to use for Direct Benefit Transfers?",
    "answer": "Aadhaar platform",
    "explanation": "The DBT target involved using the Aadhaar platform for direct cash transfers",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Multi-Level Planning to Health",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Jan Dhan Accounts",
    "option_b": "RUPAY Cards",
    "option_c": "Aadhaar platform",
    "option_d": "Mobile payments",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140101,
    "question": "What are some criticisms made against the perspective element in Indian planning?\n1 Lack of evaluation of previous plans \n2 Absence of long-term goals \n3 Data deficiencies \n4 Impact of federalism\nWhich of the statements are correct?",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "Several criticisms have been leveled against the perspective element in Indian planning: 1 Lack of evaluation of previous plans 2 Absence of long-term goals 3 Data deficiencies 4 Impact of federalism These critiques highlight the need for more comprehensive and strategic planning practices that address these concerns",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140102,
    "question": "How did the Tenth Five Year Plan try to address the perspective planning criticism?\n1 Set monitorable targets \n2 Outlined approach for Eleventh Plan \n3 Focused on outcomes over outlays \n4 Emphasized reforms\nWhich of the statements are correct?",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Five Year Plan embarked on a journey to tackle the criticism against perspective planning through a multi-pronged approach: 1 Set monitorable targets 2 Outlined approach for Eleventh Plan 3 Focused on outcomes over outlays 4 Emphasized reforms By incorporating these strategies, the Tenth Plan aimed to enhance the effectiveness and strategic alignment of planning initiatives",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140103,
    "question": "When was the National Statistical Commission set up to improve data for planning?",
    "answer": 2000,
    "explanation": "The establishment of the National Statistical Commission in the year 2000 marked a pivotal step in addressing data deficiencies that were adversely affecting the perspective planning process in India The Commission played a crucial role in improving the quality and reliability of statistical data, a cornerstone of effective planning",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": 1990,
    "option_b": 1995,
    "option_c": 2000,
    "option_d": 2005,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140104,
    "question": "What reforms aimed to add evaluation to the planning process?",
    "answer": "Quarterly review and performance budgeting",
    "explanation": "A series of reforms were introduced to bolster the evaluation component within the planning process: 1 Tax reforms 2 Disinvestment 3 Quarterly review and performance budgeting 4 Fiscal consolidation These reforms collectively aimed to enhance the scrutiny of planning initiatives and improve their efficiency and outcomes",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Tax reforms",
    "option_b": "Disinvestment",
    "option_c": "Quarterly review and performance budgeting",
    "option_d": "Fiscal consolidation",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140105,
    "question": "How did actual allocation of plan funds to states differ from theoretical allocation?\n1 Influence of political factors on actual allocation \n2 Economically backward states receiving more funds \n3 Allocation guided by alignment with Central priorities\nWhich of the statements are correct?",
    "answer": "1 and 3",
    "explanation": "The actual allocation of plan funds to states often diverged from the theoretical framework due to dynamic factors: 1 Influence of political factors on actual allocation 2 Economically backward states receiving more funds 3 Allocation guided by alignment with Central priorities These real-world considerations introduced complexities that influenced resource distribution beyond the theoretical ideal, impacting developmental outcomes",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 2",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140106,
    "question": "What strategies were adopted to address regional imbalance in development?\n1 Prioritize backward regions for Central investments \n2 Differentiate development strategies based on state needs \n3 Incentivize private investment in lagging regions \n4 Provide incentives for states' fiscal reforms\nWhich of the above are correct statements?",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "Steps like prioritizing backward regions, differentiated strategies and attracting private investment targeted regional disparities",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140107,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): Planning in India has been overly centralized \n\nReason (R): Centralization increased after Nehru's death",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A Centralization of planning increased after Nehru's demise as opposed to his emphasis on cooperative federalism",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140108,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): The 73rd and 74th amendments promoted decentralized planning\n \nReason (R): They empowered local governments constitutionally",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A By providing constitutional mandate to panchayats and municipalities, the amendments enabled decentralized grassroots planning",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140109,
    "question": "Earlier plans focused on _________ employment compared to self-employment",
    "answer": "wage",
    "explanation": "Earlier plans prioritized wage employment in industries rather than self-employment",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "wa,ge",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140110,
    "question": "Reforms era planning shifted emphasis to _________ for employment generation",
    "answer": "self-employment",
    "explanation": "Reform era planning focused on promoting self-employment unlike earlier wage employment approach",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "sel,f-e,mpl,oy,me,nt",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140111,
    "question": "The _____ amended the Industries (Development & Regulation) Act, 1951 enabling privatization of PSUs",
    "answer": "New Industrial Policy 1991",
    "explanation": "The New Industrial Policy of 1991 amended the ID&R Act of 1951 to enable privatization of PSUs",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Ne,w In,du,st,ri,al P,oli,cy 1,9,91",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140112,
    "question": "What led to excessive government control and dominance of PSUs in the Indian economy over time?",
    "answer": "Planning priorities and industrial policies",
    "explanation": "Planning emphasis on PSUs driven by Mahalanobis model and industrial policies led to excessive government control",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Socialist ideology",
    "option_b": "Lack of private capital",
    "option_c": "Planning priorities and industrial policies",
    "option_d": "Risk averse bureaucracy",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140113,
    "question": "Agriculture was overshadowed due to excessive focus on _________ in Indian planning",
    "answer": "industrialization",
    "explanation": "Excessive prioritization of industrialization led agriculture being overshadowed in early planning",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "in,du,st,ri,al,iz,at,ion",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140114,
    "question": "Match the following consequences of neglect of agriculture sector with the planning goals impacted: \n\nList 1 (Consequences)\nA Food insecurity \nB Low rural incomes and demand \nC Market failure\n\nList 2 (Goals impacted)\ni Growth \nii Equity \niii Self-reliance",
    "answer": "A - iii B - ii C - i",
    "explanation": "Neglect of agriculture led to outcomes like food insecurity, low rural demand and market failure impeding planning goals",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "A - i B - ii C - iii",
    "option_b": "A - ii B - iii <C - i",
    "option_c": "A - iii B - ii C - i",
    "option_d": "None of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140115,
    "question": "Setting up industries in backward regions without adequate infra development led to:",
    "answer": "Under-utilization of industries' potential",
    "explanation": "Establishing industries in backward regions without infra development led to under-utilization of potential",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Rise in regional disparities",
    "option_b": "Under-utilization of industries' potential",
    "option_c": "Industrialization of backward regions",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140116,
    "question": "Lack of skilled labour in backward regions was a consequence of faulty industrial location policy Comment",
    "answer": "TRUE",
    "explanation": "Lack of skilled labour arose in backward region industries due to lack of human capital development",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "TRUE",
    "option_b": "FALSE",
    "option_c": "Partially True",
    "option_d": "Partially False",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140117,
    "question": "Which of the following resulted from excessive government control of finances to fund plans? \n1 Crowding out of private investment \n2 High tax evasion \n3 Slow technological progress \n4 High inflation\nWhich of the statements are correct?",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "Government's financial dominance led to outcomes like crowding out of private sector, tax evasion and slow technology adoption",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140118,
    "question": "Which act empowered states to borrow without Centre's approval to finance state plans",
    "answer": "Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Act",
    "explanation": "The FRBM Act of 2003 allowed states to borrow without Centre's approval for financing state plans",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Planning Commission Act",
    "option_b": "Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Act",
    "option_c": "Financial Management Act",
    "option_d": "Finance Commission Act",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140119,
    "question": "Democratic _________ led to political interference in early planning",
    "answer": "immaturity",
    "explanation": "India's democratic immaturity in early years led to political interference in planning",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "im,ma,tu,ri,ty",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140120,
    "question": "_______ of the planning process caused distortions like regional imbalances",
    "answer": "Politicisation",
    "explanation": "Politicization of planning led to distortions instead of reducing regional economic disparities",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Po,li,ti,ci,sa,ti,on",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140121,
    "question": "When did the government adopt a conscious policy towards inclusive growth?",
    "answer": "2000-01",
    "explanation": "The government adopted a conscious inclusive growth policy in 2000-01 based on a review of economic reforms",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "1999-00",
    "option_b": "1991-92",
    "option_c": "1993-94",
    "option_d": "2000-01",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140122,
    "question": "Inclusive growth was a key focus in which Five Year Plan?",
    "answer": "Eleventh Plan",
    "explanation": "The Eleventh Plan (2007-12) focused on inclusive growth as an objective",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Ninth Plan",
    "option_b": "Tenth Plan",
    "option_c": "Eleventh Plan",
    "option_d": "Twelfth Plan",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140123,
    "question": "Which schemes aim to provide basic amenities to target population? \n1 Employment generation programs \n2 Food security programs \n3 Housing and sanitation schemes \n4 Skill development initiatives",
    "answer": "2, 3 and 4",
    "explanation": "Government schemes on food, housing, sanitation etc aim to provide basic amenities to disadvantaged sections",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "1 and 2",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "2, 3 and 4",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140124,
    "question": "Short-term policy for inclusive growth relies heavily on _______",
    "answer": "subsidies",
    "explanation": "Short-term inclusion policy uses subsidies but has fiscal sustainability issues",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "su,bs,id,ies",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140125,
    "question": "What does the long-term inclusive growth policy focus on? \n1 Employment generation \n2 Poverty alleviation \n3 Education and skill development \n4 Subsidies and incentives",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "Long-term policy focuses on self-reliance through employment, poverty alleviation and education/skills",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140126,
    "question": "Skill development initiatives were launched to promote ________",
    "answer": "self-reliance",
    "explanation": "Skill development equips people for self-employment and self-reliance",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "sel,f-re,li,an,ce",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140127,
    "question": "Consider the following codes and answer accordingly:\nAssertion (A): Resource mobilization involves channeling resources towards planned development goals\n \nReason (R): It encompasses government revenue, spending and investment policies",
    "answer": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "explanation": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A Resource mobilization uses fiscal policies to direct resources towards planned development objectives",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation for A",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation for A",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "A is false but R is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140128,
    "question": "Planning Commission was responsible for resource mobilization for ____________ \n1 Centre's plan schemes \n2 State plans \n3 Private sector requirements \n4 Public welfare spending",
    "answer": "1 and 2",
    "explanation": "Planning Commission mobilized resources for Centre's and states' Five Year Plan schemes",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "1 and 3",
    "option_b": "1 and 4",
    "option_c": "1 and 2",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140129,
    "question": "Fiscal consolidation was initiated to reduce government _______ and enable private sector resource mobilization",
    "answer": "deficit",
    "explanation": "Fiscal consolidation reduced government deficit to allow private sector access to finances",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "de,fi,cit",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140130,
    "question": "FRBM Act, 2003 aimed to provide states greater autonomy in ________",
    "answer": "borrowing",
    "explanation": "FRBM Act empowered states to borrow without Centre's approval for state plans",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "bor,ro,wi,ng",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140131,
    "question": "What is the primary aim of Goods and Service Tax (GST)?",
    "answer": "enhance states' revenue capacity",
    "explanation": "GST aims to enhance states' internal revenue capacity for resource mobilization",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "reduce inflation",
    "option_b": "simplify taxation",
    "option_c": "increase exports",
    "option_d": "enhance states' revenue capacity",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140132,
    "question": "Match the following terms related to government finances with their implications: \n\nList 1 \nA Revenue deficit\nB Fiscal deficit \nC Primary deficit \n\nList 2\ni Interest payments burden \nii Borrowings exceed revenue \niii Regular spending exceeds revenue",
    "answer": "A - iii B - ii C - i",
    "explanation": "Key metrics like revenue deficit, fiscal deficit and primary deficit have specific implications for government finances",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "A - ii B - iii C - i",
    "option_b": "A - i B - iiC - iii",
    "option_c": "A - iii B - ii C - i",
    "option_d": "None of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140133,
    "question": "Investment models refer to ________ used to mobilize resources for planned development",
    "answer": "means and tools",
    "explanation": "Investment models denote the means and tools used to mobilize resources for planned development",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "mea,ns a,nd to,o,ls",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140134,
    "question": "Who was the main investor in the economy during the Phase I investment model (1951-69)?",
    "answer": "Government",
    "explanation": "Phase I followed a state-led model with government as the primary investor",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Private sector",
    "option_b": "Foreign investors",
    "option_c": "Government",
    "option_d": "All were equal investors",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140135,
    "question": "Phase I resource mobilization relied heavily on which of the following?",
    "answer": "taxes and deficit financing",
    "explanation": "Phase I relied majorly on tax revenues and deficit financing to fund plans",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "foreign aid",
    "option_b": "taxes and deficit financing",
    "option_c": "PSU profits",
    "option_d": "private profits",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140136,
    "question": "What were some consequences of the Phase I investment model? \n1 Industrialization but infra gaps \n2 Dominance of public sector \n3 Lag between fund needs and mobilization \n4 High inflation\nWhich of the above are correct statements:",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "Phase I led to outcomes like industrialization amidst infra gaps, PSU dominance and funding lag",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_c": "2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140137,
    "question": "Joint sector model allowed private participation in which areas during the Phase II?",
    "answer": "Areas open to private sector",
    "explanation": "Phase II allowed private participation in industries already open to private sector",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Areas open to private sector",
    "option_b": "Areas open to government sector",
    "option_c": "Both of the above",
    "option_d": "None of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140138,
    "question": "Which act regulated foreign collaboration and FDI during Phase III of investment model?",
    "answer": "FERA",
    "explanation": "Phase III allowed limited foreign collaboration but FDI was restricted under FERA",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "FEMA",
    "option_b": "IDRA",
    "option_c": "FERA",
    "option_d": "FIIA",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140139,
    "question": "What major limitation did FERA place on foreign collaboration during Phase III?",
    "answer": "Limited to sectors open to private sector",
    "explanation": "FERA restricted foreign tie-ups to sectors already open to private Indian companies",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Limited to sectors open to private sector",
    "option_b": "Limited to sectors open to government sector",
    "option_c": "Both of the above",
    "option_d": "None of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 140140,
    "question": "Phase III investment model did not allow India to benefit from: \n1 Foreign capital \n2 Modern technology \n3 Managerial expertise \n4 Economies of scale\nWhich of the above are correct:",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "Restrictive Phase III model prevented tapping of foreign capital, technology and expertise",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> A Critical Evaluation to Phase-IV (1991 onward)",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150101,
    "question": "Central sector schemes are ________ funded by the Centre",
    "answer": "fully",
    "explanation": "Central sector schemes are fully funded by the Union government",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "ful,ly",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150102,
    "question": "Centrally sponsored schemes involve ________ funding from Centre and states",
    "answer": "shared",
    "explanation": "CSS involve shared funding between Centre and states",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "sh,ar,ed",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150103,
    "question": "Which type of schemes flow funds through state budgets?",
    "answer": "Centrally sponsored schemes",
    "explanation": "CSS funds flow through state budgets unlike direct Central sector scheme funds",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Centrally sponsored schemes",
    "option_b": "Central and State sponsored schemes",
    "option_c": "PSU sponsored schemes",
    "option_d": "None of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150104,
    "question": "Consider the statement: Centrally sponsored schemes aim to encourage states to prioritize key national focus areas",
    "answer": "TRUE",
    "explanation": "CSS encourage states to prioritize key national development focus areas",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "TRUE",
    "option_b": "FALSE",
    "option_c": "Partially True",
    "option_d": "Partially False",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150105,
    "question": "Normal Central Assistance to states is determined based on the ________",
    "answer": "Gadgil-Mukherjee formula",
    "explanation": "Normal Central Assistance is allocated to states based on the Gadgil-Mukherjee formula",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Ga,dg,il-M,ukh,er,je,e fo,rm,ula",
    "option_b": "",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "fillup"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150106,
    "question": "Additional Central Assistance is provided for which type of projects?",
    "answer": "Externally aided",
    "explanation": "Additional Central Assistance funds Externally Aided Projects",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "CSS",
    "option_b": "CPSU",
    "option_c": "Externally aided",
    "option_d": "None of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150107,
    "question": "Special Central Assistance is given to which category of states?",
    "answer": "Special category",
    "explanation": "Special Central Assistance is provided to Special Category States",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "general category",
    "option_b": "Special category",
    "option_c": "large",
    "option_d": "small",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150108,
    "question": "MPLADS funds provided to states are a form of what type of assistance?",
    "answer": "Central assistance",
    "explanation": "MPLADS funds constitute Central assistance for development",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Central assistance",
    "option_b": "State Assistance",
    "option_c": "Private Assistance",
    "option_d": "None of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150109,
    "question": "What else are Restructured CSS divided apart from optional schemes?",
    "answer": "core",
    "explanation": "CSS are bifurcated into core and optional schemes after restructuring",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "general",
    "option_b": "core",
    "option_c": "supplementary",
    "option_d": "None of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150110,
    "question": "What is the funding pattern proposed for core CSS?",
    "answer": "60:40 for general states",
    "explanation": "Core CSS have 60:40 funding between Centre and general category states",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "50:50 for general states",
    "option_b": "60:40 for general states",
    "option_c": "40:60 for general states",
    "option_d": "None of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150111,
    "question": "In the context of optional CSS restructuring, what mechanism empowers states with fiscal flexibility to allocate funds between schemes?",
    "answer": "Portability of budgetary allocations",
    "explanation": "States are endowed with the prerogative to transfer budgetary allocations between various schemes under optional CSS restructuring through the concept of portability This innovative approach enhances their financial autonomy and strategic allocation capability",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Fiscal reallocation",
    "option_b": "Budgetary decentralization",
    "option_c": "Fiscal autonomy",
    "option_d": "Portability of budgetary allocations",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150112,
    "question": "When was the Independent Evaluation Office (IEO) set up?",
    "answer": 2014,
    "explanation": "The IEO was established by the government in February 2014",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": 2012,
    "option_b": 2013,
    "option_c": 2014,
    "option_d": 2015,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150113,
    "question": "The IEO was set up based on experiences from which of the following countries \n1 Mexico \n2 UK \n3 USA \n4 World Bank\nWhich of the above are correct:",
    "answer": "2 and 4",
    "explanation": "The IEO was modeled on Mexico's evaluation office and set up with aid from UK and World Bank",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 3",
    "option_b": "1 and 4",
    "option_c": "2 and 4",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150114,
    "question": "What is the role of the IEO? \n1 Evaluate government programs \n2 Improve accountability \n3 Guide evaluation methodologies \n4 Build evaluation capabilities\nWhich of the above are correct statements:",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "The IEO evaluates programs, guides methodologies and improves accountability",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150115,
    "question": "The year 1952 marked a significant milestone with the establishment of the Programme Evaluation Organisation (PEO), which played a crucial role in India's governance landscape by fulfilling which purpose?",
    "answer": "Systematic evaluation of programs",
    "explanation": "In 1952, the Programme Evaluation Organisation (PEO) was founded, signaling a key step toward evidence-based governance, enabling systematic evaluation of government programs to enhance their efficiency and effectiveness",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Improved financial management",
    "option_b": "Systematic evaluation of programs",
    "option_c": "Effective resource allocation",
    "option_d": "Administrative decentralization",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150116,
    "question": "Alongside evaluating programs for ministries, the Programme Evaluation Organisation (PEO) also undertook evaluations for which strategic entity?",
    "answer": "Planning Commission",
    "explanation": "The Programme Evaluation Organisation (PEO) played a crucial role in evaluating programs for ministries and the Planning Commission, thereby contributing to a comprehensive assessment of policies and initiatives across various sectors",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Planning Commission",
    "option_b": "Finance Commission",
    "option_c": "Economic Commission",
    "option_d": "Development Commission",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150117,
    "question": "The Programme Evaluation Organisation (PEO) adopts a multi-tiered structure to fulfill its objectives How many main structures does the PEO's organizational framework encompass?",
    "answer": 3,
    "explanation": "The Programme Evaluation Organisation (PEO) features a comprehensive organizational framework comprising three main structures: headquarters, regional offices, and field units, facilitating effective evaluation processes at different administrative levels",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": 2,
    "option_b": 3,
    "option_c": 4,
    "option_d": 5,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150118,
    "question": "The Programme Evaluation Organisation (PEO) extends its reach through field units situated in various states In how many major states across India are these field units located?",
    "answer": 8,
    "explanation": "The Programme Evaluation Organisation (PEO) has established field units in 8 significant states across India, strategically positioning itself to conduct thorough evaluations and capture diverse regional perspectives",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": 5,
    "option_b": 6,
    "option_c": 8,
    "option_d": 10,
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150119,
    "question": "The Programme Evaluation Organisation (PEO) enhances its nationwide presence through regional evaluation offices How many such regional evaluation offices does the PEO operate?",
    "answer": "7 cities",
    "explanation": "The Programme Evaluation Organisation (PEO) functions through 7 regional evaluation offices, spread across key locations in India, facilitating comprehensive program assessments and generating valuable insights",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "7 cities",
    "option_b": "3 cities",
    "option_c": "4 cities",
    "option_d": "8 cities",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150120,
    "question": "In alignment with the Tenth Plan's perspective, evaluation was proposed to be integrated into which broad framework to enhance the efficacy of development initiatives?",
    "answer": "plan scheme",
    "explanation": "The Tenth Plan emphasized the amalgamation of evaluation into the plan scheme, thereby embedding systematic evaluation practices into India's development strategy to ensure the efficacy and outcomes of various developmental projects",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "plan scheme",
    "option_b": "finance scheme",
    "option_c": "development scheme",
    "option_d": "None of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150121,
    "question": "A specialized evaluation scheme was formulated to enhance which specific aspect of government operations?",
    "answer": "evaluation capabilities",
    "explanation": "The creation of a dedicated evaluation scheme aimed to bolster evaluation capabilities signifies the emphasis on improving the government's capacity to conduct comprehensive and effective evaluations of various programs and policies",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "accountability",
    "option_b": "transparency",
    "option_c": "funds allocation",
    "option_d": "evaluation capabilities",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150122,
    "question": "Which key institution was succeeded by the formation of NITI Aayog in 2015, heralding a paradigm shift in India's planning and governance landscape?",
    "answer": "Planning Commission",
    "explanation": "The establishment of NITI Aayog in 2015 marked the replacement of the erstwhile Planning Commission, signifying a departure from the traditional planning approach to a more collaborative and dynamic model of governance",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Finance Commission",
    "option_b": "NDC",
    "option_c": "Planning Commission",
    "option_d": "Administrative Commission",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150123,
    "question": "NITI Aayog, a transformative institution, aligns its focus with the changing needs of which evolving facet of India?",
    "answer": "New India",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog is dedicated to catering to the dynamic and evolving requirements of the transformed New India, emphasizing innovation, inclusivity, and sustainable development",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Modern India",
    "option_b": "Developed India",
    "option_c": "Emerging India",
    "option_d": "New India",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150124,
    "question": "NITI Aayog has been bestowed with a distinctive role, being described as the \"best friend\" of which crucial entities within India's governance structure?",
    "answer": "States",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog's mandate involves acting as the \"best friend\" to States at the Centre, thereby fostering cooperation, collaboration, and effective policy coordination between the central and state governments",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Central Government",
    "option_b": "States",
    "option_c": "Bureaucracy",
    "option_d": "Corporate Entities",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150125,
    "question": "Who holds the de facto position of Chairman in NITI Aayog, playing a pivotal role in guiding the institution's vision and strategic direction?",
    "answer": "Prime Minister",
    "explanation": "The Prime Minister occupies the de facto role of Chairman in NITI Aayog, signifying the leadership's active involvement in shaping and steering the institution's agenda",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "President",
    "option_b": "Prime Minister",
    "option_c": "Finance Minister",
    "option_d": "Chief Justice",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150126,
    "question": "NITI Aayog envisions the transformation of India into a knowledge-intensive and innovative society, thereby propelling it towards which direction?",
    "answer": "knowledge economy",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog's vision is centered on propelling India towards becoming a knowledge-based economy and society, fostering innovation, research, and technological advancements",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "industrialized economy",
    "option_b": "agrarian economy",
    "option_c": "service-based economy",
    "option_d": "knowledge economy",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150127,
    "question": "NITI Aayog promotes a framework that encourages cooperative and competitive dynamics between the central and state governments This framework is known as:",
    "answer": "federalism",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog's approach to fostering collaboration and competition between the central and state governments is referred to as cooperative federalism, emphasizing shared governance and coordinated decision-making",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "funding",
    "option_b": "planning",
    "option_c": "evaluation",
    "option_d": "federalism",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150128,
    "question": "NITI Aayog holds the official designation of being a specialized entity What term best describes the unique role of NITI Aayog in India's governance landscape?",
    "answer": "Think Tank",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog functions as a dedicated government Think Tank, actively engaged in research, policy formulation, and knowledge dissemination, contributing to informed decision-making",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Action Unit",
    "option_b": "Research Foundation",
    "option_c": "Strategy Center",
    "option_d": "Think Tank",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150129,
    "question": "NITI Aayog's primary focus centers around facilitating the implementation of which core element of governance, thereby ensuring effective policy execution?",
    "answer": "Implementation",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog's primary role is to facilitate the smooth implementation of policies, programs, and initiatives, ensuring that the envisioned goals are translated into concrete actions and outcomes",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Innovation",
    "option_b": "Planning",
    "option_c": "Implementation",
    "option_d": "Regulation",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150130,
    "question": "Identify the demographic changes facing India's planning since Independence:\n1 Population growth to over 1 billion\n2 Increased urbanization\n3 Large youth population\n4 Lower mortality rates\nWhich of the above are correct statements:",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "India's population has grown over 3x, urbanization increased and youth populace expanded",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150131,
    "question": "India's Gross Domestic Product (GDP) has witnessed substantial growth since independence, surging from Rs 10,000 crore to exceed what amount in crore?",
    "answer": "100 lakh crore",
    "explanation": "India's GDP has demonstrated remarkable growth, escalating from Rs 10,000 crore to surpass the monumental benchmark of Rs 100 lakh crore, reflecting the nation's economic progress",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 lakh crore",
    "option_b": "10 lakh crore",
    "option_c": "50 lakh crore",
    "option_d": "100 lakh crore",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150132,
    "question": "The Evolution of the private sector, characterized by significant expansion and global competitiveness, necessitates the adoption of new planning strategies to effectively address which emerging challenge?",
    "answer": "Policy approaches",
    "explanation": "The transformation of the private sector, marked by its substantial growth and enhanced global competitiveness, has prompted the need for novel policy approaches that can cater to the evolving landscape of economic activities and industries",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Technological advancements",
    "option_b": "Social equity",
    "option_c": "Environmental sustainability",
    "option_d": "Policy approaches",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150133,
    "question": "The burgeoning aspirations of citizens emphasize the demand for a greater focus on which key aspect of governance, prompting a shift in the approach to policy formulation and implementation?",
    "answer": "Focus on outcomes and results",
    "explanation": "The rising aspirations of citizens underscore the importance of placing a greater emphasis on the actual outcomes and results of policies and initiatives, necessitating a shift from traditional input-based approaches",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Resource allocation",
    "option_b": "Administrative efficiency",
    "option_c": "Focus on outputs",
    "option_d": "Focus on outcomes and results",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150134,
    "question": "Mahatma Gandhi's wisdom regarding the Evolution of institutions in response to changing times has been cited as a guiding principle for the transformation of which key institution in India's governance framework?",
    "answer": "Planning Commission",
    "explanation": "Quoting Mahatma Gandhi, the government highlighted the need for institutions to evolve with changing times, particularly in the context of replacing the Planning Commission with NITI Aayog, reflecting the dynamism of governance",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Finance Commission",
    "option_b": "Parliament",
    "option_c": "President",
    "option_d": "Planning Commission",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150135,
    "question": "NITI Aayog assumes an active role in enhancing the capacity of state governments by providing specialized support in which domain, ultimately contributing to their efficient governance?",
    "answer": "Consultancy",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog extends consultancy support to state governments, enabling them to enhance their administrative capabilities, strategic planning, and effective implementation of policies and programs",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Financial management",
    "option_b": "Technological innovation",
    "option_c": "Infrastructure development",
    "option_d": "Consultancy",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150136,
    "question": "NITI Aayog's mandate involves promoting coordination and convergence across ministries and states in India This function serves to address which crucial aspect of governance?",
    "answer": "Policy coherence",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog's emphasis on facilitating coordination and convergence across ministries and states contributes to policy coherence, ensuring seamless integration of strategies and initiatives across diverse sectors",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Resource allocation",
    "option_b": "Policy coherence",
    "option_c": "Sectoral specialization",
    "option_d": "Administrative decentralization",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150137,
    "question": "NITI Aayog plays a pivotal role as a think tank by focusing on which strategic activities that aid in effective policy formulation and decision-making?",
    "answer": "Strategic planning and scenario analysis",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog's role as a think tank is underscored by its engagement in strategic planning and scenario analysis, which involve assessing potential outcomes and challenges to inform informed policy decisions",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Data collection and analysis",
    "option_b": "Ideological advocacy",
    "option_c": "Project implementation",
    "option_d": "Strategic planning and scenario analysis",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150138,
    "question": "NITI Aayog positions itself as a hub that gathers, disseminates, and promotes the adoption of what important governance aspect, thereby fostering improved administrative practices?",
    "answer": "Best practices",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog functions as a knowledge hub and repository of best practices in governance, facilitating the exchange of successful approaches and models that can enhance administrative efficiency",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Innovative solutions",
    "option_b": "Strategic planning",
    "option_c": "Financial management",
    "option_d": "Best practices",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150139,
    "question": "Among its diverse roles, NITI Aayog is particularly committed to facilitating the effective implementation of which critical aspect of governance, ensuring that policies translate into tangible outcomes?",
    "answer": "Implementation",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog's focus on facilitating policy implementation underscores its commitment to bridging the gap between policy formulation and actual execution, thereby ensuring the realization of envisioned goals and results",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Strategic planning",
    "option_b": "Resource allocation",
    "option_c": "Regulatory framework",
    "option_d": "Implementation",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150140,
    "question": "NITI Aayog envisions the establishment of a collaborative national platform termed what, aiming to foster collective efforts and shared governance for India's development?",
    "answer": "Team India",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog aims to establish the \"Team India\" Wing, which serves as a collaborative national platform, bringing together diverse stakeholders to contribute to India's development journey",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "India Connect",
    "option_b": "Collaborative Network",
    "option_c": "Synergy Central",
    "option_d": "Team India",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150141,
    "question": "NITI Aayog is guided by the vision of growth is which of the following: \n1 Equitable \n2 Inclusive \n3 Sustainable\nIdentify the correct vision:",
    "answer": "1, 2 and 3",
    "explanation": "NITI is guided by the vision of growth being equitable, inclusive and sustainable",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 2",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "1, 2 and 3",
    "option_d": "None",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150142,
    "question": "NITI Aayog's strategy of empowerment is rooted in the foundation of a specific value that acknowledges the significance of human dignity and self-respect Which concept encapsulates this value?",
    "answer": "Human dignity",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog's strategy of empowerment is founded on the principles of human dignity and self-respect, recognizing individuals as dignified agents of change and development",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Civic duty",
    "option_b": "Economic growth",
    "option_c": "Social justice",
    "option_d": "Human dignity",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150143,
    "question": "Who holds the authority to appoint the Vice Chairman of NITI Aayog, a significant leadership position that influences the institution's strategic direction?",
    "answer": "Prime Minister",
    "explanation": "The Vice Chairman of NITI Aayog is appointed by the Prime Minister, signifying the central government's active role in selecting a visionary leader to guide the institution",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "President",
    "option_b": "Prime Minister",
    "option_c": "Parliament",
    "option_d": "Chief Justice",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150144,
    "question": "The Governing Council of NITI Aayog comprises Chief Ministers and Lieutenant Governors, embodying the principles of which governance model that emphasizes cooperative governance between the central and state governments?",
    "answer": "Cooperative federalism",
    "explanation": "The Governing Council of NITI Aayog, consisting of Chief Ministers and Lieutenant Governors, embodies the spirit of cooperative federalism, fostering collaborative decision-making and shared governance",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Competitive federalism",
    "option_b": "Collaborative governance",
    "option_c": "Federal cooperation",
    "option_d": "Cooperative federalism",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150145,
    "question": "The appointment of members to NITI Aayog by the Prime Minister signifies a deliberate effort to ensure which key element of governance, aligning with the institution's strategic functions?",
    "answer": "Expertise infusion",
    "explanation": "The appointment of members to NITI Aayog by the Prime Minister underscores the intention to infuse diverse expertise and insights into the institution, promoting effective policy formulation and strategic guidance",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Decentralization",
    "option_b": "Bureaucratic control",
    "option_c": "Expertise infusion",
    "option_d": "Hierarchical structure",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150146,
    "question": "NITI Aayog's Research Wing is envisaged as an in-house think tank, emphasizing the institution's commitment to which crucial aspect of governance, involving informed policy formulation?",
    "answer": "Evidence-based decision-making",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog's Research Wing is designed as an in-house think tank, focusing on conducting evidence-based research and analysis to facilitate informed decision-making and policy formulation",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Data collection",
    "option_b": "Ideological advocacy",
    "option_c": "Public relations",
    "option_d": "Evidence-based decision-making",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150147,
    "question": "The Consultancy Wing of NITI Aayog aims to provide governments with expertise grounded in a specific approach that draws on what key characteristic of the market-driven system?",
    "answer": "Market-based expertise",
    "explanation": "The Consultancy Wing of NITI Aayog offers expertise that is rooted in a market-based approach, allowing governments to benefit from insights and strategies informed by market dynamics and trends",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Bureaucratic analysis",
    "option_b": "Technological innovation",
    "option_c": "Market-based expertise",
    "option_d": "Academic research",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150148,
    "question": "The Team India Wing of NITI Aayog is structured to include representatives from which two key entities, fostering collaboration and synergy in India's governance framework?",
    "answer": "States and ministries",
    "explanation": "The Team India Wing of NITI Aayog comprises representatives from both states and ministries, promoting cohesive decision-making and coordination between various tiers of governance",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Local authorities and civil society",
    "option_b": "Corporations and international organizations",
    "option_c": "States and ministries",
    "option_d": "Political parties and trade unions",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150149,
    "question": "The core vision of NITI Aayog revolves around the principles of good governance, characterized by transparency, efficiency, and which other crucial aspect that drives responsible governance?",
    "answer": "Accountability",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog's core vision emphasizes good governance, which encompasses principles of transparency, efficiency, and accountability, ensuring responsible and effective decision-making",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Innovation",
    "option_b": "Participation",
    "option_c": "Equity",
    "option_d": "Accountability",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150150,
    "question": "NITI Aayog's strategic deployment of technology aims to strengthen transparency and accountability across various dimensions of governance, aligning with which specific goals of the institution?",
    "answer": "3 and 4",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog strategically employs technology to enhance transparency and accountability, promoting informed decision-making and effective governance across various sectors and initiatives",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 2",
    "option_b": "2 and 4",
    "option_c": "3 and 4",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150151,
    "question": "Since its establishment, has NITI Aayog formulated any Five Year Plan, marking a shift in India's planning approach from the traditional periodic plans?",
    "answer": "No",
    "explanation": "NITI Aayog, unlike its predecessor, the Planning Commission, has not formulated any Five Year Plan since its establishment, reflecting a departure from the traditional planning model",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Yes",
    "option_b": "No",
    "option_c": "Not Applicable",
    "option_d": "Not specified",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150152,
    "question": "The proposal to replace Five Year Plans with a Medium Term Fiscal Framework (MTFF) aligns with NITI Aayog's commitment to which core principle of governance, fostering a more dynamic planning approach?",
    "answer": "Flexibility and adaptability",
    "explanation": "The proposal to replace Five Year Plans with a Medium Term Fiscal Framework (MTFF) underscores NITI Aayog's emphasis on flexibility and adaptability in planning, allowing for more responsive policy adjustments",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Long-term planning",
    "option_b": "Centralization",
    "option_c": "Technological innovation",
    "option_d": "Flexibility and adaptability",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 150153,
    "question": "Which bodies' role needs resolution under NITI Aayog? \n1 Finance Commission \n2 IEO \n3 PEO\n4 NDC\nWhich of the above are correct:",
    "answer": "2, 3 and 4",
    "explanation": "Role of bodies like IEO, PEO and NDC need resolution under NITI Aayog",
    "topic_name": "Poverty, Planning, Finance and Economic I Social Development >> Planning in India  >> Central Sector Schemes and Centrally Sponsored Schemes to Recent Developments",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "1 and 2",
    "option_b": "2 and 3",
    "option_c": "2, 3 and 4",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq"
  }
]